<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng"	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>The Garden of Eloquence (1593): Dedication</title>
<author>Henry Peacham.</author>

</titleStmt>
<extent/>
  <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
    <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
    <date>Perseus 3.0</date>
    <idno type="filename">sidney.defence.perseus-eng1.xml</idno>
    <availability>
      <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
    </availability>
  </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<title>The Garden of Eloquence (1593): Tropes</title>
<author>Henry Peacham</author>
<imprint>
<pubPlace>Delmar, New York 12054</pubPlace>
<publisher>Scholars' Facsimiles &amp; Reprints, Inc.</publisher>
<date>1977</date>
</imprint>
</monogr>

</biblStruct>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>

      <refsDecl n="CTS"><cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+).(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2']/tei:div[@n='$3'])"><p>This pointer pattern extracts act and scene and line.</p></cRefPattern><cRefPattern n="chapter" matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2'])"><p>This pointer pattern extracts book and chapter.</p></cRefPattern><cRefPattern n="book" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])"><p>This pointer pattern extracts book.</p></cRefPattern></refsDecl>

</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="eng">English</language>
<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
<language ident="deu">German</language>
<language ident="fra">French</language>
<language ident="ita">Italian</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc><change><ab>converted to EpiDoc</ab></change></revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text xml:lang="eng">
<body>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">

<ab type="opener">TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE SIR JOHN Puckering Knight, Lord keeper of
the great seale of England.</ab>

<p>Albeit (Right Honorable) it may seeme to some men at the first
sight, a matter importunate to interrupt your Lordships grave, deep,
and weightie considerations, sitting as you do at the sterne of the
commonwelth in these daies of danger, yet seeing the infimitie of our
mortall estate cannot possiblie indure to stand continually bent, no,
not in the contemplation of the most excellent subject, or matter of
greatest importance, May it therefore please your good Lordship (if
for no other cause yet) partly for your owne ease, release, and
recreation, and partly for patronage to poore and painfull studentes,
to lend your honorable view to those my simple labours, hoping that as
you are not wont either to close your eies, or stop your eares to the
meanest or the poorest, so your Lordship wil not refuse to spare some
time (when your leasure may best permit) to cast your eie uppon these
meane and simple frutes of my studies: The argument whereof albeit I
confesse it subject to the exceptions of many, and peradventure to the
reprehensions of some, which seeme to make a divorce betweene nature
and art, and a seperation betweene pollicie and humanitie: yet Cicero
being both a most excellent Orator and prudent politick, doth mightily
support, and defend it against all objections, as we may plainly see
in one short sentence of his (among many other tending to this
purpose) where he saith: Ut hominis decus est ingenium, sic ingenii
lumen, est eloquentia: <note place="marg" anchored="false">De claris
oratoribum.</note> that is, as wit is mans worship, or wisedome man
honor, so eloquence is the light and brightnesse of wisedome, in which
sentence, he both expresseth the singular praises of two most worthie
vertues, and also enforceth the necessitie, and commendeth the
utilitie of their excellent conjunction.  And true it is that if we
joine with this prudent Orator in a diligent inquisition and
contemplation of wisedome, and in a deliberate consideration of art,
we shal see that verified which he hath here affirmed.  For if we
enquire what wisedome is, we shall find that it is the knowledge of
divine and humane thinges, if whose gift it is, we shall find that it
is the knowledge of divine and humane thinges, if whose gift it is, we
shalbe certified, that it is the gift of God, if we consider the
inventions thereof they are woonderfull, if the works they are
infinit, if the frutes, they are in use sweete, in nature necessarie,
both for the search of truth and for the direction of humane life.
Brieflie this vertue is the loving &amp; provident mother of mankind,
whom shee nourisheth with the sweete milke of prosperitie, defendeth
against manifolde dangers, instructeth with her counsell, and
prefereth to the imperiall dominion over all earthly creatures: and
lest dissenting with himselfe, he should by his owne contention worke
his owne confusion: she deviseth lawes to support equitie, and
appointeth punishments to represse injurie, she inventeth the art and
skill of warre, to resist violence offending against peace, she
maintaineth the one, and directeth the other, and is the mightie
Empresse of them both.</p>

<p>Finallie, by her the true felicitie of man is found out and held
up, without her it falleth by a sudden, and wofull ruine: by her it
falleth by a sudden, and wofull ruine: by her his honor is highly
advaunced, without her it sinketh into shame and reproach, and is
utterlie confounded: by her hee is indued with a blessed state of
life, without her he perisheth in miserie and death.  Now lest so
excellent a gift of the divine goodnesse (as wisedome here appeareth
to be, and is) should lye supprest by silence, and so remaine hid in
darkenesse, almightie God the deep sea of wisedome, and bright sunne
of majestie, hath opened the mouth of man, as the mouth of a
plentifull fountaine, both to powre forth the inward pasions of his
heart, and also as a heavenly planet to shew foorth, by the shining
beames of speech) the privie thoughts and secret conceites of his
mind.  By the benefit of this excellent gift, (I meane of apt speech
given by nature, and guided by Art) wisedome appeareth in her beautie,
sheweth her majestie, and exerciseth her power, working in the minde
of the hearer, partly by a pleasant proportion, &amp; as it were by a
sweet &amp; musicall harmonie, and partly by the secret and mightie power
of perswasion after a most wonderfull manner.  This then is the vertue
which the Orator in his praise before mentioned calleth eloquence, &amp;
the brightnesse of wisedome, for that by the mean hereof, as well the
rare inventions &amp; pleasant devises, as the deepe understanding, the
secret counselles, &amp; politick considerations of wisedome, are most
effectually expressed, and most comely beautified, for even as by the
power of the Sun beames, the nature of the roote is shewed in the
blossome, &amp; the goodnesse of the sap tasted in the sweetnesse of the
frute, even so the precious nature, and wonderfull power of wisedome,
is by the commendable ARt and use of eloquence, produced and brought
into open light.  So that hereby plainlie appeareth, both the great
necessitie &amp; singular utilitie of their conjunction before commended,
for the one without the other, do finde both great want, and shew
great imperfection, for to possesse great knowledge without apt
utterance, is, as to possesse great treasure without use: contrariwise
to affect eloquence without the discretion of wisdom, is, as to handle
a sweete instrument of musicke without skill.  But the man which is
well furnished with both: I meane with ample knowledge and excellent
speech, hath bene judged able, and esteemed fit to rule the world with
counsell, provinces with lawes, cities with pollicy, &amp; multitudes with
persuasion: such were those men in times past, who by their singular
wisdom and eloquence, made savage nations civil, wild people tame, and
cruell tyrants not only to become meeke, but likewise mercifull.
Hence it was, that in ancient time men did attribute so great opinion
of wisedome to the eloquent Orators of those daies, that they called
them sacred, holy, divine, &amp; the interpreters of the goddes, for so
doth Horace commending Orpheus, his words be these.</p>

	<quote rend="block">
<lg xml:lang="la">
<l>Agrestes homines sacer interpresque Deorum.</l>
<l>Caecibus, &amp; faedo victu deterruit Orpheus.</l>
<l>Dictus ob id, lenire tigres rigidosque leones.</l>
</lg></quote>

<p>The Poet here under the name of tigres and lions, meant not beasts
but men, &amp; such men as by their savage nature &amp; cruell manners, might
well be compared to fierce tigres and devouring lions, which
notwithstanding by the mightie power of wisdome, and prudent art of
perswasion were converted from that most brutish condition of life, to
the love of humanitie, &amp; polliticke government, so might is the power
of this happie union.  (I meane of wisdom &amp; eloquence) that by the one
the Orator forceth, and by the other he allureth, and by both so
worketh, that what he commendeth is beloved, what he dispraiseth is
abhorred, what he perswadeth is obeied, &amp; what he disswadeth is
avoided: so that he is in a maner the emperour of mens minds &amp;
affections, and next to the omnipotent God in the power of perswasion,
by grace, &amp; divine assistance.  The principal instruments of mans help
in this wonderfull effect, are those figures and formes of speech
conteined in this booke, which are the frutefull branches of
eloquution, and the mightie streames of eloquence: whose utilitie,
power, and vertue, I cannot sufficiently commend, but speaking by
similitude, I say they are as stars to give light, as cordials to
comfort, as harmony to delight, as pitiful spectacles to move sorrow
full passions, and as orient colours to beautifie reason.  Finally
they are as martiall instruments both of defence &amp; invasion, and being
so, what may be either more necessary, or more profitable for us, then
to hold those weapons alwaies readie in our handes, wherewith we may
defend our selves, invade our enemies, revenge our wrongs, ayd the
weake, deliver the simple from danges, conserve true religion, &amp;
confute idolatry?  for looke what the sword may do in war, for that
with violence, this with perswasion, that with shedding of blood, this
with pearcing the sffections, that with desire of death, this with
speciall regard of life.</p>

<p>Now, lest this part should seeme an emptie art of wordes, without
wisedome or substance of matter, I have gathered out of the most
excellent Orators, &amp; best approved authors, varietie of fit
examples for everie figure by it selfe:  which figures or formes of
speech, I have disposed into orders, described by their properties,
distinguished by their differences, noted their singular uses, &amp;
added certain Cautions to compasse them for feare of abuse.  And now
Right Honourable, having finished this little booke (alhtough with no
little labor) I hope to the good of many, and hurt of none, with
sincere affection, &amp; with most humble dutie, I present it to your
good Lordship, as to a lover &amp; favourer of learning, in hope of
your favourable acceptation, being mooved hereunto by long experience
of your lordships excellent wisdome, &amp; constant goodnes, ready at
al time to lend your helping hand (in good causes) to them which by
necessitie &amp; distresse, stood in need therof, among which, I am
one that have tasted of your goodnes &amp; comfort:  the remembrance
wherof, hath bin one principall motive, of taking this labor in hand,
to the end that I among the rest which love and honour your Lordship,
might have somewhat to signifie my gratitude and bound dutie:
beseeching your Honor, albeit this worke be such as your Lordship
shall litle need, being so richly furnished by nature, yet for their
sakes who may take benefit by it, you will please to shadow and
protect it under the wings of your honourable favour.  That I may not
trouble your Lordship any further, I commend your Honour with my
hartie praiers, to the mercifull protection of the Almightie,
beseeching him, that by his grace and mercy you may long continue, to
her most excellent Majestie a most faithfull and prudent Counsellour,
to the oppressed a reliefe, to innocents a sure protection, to your
country a treasure, to your friends a sure protection, to your country
a treasure, to your friends a comfort, to godlie and painfull students
a gracious Mecaenas, and to the posteritie of many ages, a renowmed
president of equitie.</p>
	<note type="closer"><ab type="dateline">At North Mymmes the 3. of
February. 1593.</ab>
<ab type="salute">Your Honors most humble to be commanded,</ab>
<ab type="signed">Henry Peacham.</ab>
</note>
</div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>