<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng"	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>A Speach In The Parliament Hovse, As Neere The Very Words As Covld Be Gathered At The
     Instant.</title>

    <author>James I</author>
    <editor role="editor">Charles Howard McIlwain</editor>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
     <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
     <name>Anne Mahoney</name>
     <name>David Smith</name>
     <name>Clifford Wulfman</name>
    </respStmt>
    <funder n="org:Tufts">Tufts University</funder>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent/>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
    <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
    <date type="release" when="2001" cert="high">Perseus 3.0</date>
    <idno type="filename">james1.speech1605.perseus-eng1.xml</idno>
    <availability>
     <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative
      Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblStruct>
     <monogr>
      <title>The Politial Works of James I: Reprinted from the Edition of 1616</title>
      <author>James I</author>
      <editor role="editor">Charles Howard McIlwain</editor>
      <imprint>
       <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
       <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
       <date>1918</date>
      </imprint>
     </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <refsDecl n="CTS">
    <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+).(\w+)"
     replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
     <p>This pointer pattern extracts section.</p>
    </cRefPattern>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <langUsage>
    <language ident="eng">English</language>
    <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
   </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2000-03-29" who="Tony Lilly">markup</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>

  <body>
   <div type="edition" n="urn:cts:engLit:james1.speech1605.perseus-eng1" xml:lang="eng">
    
     <head>A Speach In The Parliament Hovse, As Neere The Very Words As Covld Be Gathered At The Instant.</head>

    <div subtype="section" type="textpart" n="0">

     <p>MY Lords Spirituall and Temporall, and you the Knights and Burgesses of this Parliament, It
      was farre from my thoughts till very lately before my comming to this place, that this Subiect
      should haue bene ministred vnto mee, whereupon I am now to speake. But now it so falleth out,
      That whereas in the preceding Session of this Parliament, the principall occasion of my Speach
      was, to thanke and congratulate all you of this House, and in you, all the whole Com-
      mon-wealth (as being the representatiue body of the State) for your so willing, and louing
      receiuing and embracing of mee in that place, which GOD and Nature by descent of blood, had in
      his owne time prouided for me: So now my Subiect is to speake of a farre greater Thankesgiuing
      then before I gaue to you, being to a farre greater person, which is to GOD, for the great and
      miraculous Deliuery he hath at this time granted to me, and to you all, and consequently to
      the whole body of this Estate. </p>
     <p>I must therefore begin with this old and most approued Sentence of Diuinitie, <hi
       rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="lat">Misericordia Dei supra omnia opera eius</foreign></hi>.
      For Almightie God did not furnish so great matter to his glory by the Creation of this great
      World, as he did by the Redemption of the same. Neither did his generation of the little world
      in our old &amp; first Adam, so much set forth the praises of God in his Iustice and Mercy, as
      did our Regeneration in the last &amp; second Adam. </p>
     <p>And now I must craue a little pardon of you, That since Kings are in the word of GOD it
      selfe called Gods, as being his Lieutenants and Vice-gerents on earth, and so adorned and
      furnished with some sparkles of the Diuinitie; to compare some of the workes of GOD the great
      KING, towards the whole and generall world, to some of his workes towards mee, and this little
      world of my Dominions, com- passed and seuered by the Sea from the rest of the earth. For as
      GOD for the iust punishment of the first great sinnes in the originall world, when the sonnes
      of GOD went in to the daughters of men, and the cup of their inquities of all sorts was
      filled, and heaped vp to the full, did by a generall deluge and ouerflowing of waters, baptize
      the world to a generall destruction, and not to a generall purga- tion (onely excepted NOAH
      and his family, who did repent and beleeue the threat- nings of GODS iudgement:) So now when
      the world shall waxe old as a garment, and that all the impieties and sinnes that can be
      deuised against both the first and second Table, haue and shall bee committed to the full
      measure; GOD is to punish the world the second time by fire, to the generall destruction and
      not purgation <pb n="282"/> thereof. Although as was done in the former to NOAH and his family
      by the waters; So shall all we that beleeue be likewise purged, and not destroyed by the fire.
      In the like sort, I say, I may iustly compare these two great and fearefull <hi rend="italic"
       >Domes-dayes</hi>, wherewith GOD threatned to destroy mee and all you of this little world
      that haue interest in me. For although I confesse, as all mankinde, so chiefly Kings, as being
      in the higher places like the high Trees, or stayest Moun- taines, and steepest Rockes, are
      most subiect to the dayly tempest of innumerable dangers; and I amongst all other Kings haue
      euer bene subiect vnto them, not onely euer since my birth, but euen as I may iustly say,
      before my birth: and while I was yet in my mothers belly: yet haue I bene exposed to two more
      speciall and greater dangers then all the rest. </p>
     <p>The first of them, in the Kingdome where I was borne, and passed the first part of my life:
      And the last of them here, which is the greatest. In the former I should haue bene baptized in
      blood, and in my destruction not onely the King- dom wherein I then was, but ye also by your
      future interest, should haue tasted of my ruine: Yet it pleased GOD to deliuer mee, as it were
      from the very brinke of death, from the point of the dagger, and so to purge me by my
      thankefull acknowledgement of so great a benefite. But in this, which did so lately fall out,
      and which was a destruction prepared not for me alone, but for you all that are here present,
      and wherein no ranke, aage, nor sexe should haue bene spared; This was not a crying sinne of
      blood, as the former, but it may well bee called a roaring, nay a thundring sinne of fire and
      brimstone, from the which GOD hath so miracu- lously deliuered vs all. What I can speake of
      this, I know not: Nay rather, what can I not speake of it ? And therefore I must for horror
      say with the Poet, <hi rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="lat">Vox faucibus
       hU+00E6ret.</foreign></hi>
     </p>
     <p>In this great and horrible attempt, whereof the like was neuer either heard or read, I
      obserue three wonderfull, or rather miraculous euents. </p>
    </div>
    <div subtype="section" type="textpart" n="1">
     <head>1</head>


     <p>First, in the crueltie of the Plot it selfe, wherein cannot be enough admired the horrible
      and fearefull crueltie of their deuice, which was not onely for the destruc- tion of my
      Person, nor of my Wife and posteritie onely, but of the whole body of the State in generall;
      wherein should neither haue bene spared, or distinction made of yong nor of old, of great nor
      of small, of man nor of woman: The whole Nobilitie, the whole reuerend Clergie, Bishops, and
      most part of the good Preachers, the most part of the Knights and Gentrie; yea, and if that
      any in this Societie were fauourers of their profession, they should all haue gone one way:
      The whole Iudges of the land, with the most of the Lawyers, and the whole Clerkes: And as the
      wretch himselfe which is in the Tower, doeth confesse, it was purposely deuised by them, and
      concluded to be done in this house; That where the cruell Lawes (as they say) were made
      against their Religion, both place and persons should all be destroyed and blowne vp at once.
      And then consider there- <pb n="283"/> withall the cruel fourme of that practise: for by three
      different sorts in generall may mankinde be put to death. </p>
     <p>The first, by other men, and reasonable creatures, which is least cruell: for then both
      defence of men against men may be expected, and likewise who knoweth what pitie God may stirre
      vp in the hearts of the Actors at the verye instant ? besides the many wayes and meanes,
      whereby men may escape in such a present furie. </p>
     <p>And the second way more cruell then that, is by <hi rend="italic">Animal</hi> and
      vnreasonable creatures: for as they haue lesse pitie then men, so is it a greater horror and
      more vnnaturall for men to deale with them: But yet with them both resistance may auaile, and
      also some pitie may be had, as was in the Lions, in whose denne <hi rend="italic">Daniel</hi>
      was throwne; or that thankefull Lion, that had the Romane in his mercie. </p>
     <p>But the third, which is most cruel and vnmercifull of all, is the destruction by insensible
      and inanimate things, and amongst them all, the most cruell are the two Elements of Water and
      Fire; and of those two, the fire most raging and mercilesse.</p>
    </div>
    <div subtype="section" type="textpart" n="2">
     <head>2</head>

     <p>Secondly, how wonderfull it is when you shall thinke vpon the small, or rather no ground,
      whereupon the practisers were entised to inuent this Tragedie. For if these Conspirators had
      onely bene bankrupt persons, or discontented vpon occasion of any disgraces done vnto them;
      this might haue seemed to haue bene but a worke of reuenge. But for my owne part, as I
      scarcely euer knew any of them, so cannot they alledge so much as a pretended cause of griefe:
      And the wretch himselfe in hands doeth confesse, That there was no cause moouing him or them,
      but meerely and only Religion. And specially that christian men, at least so called,
      Englishmen, borne within the Countrey, and one of the specials of them my sworne Seruant in an
      Honourable place, should practise the destruc- tion of their King, his Posterity, their
      Countrey and all: Wherein their following obstinacie is so ioyned to their former malice, as
      the fellow himselfe that is in hand, cannot be moued to discouer any signes or notes of
      repentance, except onely that he doeth not yet stand to auow, that he repents for not being
      able to performe his intent.</p>
    </div>
    <div subtype="section" type="textpart" n="3">
     <head>3</head>

     <p>Thirdly, the discouery hereof is not a little wonderfull, which would bee thought the more
      miraculous by you all, if you were aswell acquainted with my naturall disposition, as those
      are who be neere about me: For as I euer did hold Suspition to be the sicknes of a Tyrant, so
      was I so farre vpon the other extremity, as I rather contemned all aduertisements, or
      apprehensions of practises. And yet now at this time was I so farre contrary to my selfe, as
      when the Letter was shewed to me by my Secretary, wherein a generall obscure aduertisement was
      giuen of some dangerous blow at this time, I did vpon the instant interpret and apprehend some
      darke phrases therein, contrary to the ordinary Grammer con- <pb n="284"/> struction of them,
      (and in an other sort then I am sure any Diuine, or Lawyer in any Vniuersitie would haue taken
      them) to be meant by this horrible forme of blowing vs vp all by Powder; And thereupon ordered
      that search to be made, whereby the matter was discouered, and the man apprehended : whereas
      if I had apprehended or interpreted it to any other sort of danger, no worldly prouision or
      preuention could haue made vs escape our vtter destruction. </p>
     <p>And in that also was there a wonderfull prouidence of God, that when the party himselfe was
      taken, he was but new come out of his house from working, hauing his Fireworke for kindling
      ready in his pocket, wherewith as he confesseth, if he had bene taken but immediatly before
      when he was in the House, he was resolued to haue blowen vp himselfe with his Takers. </p>
     <p>One thing for mine owne part haue I cause to thanke GOD in, That if GOD for our sinnes had
      suffered their wicked intents to haue preuailed, it should neuer haue bene spoken nor written
      in aages succeeding, that I had died ingloriously in an Ale-house, a Stews, or such vile
      place, but mine end should haue bene with the most Honourable and best company, and in that
      most Honourable and fittest place for a King to be in, for doing the turnes most proper to his
      Office. And the more haue We all cause to thanke and magnifie GOD for this his mercifull De-
      liuery; And specially I for my part, that he hath giuen me yet once leaue, what- soeuer should
      come of me hereafter, to assemble you in this Honourable place; And here in this place, where
      our generall destruction should haue bene, to magnifie and praise him for Our generall
      deliuery: That I may iustly now say of mine Enemies and yours, as <hi rend="italic">Dauid</hi>
      doeth often say in the Psalme, <hi rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="lat">Inciderunt in foueam
        quam fecerunt</foreign></hi>. And since <hi rend="italic">Scipio</hi> an Ethnick, led onely
      by the light of Nature, That day when he was accused by the <hi rend="italic">Tribunes</hi> of
      the people of <hi rend="italic">Rome</hi> for mispending and wasting in his <hi rend="italic"
       >Punick</hi> warres the Cities Treasure, even vpon the sudden brake out with that diuersion
      of them from that matter, calling them to remembrance how that day, was the day of the yeere,
      wherein God had giuen them so great a victory against <hi rend="italic">Hannibal</hi>,
      therefore it was fitter for them all, leauing other matters, to runne to the Temple to praise
      God for that so great deliuery, which the people did all follow with one applause: How much
      more cause haue we that are Christians to bestow this time in this place for Thankes- giuing
      to God for his great Mercy, though we had had no other errant of assem- bling here at this
      time ? wherein if I haue spoken more like a Diuine then would seeme to belong to this place,
      the matter it selfe must plead for mine excuse: For being here commen to thanke God for a
      diuine worke of his Mercy, how can I speake of this deliuerance of vs from so hellish a
      practise, so well as in language of Diuinitie, which is the direct opposite to so damnable an
      intention ? And there- for may I iustly end this purpose, as I did begin it with this
      Sentence, <hi rend="italic">The Mercie of God is aboue all his workes.</hi>
     </p>
     <p>It resteth now that I should shortly informe you what is to bee done hereafter vpon the
      occasion of this horrible and strange accident. As for your part that <pb n="285"/> are my
      faithfull and louing Subiects of all degrees, I know that your hearts are so burnt vp with
      zeale in this errant, and your tongues so ready to vtter your duetifull affections, and your
      hands and feete so bent to concurre in the execution thereof, (for which as I neede not to
      spurre you, so can I not but praise you for the same:) As it may very well be possible that
      the zeale of your hearts shall make some of you in your speaches rashly to blame such as may
      bee innocent of this attempt; But vpon the other part I wish you to consider, That I would be
      sorie that any being innocent of this practise, either domesticall or forraine, should receiue
      blame or harme for the same. For although it cannot be denied, That it was the onely blinde
      superstition of their errors in Religion, that led them to this desperate deuice; yet doth it
      not follow, That all professing that <hi rend="italic">Romish</hi> religion were guiltie of
      the same. For as it is trew, That no other sect of here- tiques, not excepting <hi
       rend="italic">Turke, Iew</hi>, nor <hi rend="italic">Pagan</hi>, no not euen those of <hi
       rend="italic">Calicute</hi>, who adore the deuill, did euer maintaine by the grounds of their
      religion, That it was lawfull, or rather meritorious (as the <hi rend="italic">Romish</hi>
      Catholickes call it) to murther Princes or people for quarrell of Religion. And although
      particular men of all professions of Religion haue beene some Theeues, some Murtherers, some
      Traitors, yet euer when they came to their end and iust punishment, they con- fessed their
      fault to bee in their nature, and not in their profession, (These <hi rend="italic"
       >Romish</hi> Catholicks onely excepted:) Yet it is trew on the other side, that many honest
      men blinded peraduenture with some opinions of Popery, as if they be not found in the
      questions of the <hi rend="italic">Reall presence</hi>, or in the number of the Sacraments, or
      some such Schoole question: yet doe they either not know, or at least not beleeue all the trew
      grounds of Popery, which is in deed <hi rend="italic">The mysterie of iniquitie</hi>. And
      therefore doe we iustly confesse, that many Papists, especially our forefathers, laying their
      onely trust vpon CHRIST and his Merits at their last breath, may be, and often times are
      saued; detesting in that point, and thinking the crueltie of Puritanes worthy of fire, that
      will admit no saluation to any Papist. I therefore thus doe conclude this point, That as vpon
      the one part many honest men, se- duced with some errors of Popery, may yet remaine good and
      faithfull Subiects: So vpon the other part, none of those that trewly know and beleeue the
      whole grounds, and Schoole conclusions of their doctrine, can euer proue either good
      Christians, or faithfull Subiects. And for the part of forraine Princes and States, I may so
      much the more acquite them, and their Ministers of their knowledge and consent to any such
      villanie, as I may iustly say, that in that point I better know all Christian Kings by my
      selfe, That no King nor Prince of Honour will euer abase himselfe so much, as to thinke a good
      thought of so base and dis- honourable a Treachery, wishing you therefore, that as God hath
      giuen me an happie Peace and Amitie, with all other Christian Princes my neighbours (as was
      euen now very grauely told you by my L. Chancellor) that so you will reuerently iudge and
      speak of them in this case. And for my part I would wish with those ancient Philosophers, that
      there were a Christall window in my brest, <pb n="286"/> wherein all my people might see the
      secretest thoughts of my heart, for then might you all see no alteration in my minde for this
      accident, further then in these two points. The first, Caution and warinesse in gouernment, to
      discouer and search out the mysteries of this wickednesse as farre as may be: The other, after
      due triall, Seueritie of punishment vpon those that shall bee found guilty of so detestable
      and vnheard of villanie. And now in this matter if I haue troubled your eares with an abrupt
      speach, vndigested in any good methode or order; you haue to consider that an abrupt, and
      vnaduised speach doeth best become in the relation of so abrupt and vnorderly an accident. </p>
     <p>And although I haue ordained the proroguing of this Parliament vntil after Christmas vpon
      two necessary respects: whereof the first is, that neither I nor my Councell can haue leisure
      at this time both to take order for the Apprehension and triall of these Conspiratours, and
      also to wait vpon the dayly affaires of the Parliament, as the Councell must doe: And the
      other reason is, the necessitie at this time of diuers of your presences in your Shires that
      haue Charges and Com- mandements there. For as these wretches thought to haue blowen vp in a
      maner the whole world of this Island, euery man being now commen vp here, either for publike
      causes of Parliament, or else for their owne piruate causes in Law, or otherwise: So these
      Rebels that now wander through the Countrey, could neuer haue gotten so fit a time of safetie
      in their passage, or whatsoeuer vnlawfull Actions, as now when the Countrey by the foresaid
      occasions is in a maner left desolate, and waste vnto them. Besides that, it may be that I
      shall desire you at your next Session, to take vpon you the Iudgement of this Crime: For as so
      extraordinary a Fact deserues extraordinary Iudgement, So can there not I thinke (following
      euen their owne Rule) be a fitter Iudgement for them, then that they should be measured with
      the same measure wherewith they thought to measure vs: And that the same place and persons,
      whom they thought to destroy, should be the iust auengers of their so vnnaturall a Parricide:
      Yet not knowing that I will haue occasion to meete with you my selfe in this place at the
      beginning of the next Session of this Parliament, (because if it had not been for deliuering
      of the Articles agreed vpon by the Commissioners of the Vnion, which was thought most
      conuenient to be done in my presence, where both Head and Members of the Parliament were met
      together, my presence had not otherwise been requisite here at this time:) I haue therefore
      thought good for conclusion of this Meeting, to discourse to you somewhat anent the trew
      nature and definition of a Parlia- ment, which I will remit to your memories till your next
      sitting downe, that you may then make vse of it as occasion shall bee ministred. </p>
     <p>For albeit it be trew, that at the first Session of my first Parliament, which was not long
      after mine Entrie into this Kingdome, It could not become me to in- forme you of any thing
      belonging to Law or State heere: (for all knowledge must either bee infused or acquired, and
      seeing the former sort thereof is now with Prophecie ceased in the world, it could not be
      possible for me at my first Entry <pb n="287"/> here, before Experience had taught it me, to
      be able to vnderstand the particular mysteries of this State:) yet now that I haue reigned
      almost three yeeres amongst you, and haue beene carefull to obserue those things that belong
      to the office of a King, albeit that Time be but a short time for experience in others, yet in
      a King may it be thought a reasonable long time, especially in me, who, although I be but in a
      maner a new King heere, yet haue bene long acquainted with the office of a King in such
      another Kingdome, as doeth neerest of all others agree with the Lawes and customes of this
      State. Remitting to your consideration to iudge of that which hath beene concluded by the
      Commissioners of the Vnion, wherein I am at this time to signifie vnto you, That as I can
      beare witnesse to the foresaid Commissioners, that they haue not agreed nor concluded therein
      any thing wherein they haue not foreseen as well the weale and commodity of the one Countrey,
      as of the other; So can they all beare mee record, that I was so farre from pressing them to
      agree to any thing, which might bring with it any pre- iudice to this people; as by the
      contrary I did euer admonish them, neuer to conclude vpon any such Vnion, as might cary hurt
      or grudge with it to either of the said Nations: for the leauing of any such thing, could not
      but be the greatest hindrance that might be to such an Action, which God by the lawes of
      Nature had prouided to be in his owne time, and hath now in effect perfected in my Person, to
      which purpose my Lord Chancellour hath better spoken, then I am able to relate. </p>
     <p>And as to the nature of this high Court of Parliament, It is nothing else but the Kings
      great Councell, which the King doeth assemble either vpon occasion of interpreting, or
      abrogating old Lawes, or making of new, according as ill maners shall deserue, or for the
      publike punishment of notorious euill doers, or the praise and reward of the vertuous and well
      deseruers; wherein these foure things are to be considered. </p>
     <p>First, whereof this Court is composed. </p>
     <p>Secondly, what matters are proper for it. </p>
     <p>Thirdly, to what end it is ordeined. </p>
     <p>And fourthly, what are the meanes and wayes whereby this end should bee brought to passe. </p>
     <p>As for the thing it selfe, It is composed of a Head and a Body: The Head is the King, the
      Body are the members of the Parliament. This Body againe is subdiuided into two parts; The
      Vpper and Lower House: The Vpper com- pounded partly of Nobility, Temporall men, who are
      heritable Councellors to the high Court of Parliament by the honour of their Creation and
      Lands: And partly of Bishops, Spirituall men, who are likewise by the vertue of their place
      and dignitie Councellours, Life Renters, or <hi rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="lat">Ad
        vitam</foreign></hi> of this Court. The other House is composed of Knights for the Shire;
      and Gentry, and Burgesses for the Townes. But because the number would be infinite for all the
      Gentlemen and Burgesses to bee present at euery Parliament, Therefore a certaine number is
      selected and <pb n="288"/> chosen out of that great Body, seruing onely for that Parliament,
      where their persons are the representation of that Body. </p>
     <p>Now the matters whereof they are to treate ought therefore to be generall, and rather of
      such matters as cannot well bee performed without the assembling of that generall Body, and no
      more of these generals neither, then necessity shall require: for as <hi rend="italic"
        ><foreign xml:lang="lat">in Corruptissima Republica sunt plurimU+00E6 leges</foreign></hi>:
      So doeth the life and strength of the Law consist not in heaping vp infinite and confused
      numbers of Lawes, but in the right interpreation and good execution of good and wholesome
      Lawes. If this be so then, neither is this a place on the one side for euery rash and
      harebrained fellow to propone new Lawes of his owne inuention: nay rather I could wish these
      busie heads to remember that Law of the Lacedemonians, That whosoeuer came to propone a new
      Law to the people, behooued publikely to present himselfe with a rope about his necke, that in
      case the Law were not allowed, he should be hanged therewith. So warie should men be of
      proponing Nouelties, but most of all not to propone any bitter or seditious Laws, which can
      produce nothing but grudges and discontentment betweene the Prince and his people: Nor yet is
      it on the other side a conuenient place for priuate men vnder the colour of general Lawes, to
      propone nothing but their owne particular gaine, either to the hurt of their priuate
      neighbours, or to the hurt of the whole State in generall, which many times vnder faire and
      pleasing Titles, are smoothly passed ouer, and so by stealth procure without consideration,
      that the piruate meaning of them tendeth to nothing but either to the wrecke of a particular
      partie, or else vnder colour of publike benefite to pill the poore people and serue as it were
      for a generall Impost vpon them for filling the purses of some priuate persons. </p>
     <p>And as to the end for which the Parliament is ordeined, being only for the aduancement of
      Gods glory, and the establishment and wealth of the King and his people: It is no place then
      for particular men to vtter there their priuate conceipts, not for satisfaction of their
      curiosities, and least of all to make shew of their eloquence by tyning the time with long
      studied and eloquent Orations: No, the reuerence of God, their King, and their Countrey being
      well setled in their hearts, will make them ashamed of such toyes, and remember that they are
      there as sworne Councellours to their King, to giue their best aduise for the further- ance of
      his Seruice, and the florishing Weale of his Estate. </p>
     <p>And lastly, if you will rightly consider the meanes and wayes how to bring all your labours
      to a good end, you must remember, That you are heere as- sembled by your lawfull King to giue
      him your best aduises, in the matters proposed by him vnto you, being of that nature, which I
      haue already told, wherein you are grauely to deliberate, and vpon your consciences plainely
      to determine how farre those things propounded doe agree with the weale, both of your King and
      of your Countrey, whose weales cannot be separated. And as for my selfe, the world shall euer
      beare mee witnesse, That I neuer shall propone any thing vnto you, which shall not as well
      tend to the weale publike, as to any <pb n="289"/> benefite for me: So shall I neuer oppone my
      selfe to that, which may tend to the good of the Common-wealth, for the which I am ordeined,
      as I haue often said. And as you are to giue ycur aduise in such things as shall by your King
      be pro- posed: So is it on your part your dueties to propone any thing that you can after
      mature deliberation iudge to be needefull, either for these ends already spoken of, or
      otherwise for the discouery of any latent euill in the Kingdome, which per- aduenture may not
      haue commen to the Kings eare. If this then ought to bee your graue maner of proceeding in
      this place, Men should bee ashamed to make shew of the quicknesse of their wits here, either
      in taunting, scoffing, or detracting the Prince or State in any point, or yet in breaking
      iests vpon their fellowes, for which the Ordinaries or Ale-houses are fitter places, then this
      Honourable and high Court of Parliament. </p>
     <p>In conclusion then since you are to break vp, for the reasons I haue already told you, I
      wish such of you as haue any charges in your Countreys, to hasten you home for the repressing
      of the insolencies of these Rebels, and apprehension of their persons, wherein as I heartily
      pray to the Almightie for your prosperous successe: So doe I not doubt, but we shall shortly
      heare the good newes of the same; And that you shall haue an happie returne, and meeting here
      to all our comforts.</p>
     <p>
      <note anchored="true" resp="ed" place="inline"><hi rend="italic">Here the Lord Chancellor
        spake touching the proroguing of the Parliament: And hauing done, his Maiestie rose againe,
        and said,</hi>
      </note></p>
     <p>Since it pleased God to graunt mee two such notable Deliueries vpon one day of the weeke,
      which was Tuesday, and likewise one day of the Moneth, which was the fifth; Thereby to teach
      mee, That as it was the same deuill that still per- secuted mee; So it was one and the same
      GOD that still mightily deliuered mee: I thought it therefore not amisse, That the one and
      twentieth day of Ianuary, which fell to be vpon Tuesday, should bee the day of meeting of this
      next Session of Parliament, hoping and assuring my selfe, that the same GOD, who hath now
      granted me and you all so notable and gracious a deliuerie, shall prosper all our affaires at
      that next Session, and bring them to an happie conclusion. And now I consider GOD hath well
      prouided it, that the ending of this Parliament hath bene so long continued: For as for my
      owne part, I neuer had any other inten- tion, but onely to seeke so farre my weale, and
      prosperitie, as might coniunctly stand with the flourishing State of the whole Common-wealth,
      as I haue often told you; So on the other part I confesse, if I had bene in your places at the
      beginning of this Parliament, (which was so soone after mine entry into this Kingdome, wherein
      ye could not possibly haue so perfect a knowledge of mine inclination, as experience since
      hath taught you,) I could not but haue suspected, and mis-interpreted diuers things, In the
      trying whereof, now I hope, by your experience of my behauiour and forme of gouernment, you
      are well ynough cleared, and resolued. <pb n="290"/>
     </p>
    </div>
   
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
