<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="../../../schemas/perseus_marlowe.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Hero and Leander</title>
<title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
<author>Christopher Marlowe</author>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt><p>later</p></publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc><bibl/></sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>

<!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
<step refunit="sestyad" delim="." n="chunk" from="DESCENDANT (1 DIV2 N %1)"/>
<step refunit="line" from="DESCENDANT (1 L N %2)"/>
</refsDecl> -->

      <refsDecl n="CTS"><cRefPattern n="asl" matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+).(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath((//div[@subtype='act' and @n='$1']/div[@subtype='scene' and @n='$2']//lb[@ed='G'])[$3]/parent::*)"><p>This pointer pattern extracts act, scene, and line.</p></cRefPattern><cRefPattern n="as" matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(//div[@subtype='act' and @n='$1']/div[@subtype='scene' and @n='$2'])"><p>This pointer pattern extracts act and scene.</p></cRefPattern><cRefPattern n="sestyad" matchPattern="([0-6])" replacementPattern="#xpath(//div[@subtype='sestyad' and @n='$1'])"><p>This pointer pattern extracts act.</p></cRefPattern><cRefPattern n="sestyad line" matchPattern="([0-6]).(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(//div[@subtype='sestyad' and @n='$1']//l[@n='$2])"><p>This pointer pattern extracts act.</p></cRefPattern></refsDecl>



</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="eng">English</language>
<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>


</teiHeader>

<text xml:lang="eng">
<front>



<div type="apparatus">
<listWit>
<witness xml:id="Bow"><bibl><title>Complete Works</title>, ed. Bowers, 1973</bibl></witness>
<witness xml:id="Q1">Quarto, 1598</witness>
<witness xml:id="Q2">Quarto, 1598</witness>
<witness xml:id="Q3">Quarto, 1600</witness>
<witness xml:id="Q4">Quarto, 1606</witness>
<witness xml:id="Q5">Quarto, 1609</witness>
<witness xml:id="Q6">Quarto, 1613</witness>
<witness xml:id="Q7">Quarto, 1617</witness>
<witness xml:id="Q8">Quarto, 1622</witness>
<witness xml:id="Q9">Quarto, 1629</witness>
<witness xml:id="Q10">Quarto, 1637</witness>
<witness xml:id="Bs"><bibl><title>Restituta</title>, ed. Sir Egerton Brydges, vol. II, 1815</bibl></witness>
<witness xml:id="S"><bibl><title>Select English Poets</title>, no. VIII, ed. Singer, 1821</bibl></witness>
<witness xml:id="R"><bibl><title>Works</title>, ed. Robinson, 1826</bibl></witness>
<witness xml:id="D1"><bibl><title>Works</title>, ed. Dyce 1, 1850</bibl></witness>
<witness xml:id="D2"><bibl><title>Works</title>, ed. Dyce 2, 1858</bibl></witness>
<witness xml:id="C"><bibl><title>Works</title>, Cunningham, 1878</bibl></witness>
<witness xml:id="B"><bibl><title>Works</title>, Bullen, 1885</bibl></witness>
<witness xml:id="TB"><bibl><title>Works</title>, Tucker Brooke, 1910</bibl></witness>
<witness xml:id="M"><bibl><title>Poems</title>, Methuen, ed. Martin, 1931</bibl></witness>
<witness xml:id="Bt"><bibl><title>Poems of Chapman</title>, ed. Batlett, 1941</bibl></witness>
<witness xml:id="Rv"><bibl><title>Poems</title>, Revel's, ed. MacLure, 1968</bibl></witness>
<witness xml:id="Mal">MS notes by Malone in Bodleian Q3</witness>
<witness xml:id="Br">MS notes by Broughton in BM copy of Robinson</witness>
<witness xml:id="Coll">Ms notes by Collier in BM copy of Dyce1
</witness>
<witness xml:id="D"/>
</listWit>
</div>



</front>


<body>
<div type="textpart" subtype="part" n="1">
<div type="textpart">
<ab type="opener">
<ab type="salute">To the Right Worshipfull, Sir Thomas Walsingham, Knight</ab>
</ab>
<p><lb/>Sir, wee thinke not our selves discharged of the dutie wee owe to our
<lb/>friend, when wee have brought the breathlesse bodie to the earth: for
<lb/>albeit the eye there taketh his ever farwell of that beloved object, yet the
<lb/>impression of the man, that hath beene deare unto us, living an after
<lb/>life in our memory, there putteth us in mind of farther obsequies due
<lb/>unto the deceased. And namely of the performance of whatsoever we
<lb/>may judge shal make to his living credit, and to the effecting of his <lb/>determinations prevented by the stroke of death. By these meditations
<lb/>(as by an intellectuall will) I suppose my selfe executor to the unhappily <lb/>deceased author of this Poem, upon who knowing that in his lift time
<lb/>you bestowed many kind favours, entertaining the parts of reckoning
<lb/>and woorth which you found in him, with good countenance and liberall
<lb/>affection: I cannot but see so far into the will of him dead, but what-
<lb/>soever issue of his brain should chance to come abroad, that the first
<lb/>breath it should take might be the gentle aire of your liking: for since
<lb/>his selfe had ben accustomed therunto, it would proove more agreeable
<lb/>and thriving to his right children, than any other foster countenance <lb/>whatsoever. At this time seeing that this unfinished Tragedy happens
<lb/>under my hands to be imprinted; of a double duty, the one to your selfe,
<lb/>the other to the deceased, I present the same to your most
<lb/>favourable allowance, offring my utmost selfe
<lb/>now and ever to bee readie, </p>
<ab type="signed">At your Worships disposing:
<lb/><name>Edward Blunt</name>.</ab>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="sestyad" n="1">
<head>Hero and Leander</head>

<argument><head>THE ARGUMENT OF THE FIRST SESTYAD</head>
<l n="1"><name>Heros</name> description and her Loves,</l>
<l n="2">The Phane of <name>Venus</name>; where he moves</l>
<l n="3">His worthie Love-suite, and attaines;</l>
<l n="4">Whose blisse the wrath of Fates restraines,</l>
<l n="5">For <name>Cupids</name> grace to <name>Mercurie</name>,</l>
<l n="6">Which tale the Author doth implie.</l></argument>



<lg type="paragraph"><l n="7">On <name>Hellespont</name> guiltie of True-loves blood,</l>
<l n="8">In view and opposit two citties stood,</l>
<l n="9">Seaborderers, disjoin'd by <name>Neptune</name> might:</l>
<l n="10">The one <name>Abydos</name>, the other <name>Sestos</name> hight.</l>
<l n="11">At <name>Sestos</name>, <name>Hero</name> dwelt; <name>Hero</name> the faire,</l>
<l n="12">Whom young <name>Apollo</name> courted for her haire,</l>
<l n="13">And offred as a dower his burning throne,</l>
<l n="14">Where she should sit for men to gaze upon.</l>
<l n="15">The outside of her garments were of lawne,</l>
<l n="16">The lining, purple silke, with guilt starres drawne,</l>
<l n="17">Her wide sleeves greene, and bordered with a grove,</l>
<l n="18">Where <name>Venus</name> in her naked glory strove,</l>
<l n="19">To please the carelesse and disdainfull eies,</l>
<l n="20">Of proud <name>Adonis</name> that before her lies.</l>
<l n="21">Her kirtle blew, whereon was many a staine,</l>
<l n="22">Made with the blood of wretched Lovers slaine.</l>
<l n="23">Upon her head she ware a myrtle wreath,</l>
<l n="24">From whence her vaile reacht to the ground beneath.</l>
<l n="25">Her vaile was artificiall flowers and leaves,</l>
<l n="26">Whose workmanship both man and beast deceaves.</l>
<l n="27">Many would praise the sweet smell as she past,</l>
<l n="28">When t'was the odour which her breath foorth cast.</l>
<l n="29">And there for honie, bees have sought in vaine,</l>
<l n="30">And beat from thence, have lighted there againe.</l>
<l n="31">About her necke hung chaines of peble stone,</l>
<l n="32">Which lightned by her necke, like Diamonds shone.</l>
<l n="33">She ware no gloves, for neither sunne nor wind</l>
<l n="34">Would burne or parch her hands, but to her mind,</l>
<l n="35">Or warme or coole them: for they tooke delite</l>
<l n="36">To play upon those hands, they were so white.</l>
<l n="37">Buskins of shels all silvered, used she,</l>
<l n="38">And brancht with blushing corall to the knee;</l>
<l n="39">Where sparrowes pearcht, of hollow pearle and gold,</l>
<l n="40">Such as the world would woonder to behold:</l>
<l n="41">Those with sweet water oft her handmaid fils,</l>
<l n="42">Which as shee went would cherupe through the bils.</l>
<l n="43">Some say, for her the fairest <name>Cupid</name> pyn'd,</l>
<l n="44">And looking in her face, was strooken blind.</l>
<l n="45">But this is true, so like was one the other,</l>
<l n="46">As he imagyn'd <name>Hero</name> was his mother.</l>
<l n="47">And oftentimes into her bosome flew,</l>
<l n="48">About her naked necke his bare armes threw.</l>
<l n="49">And laid his childish head upon her brest,</l>
<l n="50">And with still panting rockt, there tooke his rest.</l>
<l n="51">So lovely faire was <name>Hero</name>, <name>Venus</name> <name>Nun</name>,</l>
<l n="52">As nature wept, thinking she was undone;</l>
<l n="53">Because she tooke more from her than she left,</l>
<l n="54">And of such wondrous beautie her bereft:</l>
<l n="55">Therefore in signe her treasure suffred wracke,</l>
<l n="56">Since <name>Heroes</name> time, hath halfe the world beene blacke.</l>
<l n="57">Amorous <name>Leander</name>, beautifull and yoong,</l>
<l n="58">(Whose tragedie divine <name>Musaeus</name> soong)</l>
<l n="59">Dwelt at <name>Abidus</name>; since him, dwelt there none,</l>
<l n="60">For whom succeeding times make greater mone.</l>
<l n="61">His dangling tresses that were never shorne,</l>
<l n="62">Had they beene cut, and unto <name>Colchos</name> borne,</l>
<l n="63">Would have allur'd the vent'rous youth of <name>Greece</name>,</l>
<l n="64">To hazard more, than for the golden Fleece.</l>
<l n="65">Faire <name>Cinthia</name> wisht, his armes might be her spheare,</l>
<l n="66">Greefe makes her pale, because she mooves not there.</l>
<l n="67">His bodie was as straight as <name>Circes</name> wand,</l>
<l n="68"><name>Jove</name> might have sipt out <name>Nectar</name> from his hand.</l>
<l n="69">Even as delicious meat is to the tast,</l>
<l n="70">So was his necke in touching, and surpast</l>
<l n="71">The white of <name>Pelops</name> shoulder. I could tell ye,</l>
<l n="72">How smooth his brest was, and how white his bellie,</l>
<l n="73">And whose immortall fingars did imprint,</l>
<l n="74">That heavenly path, with many a curious dint,</l>
<l n="75">That runs along his backe, but my rude pen,</l>
<l n="76">Can hardly blazon foorth the loves of men,</l>
<l n="77">Much lesse of powerfull gods. Let it suffise,</l>
<l n="78">That my slacke muse, sings of <name>Leanders</name> eies,</l>
<l n="79">Those Orient cheekes and lippes, exceeding his</l>
<l n="80">That leapt into the water for a kis</l>
<l n="81">Of his owne shadow, and despising many,</l>
<l n="82">Died ere he could enjoy the love of any.</l>
<l n="83">Had wilde <name>Hippolitus</name>, <name>Leander</name> seene,</l>
<l n="84">Enamoured of his beautie had he beene,</l>
<l n="85">His presence made the rudest paisant melt,</l>
<l n="86">That in the vast uplandish countrie dwelt,</l>
<l n="87">The barbarous <name>Thratian</name> soldier moov'd with nought,</l>
<l n="88">Was moov'd with him, and for his favour sought.</l>
<l n="89">Some swore he was a maid in mans attire,</l>
<l n="90">For in his lookes were all that men desire,</l>
<l n="91">A pleasant smiling cheeke, a speaking eye,</l>
<l n="92">A brow for Love to banquet roiallye,</l>
<l n="93">And such as knew he was a man would say,</l>
<l n="94"><name>Leander</name>, thou art made for amorous play:</l>
<l n="95">Why art thou not in love and lov'd of all?</l>
<l n="96">Though thou be faire, yet be not thine owne thrall.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="97">The men of wealthie <name>Sestos</name>, everie yeare,</l>
<l n="98">(For his sake whom their goddesse held so deare,</l>
<l n="99">Rose-cheekt <name>Adonis</name>) kept a solemne feast.</l>
<l n="100">Thither resorted many a wandring guest,</l>
<l n="101">To meet their loves; such as had none at all,</l>
<l n="102">Came lovers home, from this great festivall.</l>
<l n="103">For everie street like to a Firmament</l>
<l n="104">Glistered with breathing stars, who where they went,</l>
<l n="105">Frighted the melancholie earth, which deem'd,</l>
<l n="106">Eternall heaven to burne, for so it seem'd,</l>
<l n="107">As if another <name>Phaeton</name> had got</l>
<l n="108">The guidance of the sunnes rich chariot.</l>
<l n="109">But far above the loveliest, <name>Hero</name> shin'd,</l>
<l n="110">And stole away th'inchaunted gazers mind,</l>
<l n="111">For like Sea-nimphs inveigling harmony,</l>
<l n="112">So was her beautie to the standers by.</l>
<l n="113">Nor that night-wandring pale and watrie starre,</l>
<l n="114">(When yawning dragons draw her thirling carre,</l>
<l n="115">From <name>Latmus</name> mount up to the glomie skie,</l>
<l n="116">Where crown'd with blazing light and majestie,</l>
<l n="117">She proudly sits) more over-rules the flood,</l>
<l n="118">Than she the hearts of those that neere her stood.</l>
<l n="119">Even as, when gawdie Nymphs pursue the chace,</l>
<l n="120">Wretched Ixions shaggie footed race,</l>
<l n="121">Incenst with savage heat, gallop amaine,</l>
<l n="122">From steepe Pine-bearing mountains to the plaine:</l>
<l n="123">So ran the people foorth to gaze upon her,</l>
<l n="124">And all that view'd her, were enamour'd on her.</l>
<l n="125">And as in furie of a dreadfull fight,</l>
<l n="126">Their fellowes being slaine or put to flight,</l>
<l n="127">Poore soldiers stand with fear of death dead strooken,</l>
<l n="128">So at her presence all surpris'd and tooken,</l>
<l n="129">Await the sentence of her scornefull eies:</l>
<l n="130">He whom she favours lives, the other dies.</l>
<l n="131">There might you see one sigh, another rage,</l>
<l n="132">And some (their violent passions to asswage)</l>
<l n="133">Compile sharpe satyrs, but alas too late,</l>
<l n="134">For faithfull love will never turne to hate.</l>
<l n="135">And many seeing great princes were denied,</l>
<l n="136">Pyn'd as they went, and thinking on her died.</l>
<l n="137">On this feast day, O cursed day and hower,</l>
<l n="138">Went <name>Hero</name> thorow <name>Sestos</name>, from her tower</l>
<l n="139">To <name>Venus</name> temple, where unhappilye,</l>
<l n="140">As after chaunc'd, they did each other spye.</l>
<l n="141">So faire a church as this, had <name>Venus</name> none,</l>
<l n="142">The wals were of discoloured <name>Jasper</name> stone,</l>
<l n="143">Wherein was <name>Proteus</name> carved, and o'rehead,</l>
<l n="144">A livelie vine of greene sea agget spread;</l>
<l n="145">Where by one hand, light headed <name>Bacchus</name> hoong,</l>
<l n="146">And with the other, wine from grapes Out wroong.</l>
<l n="147">Of Christall shining faire, the pavement was,</l>
<l n="148">The towne of <name>Sestos</name> cal'd it <name>Venus</name> glasse.</l>
<l n="149">There might you see the gods in sundrie shapes,</l>
<l n="150">Committing headdie ryots, incest, rapes:</l>
<l n="151">For know, that underneath this radiant floure,</l>
<l n="152">Was <name>Danaes</name> statue in a brazen tower,</l>
<l n="153"><name>Jove</name>, slylie stealing from his sisters bed,</l>
<l n="154">To dallie with <name>Idalian Ganimed</name>:</l>
<l n="155">And for his love <name>Europa</name>, bellowing loud,</l>
<l n="156">And tumbling with the Rainbow in a cloud:</l>
<l n="157">Blood-quaffing <name>Mars</name>, heaving the yron net,</l>
<l n="158">Which limping <name>Vulcan</name> and his <name>Cyclops</name> set:</l>
<l n="159">Love kindling fire, to burne such townes as <name>Troy</name>,</l>
<l n="160"><name>Sylvanus</name> weeping for the lovely boy</l>
<l n="161">That now is turn'd into a <name>Cypres</name> tree,</l>
<l n="162">Under whose shade the Wood-gods love to bee.</l>
<l n="163">And in the midst a silver altar stood,</l>
<l n="164">There <name>Hero</name> sacrificing turtles blood,</l>
<l n="165">Vaild to the ground, vailing her eie-lids close,</l>
<l n="166">And modestly they opened as she rose:</l>
<l n="167">Thence flew Loves arrow with the golden head,</l>
<l n="168">And thus <name>Leander</name> was enamoured.</l>
<l n="169">Stone still he stood, and evermore he gazed,</l>
<l n="170">Till with the fire that from his count'nance blazed,</l>
<l n="171">Relenting <name>Heroes</name> gentle heart was strooke,</l>
<l n="172"><quote>Such force and vertue hath an amorous looke.</quote></l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="173">It lies not in our power to love, or hate,</l>
<l n="174">For will in us is over-rul'd by fate.</l>
<l n="175">When two are stript, long ere the course begin,</l>
<l n="176">We wish that one should loose, the other win.</l>
<l n="177">And one especiallie doe we affect,</l>
<l n="178">Of two gold Ingots like in each respect.</l>
<l n="179">The reason no man knowes, let it suffise,</l>
<l n="180">What we behold is censur'd by our eies.</l>
<l n="181">Where both deliberat, the love is slight,</l>
<l n="182">Who ever lov'd, that lov'd not at first sight?</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="183">He kneel'd, but unto her devoutly praid;</l>
<l n="184">Chast <name>Hero</name> to her selfe thus softly said:</l>
<l n="185">Were I the saint hee worships, I would heare him,</l>
<l n="186">And as shee spake those words, came somewhat nere him.</l>
<l n="187">He started up, she blusht as one asham'd;</l>
<l n="188">Wherewith <name>Leander</name> much more was inflam'd.</l>
<l n="189">He toucht her hand, in touching it she trembled,</l>
<l n="190"><quote>Love deepely grounded, hardly is dissembled.</quote></l>
<l n="191">These lovers parled by the touch of hands,</l>
<l n="192">True love is mute, and oft amazed stands.</l>
<l n="193">Thus while dum signs their yeelding harts entangled,</l>
<l n="194">The aire with sparkes of living fire was spangled,</l>
<l n="195">And night deepe drencht in mystie <name>Acheron</name>,</l>
<l n="196">Heav'd up her head, and halfe the world upon,</l>
<l n="197">Breath'd darkenesse forth (darke night is <name>Cupids</name> day.)</l>
<l n="198">And now begins <name>Leander</name> to display</l>
<l n="199">Loves holy fire, with words, with sighs and teares,</l>
<l n="200">Which like sweet musicke entred <name>Heroes</name> eares,</l>
<l n="201">And yet at everie word shee turn'd aside,</l>
<l n="202">And alwaies cut him off as he replide.</l>
<l n="203">At last, like to a bold sharpe Sophister,</l>
<l n="204">With chearefull hope thus he accosted her.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="205">Faire creature, let me speake without offence,</l>
<l n="206">I would my rude words had the influence,</l>
<l n="207">To lead thy thoughts, as thy faire lookes doe mine,</l>
<l n="208">Then shouldst thou bee his prisoner who is thine.</l>
<l n="209">Be not unkind and faire, mishapen stuffe</l>
<l n="210">Are of behaviour boisterous and ruffe.</l>
<l n="211">O shun me not, but heare me ere you goe,</l>
<l n="212">God knowes I cannot force love, as you doe.</l>
<l n="213">My words shall be as spotlesse as my youth,</l>
<l n="214">Full of simplicitie and naked truth.</l>
<l n="215">This sacrifice (whose sweet perfume descending,</l>
<l n="216">From <name>Venus</name> altar to your footsteps bending)</l>
<l n="217">Doth testifie that you exceed her farre,</l>
<l n="218">To whom you offer, and whose Nunne you are.</l>
<l n="219">Why should you worship her? her you surpasse,</l>
<l n="220">As much as sparkling Diamonds flaring glasse.</l>
<l n="221">A Diamond set in lead his worth retaines,</l>
<l n="222">A heavenly Nimph, belov'd of humane swaines,</l>
<l n="223">Receives no blemish, but oft-times more grace,</l>
<l n="224">Which makes me hope, although I am but base,</l>
<l n="225">Base in respect of thee, divine and pure,</l>
<l n="226">Dutifull service may thy love procure,</l>
<l n="227">And I in dutie will excell all other,</l>
<l n="228">As thou in beautie doest exceed Loves mother.</l>
<l n="229">Nor heaven, nor thou, were made to gaze upon,</l>
<l n="230">As heaven preserves all things, so save thou one.</l>
<l n="231">A stately builded ship, well rig'd and tall,</l>
<l n="232">The Ocean maketh more majesticall:</l>
<l n="233">Why vowest thou then to live in <name>Sestos</name> here,</l>
<l n="234">Who on Loves seas more glorious wouldst appeare?</l>
<l n="235">Like untun'd golden strings all women are,</l>
<l n="236">Which long time lie untoucht, will harshly jarre.</l>
<l n="237">Vessels of Brasse oft handled, brightly shine,</l>
<l n="238">What difference betwixt the richest mine</l>
<l n="239">And basest mold, but use? for both not us'de,</l>
<l n="240">Are of like worth. Then treasure is abus'de,</l>
<l n="241">When misers keepe it; being put to lone,</l>
<l n="242">In time it will returne us two for one.</l>
<l n="243">Rich robes, themselves and others do adorne,</l>
<l n="244">Neither themselves nor others, if not worne.</l>
<l n="245">Who builds a pallace and rams up the gate,</l>
<l n="246">Shall see it ruinous and desolate.</l>
<l n="247">Ah simple <name>Hero</name>, learne thy selfe to cherish,</l>
<l n="248">Lone women like to emptie houses perish.</l>
<l n="249">Lesse sinnes the poore rich man that starves himselfe,</l>
<l n="250">In heaping up a masse of drossie pelfe,</l>
<l n="251">Than such as you: his golden earth remains,</l>
<l n="252">Which after his disceasse, some other gains.</l>
<l n="253">But this faire jem, sweet in the losse alone,</l>
<l n="254">When you fleet hence, can be bequeath'd to none.</l>
<l n="255">Or if it could, downe from th'enameld skie,</l>
<l n="256">All heaven would come to claime this legacie,</l>
<l n="257">And with intestine broiles the world destroy,</l>
<l n="258">And quite confound natures sweet harmony.</l>
<l n="259">Well therefore by the gods decreed it is,</l>
<l n="260">We humane creatures should enjoy that blisse.</l>
<l n="261">One is no number, mayds are nothing then,</l>
<l n="262">Without the sweet societie of men.</l>
<l n="263">Wilt thou live single still? one shalt thou bee,</l>
<l n="264">Though never-singling <name>Hymen</name> couple thee.</l>
<l n="265">Wild savages, that drinke of running springs,</l>
<l n="266">Thinke water farre excels all earthly things:</l>
<l n="267">But they that dayly tast neat wine, despise it.</l>
<l n="268">Virginitie, albeit some highly prise it,</l>
<l n="269">Compar'd with marriage, had you tried them both,</l>
<l n="270">Differs as much, as wine and water doth.</l>
<l n="271">Base boullion for the stampes sake we allow,</l>
<l n="272">Even so for mens impression do we you.</l>
<l n="273">By which alone, our reverend fathers say,</l>
<l n="274">Women receave perfection everie way.</l>
<l n="275">This idoll which you terme <name>Virginitie</name>,</l>
<l n="276">Is neither essence subject to the eie,</l>
<l n="277">No, nor to any one exterior sence,</l>
<l n="278">Nor hath it any place of residence,</l>
<l n="279">Nor is't of earth or mold celestiall,</l>
<l n="280">Or capable of any forme at all.</l>
<l n="281">Of that which hath no being, doe not boast,</l>
<l n="282">Things that are not at all, are never lost.</l>
<l n="283">Men foolishly doe call it vertuous,</l>
<l n="284">What vertue is it that is borne with us?</l>
<l n="285">Much lesse can honour bee ascrib'd thereto,</l>
<l n="286">Honour is purchac'd by the deedes wee do.</l>
<l n="287">Beleeve me <name>Hero</name>, honour is not wone,</l>
<l n="288">Untill some honourable deed be done.</l>
<l n="289">Seeke you for chastitie, immortall fame,</l>
<l n="290">And know that some have wrong'd <name>Dianas</name> name?</l>
<l n="291">Whose name is it, if she be false or not,</l>
<l n="292">So she be faire, but some vile toongs will blot?</l>
<l n="293">But you are faire (aye me) so wondrous faire,</l>
<l n="294">So yoong, so gentle, and so debonaire,</l>
<l n="295">As <name>Greece</name> will thinke, if thus you live alone,</l>
<l n="296">Some one or other keepes you as his owne.</l>
<l n="297">Then <name>Hero</name> hate me not, nor from me flie,</l>
<l n="298">To follow swiftly blasting infamie.</l>
<l n="299">Perhaps, thy sacred Priesthood makes thee loath,</l>
<l n="300">Tell me, to whom mad'st thou that heedlesse oath?</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="301">To <name>Venus</name>, answered shee, and as shee spake,</l>
<l n="302">Foorth from those two tralucent cesternes brake,</l>
<l n="303">A streame of liquid pearle, which downe her face</l>
<l n="304">Made milk-white paths, wheron the gods might trace</l>
<l n="305">To <name>Joves</name> high court. Hee thus replide: The rites</l>
<l n="306">In which Loves beauteous Empresse most delites,</l>
<l n="307">Are banquets, Dorick musicke, midnight-revell,</l>
<l n="308">Plaies, maskes, and all that stern age counteth evill.</l>
<l n="309">Thee as a holy Idiot doth she scorne,</l>
<l n="310">For thou in vowing chastitie, hast sworne</l>
<l n="311">To rob her name and honour, and thereby</l>
<l n="312">Commit'st a sinne far worse than perjurie.</l>
<l n="313">Even sacrilege against her Deitie,</l>
<l n="314">Through regular and formall puritie.</l>
<l n="315">To expiat which sinne, kisse and shake hands,</l>
<l n="316">Such sacrifice as this, <name>Venus</name> demands.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="317">Thereat she smild, and did denie him so,</l>
<l n="318">As put thereby, yet might he hope for mo.</l>
<l n="319">Which makes him quickly re-enforce his speech,</l>
<l n="320">And her in humble manner thus beseech.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="321">Though neither gods nor men may thee deserve,</l>
<l n="322">Yet for her sake whom you have vow'd to serve,</l>
<l n="323">Abandon fruitlesse cold Virginitie,</l>
<l n="324">The gentle queene of Loves sole enemie.</l>
<l n="325">Then shall you most resemble <name>Venus</name> Nun,</l>
<l n="326">When <name>Venus</name> sweet rites are perform'd and done.</l>
<l n="327">Flint-brested <name>Pallas</name> joies in single life,</l>
<l n="328">But <name>Pallas</name> and your mistresse are at strife.</l>
<l n="329">Love <name>Hero</name> then, and be not tirannous,</l>
<l n="330">But heale the heart, that thou hast wounded thus,</l>
<l n="331">Nor staine thy youthfull years with avarice,</l>
<l n="332">Faire fooles delight to be accounted nice.</l>
<l n="333">The richest corne dies, if it be not reapt,</l>
<l n="334">Beautie alone is lost, too warily kept.</l>
<l n="335">These arguments he us'de, and many more,</l>
<l n="336">Wherewith she yeelded, that was woon before.</l>
<l n="337"><name>Heroes</name> lookes yeelded, but her words made warre,</l>
<l n="338">Women are woon when they begin to jarre.</l>
<l n="339">Thus having swallow'd <name>Cupids</name> golden hooke,</l>
<l n="340">The more she striv'd, the deeper was she strooke.</l>
<l n="341">Yet evilly faining anger, strove she still,</l>
<l n="342">And would be thought to graunt against her will.</l>
<l n="343">So having paus'd a while, at last shee said:</l>
<l n="344">Who taught thee Rhethoricke to deceive a maid?</l>
<l n="345">Aye me, such words as these should I abhor,</l>
<l n="346">And yet I like them for the Orator.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="347">With that <name>Leander</name> stoopt, to have imbrac'd her,</l>
<l n="348">But from his spreading armes away she cast her,</l>
<l n="349">And thus bespake him: Gentle youth forbeare</l>
<l n="350">To touch the sacred garments which I weare.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="351">Upon a rocke, and underneath a hill,</l>
<l n="352">Far from the towne (where all is whist and still,</l>
<l n="353">Save that the sea playing on yellow sand,</l>
<l n="354">Sends foorth a ratling murmure to the land,</l>
<l n="355">Whose sound allures the golden <name>Morpheus</name>,</l>
<l n="356">In silence of the night to visite us,)</l>
<l n="357">My turret stands, and there God knowes I play</l>
<l n="358">With <name>Venus</name> swannes and sparrowes all the day.</l>
<l n="359">A dwarfish beldame beares me companie,</l>
<l n="360">That hops about the chamber where I lie,</l>
<l n="361">And spends the night (that might be better spent)</l>
<l n="362">In vaine discourse, and apish merriment.</l>
<l n="363">Come thither; As she spake this, her toong tript,</l>
<l n="364">For unawares <quote>(Come thither)</quote> from her slipt,</l>
<l n="365">And sodainly her former colour chang'd,</l>
<l n="366">And here and there her eies through anger rang'd.</l>
<l n="367">And like a planet, mooving severall wales,</l>
<l n="368">At one selfe instant, she poore soule assaies,</l>
<l n="369">Loving, not to love at all, and everie part</l>
<l n="370">Strove to resist the motions of her hart.</l>
<l n="371">And hands so pure, so innocent, nay such,</l>
<l n="372">As might have made heaven stoope to have a touch,</l>
<l n="373">Did she uphold to <name>Venus</name>, and againe,</l>
<l n="374">Vow'd spotlesse chastitie, but all in vaine.</l>
<l n="375"><name>Cupid</name> beats downe her praiers with his wings,</l>
<l n="376">Her vowes above the emptie aire he flings:</l>
<l n="377">All deepe enrag'd, his sinowie bow he bent,</l>
<l n="378">And shot a shaft that burning from him went,</l>
<l n="379">Wherewith she strooken, look'd so dolefully,</l>
<l n="380">As made Love sigh, to see his tirannie.</l>
<l n="381">And as she wept, her teares to pearle he turn'd,</l>
<l n="382">And wound them on his arme, and for her mourn'd:</l>
<l n="383">Then towards the pallace of the Destinies,</l>
<l n="384">Laden with languishment and griefe he flies.</l>
<l n="385">And to those sterne nymphs humblie made request,</l>
<l n="386">Both might enjoy ech other, and be blest.</l>
<l n="387">But with a ghastly dreadfull countenaunce,</l>
<l n="388">Threatning a thousand deaths at everie glaunce,</l>
<l n="389">They answered Love, nor would vouchsafe so much</l>
<l n="390">As one poore word, their hate to him was such.</l>
<l n="391">Harken a while, and I will tell you why:</l>
<l n="392">Heavens winged herrald, <name>Jove-borne Mercury</name>,</l>
<l n="393">The self-same day that he asleepe had layd</l>
<l n="394">Inchaunted <name>Argus</name>, spied a countrie mayd,</l>
<l n="395">Whose carelesse haire, in stead of pearle t'adorne it,</l>
<l n="396">Glist'red with deaw, as one that seem'd to skorne it:</l>
<l n="397">Her breath as fragrant as the morning rose,</l>
<l n="398">Her mind pure, and her toong untaught to glose.</l>
<l n="399">Yet prowd she was, (for loftie pride that dwels</l>
<l n="400">In tow'red courts, is oft in sheapheards cels.)</l>
<l n="401">And too too well the faire vermilion knew,</l>
<l n="402">And silver tincture of her cheekes, that drew</l>
<l n="403">The love of everie swaine: On her, this god</l>
<l n="404">Enamoured was, and with his snakie rod,</l>
<l n="405">Did charme her nimble feet, and made her stay,</l>
<l n="406">The while upon a hillocke downe he lay,</l>
<l n="407">And sweetly on his pipe began to play,</l>
<l n="408">And with smooth speech, her fancie to assay,</l>
<l n="409">Till in his twining armes he lockt her fast,</l>
<l n="410">And then he woo'd with kisses, and at last,</l>
<l n="411">As sheap-heards do, her on the ground hee layd,</l>
<l n="412">And tumbling in the grasse, he often strayd</l>
<l n="413">Beyond the bounds of shame, in being bold</l>
<l n="414">To eie those parts, which no eie should behold.</l>
<l n="415">And like an insolent commaunding lover,</l>
<l n="416">Boasting his parentage, would needs discover</l>
<l n="417">The way to new <name>Elisium</name>: but she,</l>
<l n="418">Whose only dower was her chastitie,</l>
<l n="419">Having striv'ne in vaine, was now about to crie,</l>
<l n="420">And crave the helpe of sheap-heards that were nie.</l>
<l n="421">Herewith he stayd his furie, and began</l>
<l n="422">To give her leave to rise: away she ran,</l>
<l n="423">After went <name>Mercurie</name>, who us'd such cunning,</l>
<l n="424">As she to heare his tale, left off her running.</l>
<l n="425">Maids are not woon by brutish force and might,</l>
<l n="426">But speeches full of pleasure and delight.</l>
<l n="427">And knowing <name>Hermes</name> courted her, was glad</l>
<l n="428">That she such lovelinesse and beautie had</l>
<l n="429">As could provoke his liking, yet was mute,</l>
<l n="430">And neither would denie, nor graunt his sute.</l>
<l n="431">Still vowd he love, she wanting no excuse</l>
<l n="432">To feed him with delaies, as women use:</l>
<l n="433">Or thirsting after immortalitie,</l>
<l n="434">All women are ambitious naturallie:</l>
<l n="435">Impos'd upon her lover such a taske,</l>
<l n="436">As he ought not performe, nor yet she aske.</l>
<l n="437">A draught of flowing <name>Nectar</name>, she requested,</l>
<l n="438">Wherewith the king of Gods and men is feasted.</l>
<l n="439">He readie to accomplish what she wil'd,</l>
<l n="440">Stole some from <name>Hebe</name> (<name>Hebe</name>, <name>Joves</name> cup fil'd,)</l>
<l n="441">And gave it to his simple rustike love,</l>
<l n="442">Which being knowne (as what is hid from <name>Jove</name>?)</l>
<l n="443">He inly storm'd, and waxt more furious,</l>
<l n="444">Than for the fire filcht by <name>Prometheus</name>;</l>
<l n="445">And thrusts him down from heaven: he wandring here,</l>
<l n="446">In mournfull tearmes, with sad and heavie cheare</l>
<l n="447">Complaind to <name>Cupid</name>; <name>Cupid</name> for his sake,</l>
<l n="448">To be reveng'd on <name>Jove</name>, did undertake,</l>
<l n="449">And those on whom heaven, earth, and hell relies,</l>
<l n="450">I mean the Adamantine Destinies,</l>
<l n="451">He wounds with love, and forst them equallie,</l>
<l n="452">To dote upon deceitfull <name>Mercurie</name>.</l>
<l n="453">They offred him the deadly fatall knife,</l>
<l n="454">That sheares the slender threads of humane life,</l>
<l n="455">At his faire feathered feet, the engins layd,</l>
<l n="456">Which th'earth from ougly <name>Chaos</name> den up-wayd:</l>
<l n="457">These he regarded not, but did intreat,</l>
<l n="458">That <name>Jove</name>, usurper of his fathers seat,</l>
<l n="459">Might presently be banisht into hell,</l>
<l n="460">And aged <name>Saturne</name> in <name>Olympus</name> dwell.</l>
<l n="461">They granted what he crav'd, and once againe,</l>
<l n="462"><name>Saturne</name> and <name>Ops</name>, began their golden raigne.</l>
<l n="463">Murder, rape, warre, lust and trecherie,</l>
<l n="464">Were with <name>Jove</name> clos'd in <name>Stigian</name> Emperie.</l>
<l n="465">But long this blessed time continued not;</l>
<l n="466">As soone as he his wished purpose got,</l>
<l n="467">He recklesse of his promise, did despise</l>
<l n="468">The love of th'everlasting Destinies.</l>
<l n="469">They seeing it, both Love and him abhor'd,</l>
<l n="470">And <name>Jupiter</name> unto his place restor'd.</l>
<l n="471">And but that Learning, in despight of Fate,</l>
<l n="472">Will mount aloft, and enter heaven gate,</l>
<l n="473">And to the seat of <name>Jove</name> it selfe advaunce,</l>
<l n="474"><name>Hermes</name> had slept in hell with ignoraunce.</l>
<l n="475">Yet as a punishment they added this,</l>
<l n="476">That he and <name>Povertie</name> should alwaies kis.</l>
<l n="477">And to this day is everie scholler poore,</l>
<l n="478">Grosse gold, from them runs headlong to the boore.</l>
<l n="479">Likewise the angrie sisters thus deluded,</l>
<l n="480">To venge themselves on <name>Hermes</name>, have concluded</l>
<l n="481">That <name>Midas</name> brood shall sit in Honors chaire,</l>
<l n="482">To which the <name>Muses</name> sonnes are only heire:</l>
<l n="483">And fruitfull wits that in aspiring are,</l>
<l n="484">Shall discontent run into regions farre;</l>
<l n="485">And few great lords in vertuous deeds shall joy,</l>
<l n="486">But be surpris'd with every garish toy.</l>
<l n="487">And still inrich the loftie servile clowne,</l>
<l n="488">Who with incroching guile, keepes learning downe.</l>
<l n="489">Then muse not, <name>Cupids</name> sute no better sped,</l>
<l n="490">Seeing in their loves, the Fates were injured.</l>
<!--trailer omitted--></lg>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="sestyad" n="2">
<argument><head>THE ARGUMENT OF THE SECOND SESTYAD</head>
<l n="1"><name>Hero</name> of love takes deeper sence,</l>
<l n="2">And doth her love more recompence.</l>
<l n="3">Their first nights meeting, where sweet kisses</l>
<l n="4">Are th'only crownes of both their blisses.</l>
<l n="5">He swims t'<name>Abydus</name>, and returnes;</l>
<l n="6">Cold <name>Neptune</name>with his beautie burnes,</l>
<l n="7">Whose suite he shuns, and doth aspire</l>
<l n="8"><name>Heros</name> faire towre, and his desire.</l></argument>

<lg><l n="9">By this, sad <name>Hero</name>, with love unacquainted,</l>
<l n="10">Viewing <name>Leanders</name> face, fell downe and fainted.</l>
<l n="11">He kist her, and breath'd life into her lips,</l>
<l n="12">Wherewith as one displeas'd, away she trips.</l>
<l n="13">Yet as she went, full often look'd behind,</l>
<l n="14">And many poore excuses did she find,</l>
<l n="15">To linger by the way, and once she stayd,</l>
<l n="16">And would have turn'd againe, but was afrayd,</l>
<l n="17">In offring parlie, to be counted light.</l>
<l n="18">So on she goes, and in her idle flight,</l>
<l n="19">Her painted fanne of curled plumes let fall,</l>
<l n="20">Thinking to traine <name>Leander</name> therewithall.</l>
<l n="21">He being a novice, knew not what she meant,</l>
<l n="22">But stayd, and after her a letter sent.</l>
<l n="23">Which joyfull <name>Hero</name> answerd in such sort,</l>
<l n="24">As he had hope to scale the beauteous fort,</l>
<l n="25">Wherein the liberall graces lock'd their wealth,</l>
<l n="26">And therefore to her tower he got by stealth.</l>
<l n="27">Wide open stood the doore, hee need not clime,</l>
<l n="28">And she her selfe before the pointed time,</l>
<l n="29">Had spread the boord, with roses strowed the roome,</l>
<l n="30">And oft look't out, and mus'd he did not come.</l>
<l n="31">At last he came, O who can tell the greeting,</l>
<l n="32">These greedie lovers had, at their first meeting.</l>
<l n="33">He askt, she gave, and nothing was denied,</l>
<l n="34">Both to each other quickly were affied.</l>
<l n="35">Looke how their hands, so were their hearts united,</l>
<l n="36">And what he did, she willingly requited.</l>
<l n="37">(Sweet are the kisses, the imbracements sweet,</l>
<l n="38">When like desires and affections meet,</l>
<l n="39">For from the earth to heaven, is <name>Cupid</name> rais'd,</l>
<l n="40">Where fancie is in equall ballance pais'd.)</l>
<l n="41">Yet she this rashnesse sodainly repented,</l>
<l n="42">And turn'd aside, and to her selfe lamented.</l>
<l n="43">As if her name and honour had beene wrong'd,</l>
<l n="44">By being possest of him for whom she long'd:</l>
<l n="45">I, and shee wisht, albeit not from her hart,</l>
<l n="46">That he would leave her turret and depart.</l>
<l n="47">The mirthfull God of amorous pleasure smil'd,</l>
<l n="48">To see how he this captive Nymph beguil'd.</l>
<l n="49">For hitherto hee did but fan the fire,</l>
<l n="50">And kept it downe that it might mount the hier.</l>
<l n="51">Now waxt she jealous, least his love abated,</l>
<l n="52">Fearing her owne thoughts made her to be hated.</l>
<l n="53">Therefore unto him hastily she goes,</l>
<l n="54">And like light <name>Salmacis</name>, her body throes</l>
<l n="55">Upon his bosome, where with yeelding eyes,</l>
<l n="56">She offers up her selfe a sacrifice,</l>
<l n="57">To slake his anger, if he were displeas'd,</l>
<l n="58">O what god would not therewith be appeas'd?</l>
<l n="59">Like <name>Aesops</name> cocke, this jewell he enjoyed,</l>
<l n="60">And as a brother with his sister toyed,</l>
<l n="61">Supposing nothing else was to be done,</l>
<l n="62">Now he her favour and good will had wone.</l>
<l n="63">But know you not that creatures wanting sence,</l>
<l n="64">By nature have a mutuall appetence,</l>
<l n="65">And wanting organs to advaunce a step,</l>
<l n="66">Mov'd by Loves force, unto ech other lep?</l>
<l n="67">Much more in subjects having intellect,</l>
<l n="68">Some hidden influence breeds like effect.</l>
<l n="69">Albeit <name>Leander</name> rude in love, and raw,</l>
<l n="70">Long dallying with <name>Hero</name>, nothing saw</l>
<l n="71">That might delight him more, yet he suspected</l>
<l n="72">Some amorous rites or other were neglected.</l>
<l n="73">Therefore unto his bodie, hirs he clung,</l>
<l n="74">She, fearing on the rushes to be flung,</l>
<l n="75">Striv'd with redoubled strength: the more she strived,</l>
<l n="76">The more a gentle pleasing heat revived,</l>
<l n="77">Which taught him all that elder lovers know,</l>
<l n="78">And now the same gan so to scorch and glow,</l>
<l n="79">As in plaine termes (yet cunningly) he crav'd it,</l>
<l n="80">Love alwaies makes those eloquent that have it.</l>
<l n="81">Shee, with a kind of graunting, put him by it,</l>
<l n="82">And ever as he thought himselfe most nigh it,</l>
<l n="83">Like to the tree of <name>Tantalus</name> she fled,</l>
<l n="84">And seeming lavish, sav'de her maydenhead.</l>
<l n="85">Ne're king more sought to keepe his diademe,</l>
<l n="86">Than <name>Hero</name> this inestimable gemme.</l>
<l n="87">Above our life we love a stedfast friend,</l>
<l n="88">Yet when a token of great worth we send,</l>
<l n="89">We often kisse it, often looke thereon,</l>
<l n="90">And stay the messenger that would be gon:</l>
<l n="91">No marvell then, though <name>Hero</name> would not yeeld</l>
<l n="92">So soone to part from that she deerely held.</l>
<l n="93">Jewels being lost are found againe, this never,</l>
<l n="94">T'is lost but once, and once lost, lost for ever.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="95">Now had the morne espy'de her lovers steeds,</l>
<l n="96">Whereat she starts, puts on her purple weeds,</l>
<l n="97">And red for anger that he stayd so long,</l>
<l n="98">All headlong throwes her selfe the clouds among</l>
<l n="99">And now <name>Leander</name> fearing to be mist,</l>
<l n="100">Imbrast her sodainly, tooke leave, and kist,</l>
<l n="101">Long was he taking leave, and loath to go,</l>
<l n="102">And kist againe, as lovers use to do.</l>
<l n="103">Sad <name>Hero</name> wroong him by the hand, and wept,</l>
<l n="104">Saying, let your vowes and promises be kept.</l>
<l n="105">Then standing at the doore, she turnd about,</l>
<l n="106">As loath to see <name>Leander</name> going out.</l>
<l n="107">And now the sunne that through th'orizon peepes,</l>
<l n="108">As pittying these lovers, downeward creepes.</l>
<l n="109">So that in silence of the cloudie night,</l>
<l n="110">Though it was morning, did he take his flight.</l>
<l n="111">But what the secret trustie night conceal'd,</l>
<l n="112"><name>Leanders</name> amorous habit soone reveal'd.</l>
<l n="113">With <name>Cupids</name> myrtle was his bonet crownd,</l>
<l n="114">About his armes the purple riband wound,</l>
<l n="115">Wherewith she wreath'd her largely spreading heare,</l>
<l n="116">Nor could the youth abstaine, but he must weare</l>
<l n="117">The sacred ring wherewith she was endow'd,</l>
<l n="118">When first religious chastitie she vow'd:</l>
<l n="119">Which made his love through <name>Sestos</name> to bee knowne,</l>
<l n="120">And thence unto <name>Abydus</name> sooner blowne,</l>
<l n="121">Than he could saile, for incorporeal Fame,</l>
<l n="122">Whose waight consists in nothing but her name,</l>
<l n="123">Is swifter than the wind, whose tardie plumes,</l>
<l n="124">Are reeking water, and dull earthlie fumes.</l>
<l n="125">Home when he came, he seem'd not to be there,</l>
<l n="126">But like exiled aire thrust from his sphere,</l>
<l n="127">Set in a forren place, and straight from thence,</l>
<l n="128"><name>Alcides</name> like, by mightie violence,</l>
<l n="129">He would have chac'd away the swelling maine,</l>
<l n="130">That him from her unjustly did detaine.</l>
<l n="131">Like as the sunne in a Dyameter,</l>
<l n="132">Fires and inflames objects remooved farre,</l>
<l n="133">And heateth kindly, shining lat'rally;</l>
<l n="134">So beautie, sweetly quickens when t'is ny,</l>
<l n="135">But being separated and remooved,</l>
<l n="136">Burnes where it cherisht, murders where it loved.</l>
<l n="137">Therefore even as an Index to a booke,</l>
<l n="138">So to his mind was yoong <name>Leanders</name> looke.</l>
<l n="139">O none but gods have power their love to hide,</l>
<l n="140">Affection by the count'nance is descride.</l>
<l n="141">The light of hidden fire it selfe discovers,</l>
<l n="142">And love that is conceal'd, betraies poore lovers.</l>
<l n="143">His secret flame apparantly was seene,</l>
<l n="144"><name>Leanders</name> Father knew where hee had beene,</l>
<l n="145">And for the same mildly rebuk't his sonne,</l>
<l n="146">Thinking to quench the sparckles new begonne.</l>
<l n="147">But love resisted once, growes passionate,</l>
<l n="148">And nothing more than counsaile, lovers hate.</l>
<l n="149">For as a hote prowd horse highly disdaines,</l>
<l n="150">To have his head control'd, but breakes the raines,</l>
<l n="151">Spits foorth the ringled bit, and with his hoves,</l>
<l n="152">Checkes the submissive ground: so hee that loves,</l>
<l n="153">The more he is restrain'd, the woorse he fares,</l>
<l n="154">What is it now, but mad <name>Leander</name> dares?</l>
<l n="155">O <name>Hero</name>, <name>Hero</name>, thus he cry'de full oft,</l>
<l n="156">And then he got him to a rocke aloft.</l>
<l n="157">Where having spy'de her tower, long star'd he on't,</l>
<l n="158">And pray'd the narrow toyling <name>Hellespont</name>,</l>
<l n="159">To part in twaine, that hee might come and go,</l>
<l n="160">But still the rising billowes answered no.</l>
<l n="161">With that hee stript him to the yv'rie skin,</l>
<l n="162">And crying, Love I come, leapt lively in.</l>
<l n="163">Whereat the saphir visag'd god grew prowd,</l>
<l n="164">And made his capring <name>Triton</name> sound alowd,</l>
<l n="165">Imagining, that <name>Ganimed</name> displeas'd,</l>
<l n="166">Had left the heavens, therefore on him hee seaz'd.</l>
<l n="167"><name>Leander</name> striv'd, the waves about him wound,</l>
<l n="168">And puld him to the bottome, where the ground</l>
<l n="169">Was strewd with pearle, and in low corrall groves,</l>
<l n="170">Sweet singing Meremaids, sported with their loves</l>
<l n="171">On heapes of heavie gold, and tooke great pleasure,</l>
<l n="172">To spurne in carelesse sort, the shipwracke treasure.</l>
<l n="173">For here the stately azure pallace stood,</l>
<l n="174">Where kingly <name>Neptune</name> and his traine abode.</l>
<l n="175">The lustie god imbrast him, cald him love,</l>
<l n="176">And swore he never should returne to <name>Jove</name>.</l>
<l n="177">But when he knew it was not <name>Ganimed</name>,</l>
<l n="178">For under water he was almost dead,</l>
<l n="179">He heav'd him up, and looking on his face,</l>
<l n="180">Beat downe the bold waves with his triple mace,</l>
<l n="181">Which mounted up, intending to have kist him,</l>
<l n="182">And fell in drops like teares, because they mist him.</l>
<l n="183"><name>Leander</name> being up, began to swim,</l>
<l n="184">And looking backe, saw <name>Neptune</name> follow him.</l>
<l n="185">Whereat agast, the poore soule gan to crie,</l>
<l n="186">O let mee visite <name>Hero</name> ere I die.</l>
<l n="187">The god put <name>Helles</name> bracelet on his arme,</l>
<l n="188">And swore the sea should never doe him harme.</l>
<l n="189">He clapt his plumpe cheekes, with his tresses playd,</l>
<l n="190">And smiling wantonly, his love bewrayd.</l>
<l n="191">He watcht his armes, and as they opend wide,</l>
<l n="192">At every stroke, betwixt them would he slide,</l>
<l n="193">And steale a kisse, and then run out and daunce,</l>
<l n="194">And as he turnd, cast many a lustfull glaunce,</l>
<l n="195">And throw him gawdie toies to please his eie,</l>
<l n="196">And dive into the water, and there prie</l>
<l n="197">Upon his brest, his thighs, and everie lim,</l>
<l n="198">And up againe, and close beside him swim,</l>
<l n="199">And talke of love: <name>Leander</name> made replie,</l>
<l n="200">You are deceav'd, I am no woman I.</l>
<l n="201">Thereat smilde <name>Neptune</name>, and then told a tale,</l>
<l n="202">How that a sheapheard sitting in a vale,</l>
<l n="203">Playd with a boy so faire and so kind,</l>
<l n="204">As for his love, both earth and heaven pyn'd;</l>
<l n="205">That of the cooling river durst not drinke,</l>
<l n="206">Least water-nymphs should pull him from the brinke.</l>
<l n="207">And when hee sported in the fragrant lawnes,</l>
<l n="208">Gote-footed Satyrs, and up-staring Fawnes,</l>
<l n="209">Would steale him thence. Ere halfe this tale was done,</l>
<l n="210">Aye me, <name>Leander</name> cryde, th'enamoured sunne,</l>
<l n="211">That now should shine on <name>Thetis</name> glassie bower,</l>
<l n="212">Descends upon my radiant <name>Heroes</name> tower.</l>
<l n="213">O that these tardie armes of mine were wings,</l>
<l n="214">And as he spake, upon the waves he springs.</l>
<l n="215"><name>Neptune</name> was angrie that hee gave no eare,</l>
<l n="216">And in his heart revenging malice bare:</l>
<l n="217">He flung at him his mace, but as it went,</l>
<l n="218">He cald it in, for love made him repent.</l>
<l n="219">The mace returning backe, his owne hand hit,</l>
<l n="220">As meaning to be veng'd for darting it.</l>
<l n="221">When this fresh bleeding wound <name>Leander</name> viewd,</l>
<l n="222">His colour went and came, as if he rewd</l>
<l n="223">The greefe which <name>Neptune</name> felt. In gentle brests,</l>
<l n="224">Relenting thoughts, remorse and pittie rests.</l>
<l n="225">And who have hard hearts, and obdurat minds,</l>
<l n="226">But vicious, harebraind, and illit'rat hinds?</l>
<l n="227">The god seeing him with pittie to be moved,</l>
<l n="228">Thereon concluded that he was beloved.</l>
<l n="229">(Love is too full of faith, too credulous,</l>
<l n="230">With follie and false hope deluding us.)</l>
<l n="231">Wherefore <name>Leanders</name> fancie to surprize,</l>
<l n="232">To the rich <name>Ocean</name> for gifts he flies.</l>
<l n="233">'Tis wisedome to give much, a gift prevailes,</l>
<l n="234">When deepe perswading Oratorie failes.</l>
<l n="235">By this <name>Leander</name> being nere the land,</l>
<l n="236">Cast downe his wearie feet, and felt the sand.</l>
<l n="237">Breathlesse albeit he were, he rested not,</l>
<l n="238">Till to the solitarie tower he got.</l>
<l n="239">And knockt and cald, at which celestiall noise,</l>
<l n="240">The longing heart of <name>Hero</name> much more joies</l>
<l n="241">Then nymphs and sheapheards, when the timbrell rings,</l>
<l n="242">Or crooked Dolphin when the sailer sings;</l>
<l n="243">She stayd not for her robes, but straight arose,</l>
<l n="244">And drunke with gladnesse, to the dore she goes.</l>
<l n="245">Where seeing a naked man, she scriecht for feare,</l>
<l n="246">Such sights as this, to tender maids are rare.</l>
<l n="247">And ran into the darke her selfe to hide,</l>
<l n="248">Rich jewels in the darke are soonest spide.</l>
<l n="249">Unto her was he led, or rather drawne,</l>
<l n="250">By those white limmes, which sparckled through the lawne.</l>
<l n="251">The neerer that he came, the more she fled,</l>
<l n="252">And seeking refuge, slipt into her bed.</l>
<l n="253">Whereon <name>Leander</name> sitting, thus began,</l>
<l n="254">Through numming cold, all feeble, faint and wan:</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="255">If not for love, yet love for pittie sake,</l>
<l n="256">Me in thy bed and maiden bosome take,</l>
<l n="257">At least vouchsafe these armes some little roome,</l>
<l n="258">Who hoping to imbrace thee, cherely swome.</l>
<l n="259">This head was beat with manie a churlish billow,</l>
<l n="260">And therefore let it rest upon thy pillow.</l>
<l n="261">Herewith afrighted <name>Hero</name> shrunke away,</l>
<l n="262">And in her luke-warme place <name>Leander</name> lay.</l>
<l n="263">Whose lively heat like fire from heaven fet,</l>
<l n="264">Would animate grosse clay, and higher set</l>
<l n="265">The drooping thoughts of base declining soules,</l>
<l n="266">Then drerie <name>Mars</name>, carowsing <name>Nectar</name> boules.</l>
<l n="267">His hands he cast upon her like a snare,</l>
<l n="268">She overcome with shame and sallow feare,</l>
<l n="269">Like chast <name>Diana</name>, when <name>Acteon</name> spyde her,</l>
<l n="270">Being sodainly betraide, dyv'd downe to hide her.</l>
<l n="271">And as her silver body downeward went,</l>
<l n="272">With both her hands she made the bed a tent,</l>
<l n="273">And in her owne mind thought her selfe secure,</l>
<l n="274">O'recast with dim and darksome coverture.</l>
<l n="275">And now she lets him whisper in her eare,</l>
<l n="276">Flatter, intreat, promise, protest and sweare,</l>
<l n="277">Yet ever as he greedily assayd</l>
<l n="278">To touch those dainties, she the <name>Harpey</name> playd,</l>
<l n="279">And every lim did as a soldier stout,</l>
<l n="280">Defend the fort, and keep the foe-man out.</l>
<l n="281">For though the rising yv'rie mount he scal'd,</l>
<l n="282">Which is with azure circling lines empal'd,</l>
<l n="283">Much like a globe, (a globe may I tearme this,</l>
<l n="284">By which love sailes to regions full of blis,)</l>
<l n="285">Yet there with <name>Sysiphus</name> he toyld in vaine,</l>
<l n="286">Till gentle parlie did the truce obtaine.</l>
<l n="287">Wherein <name>Leander</name> on her quivering brest,</l>
<l n="288">Breathlesse spoke some thing, and sigh'd out the rest;</l>
<l n="289">Which so prevail'd, as he with small ado,</l>
<l n="290">Inclos'd her in his armes and kist her to.</l>
<l n="291">And everie kisse to her was as a charme,</l>
<l n="292">And to <name>Leander</name> as a fresh alarme.</l>
<l n="293">So that the truce was broke, and she alas,</l>
<l n="294">(Poore sillie maiden) at his mercie was.</l>
<l n="295">Love is not ful of pittie (as men say)</l>
<l n="296">But deaffe and cruell, where he meanes to pray.</l>
<l n="297">Even as a bird, which in our hands we wring,</l>
<l n="298">Foorth plungeth, and oft flutters with her wing,</l>
<l n="299">She trembling strove, this strife of hers (like that</l>
<l n="300">Which made the world) another world begat,</l>
<l n="301">Of unknowne joy. Treason was in her thought,</l>
<l n="302">And cunningly to yeeld her selfe she sought.</l>
<l n="303">Seeming not woon, yet woon she was at length,</l>
<l n="304">In such warres women use but halfe their strength.</l>
<l n="305"><name>Leander</name> now like Theban <name>Hercules</name>,</l>
<l n="306">Entred the orchard of <name>Th'esperides</name>,</l>
<l n="307">Whose fruit none rightly can describe, but hee</l>
<l n="308">That puls or shakes it from the golden tree:</l>
<l n="309">And now she wisht this night were never done,</l>
<l n="310">And sigh'd to thinke upon th'approching sunne,</l>
<l n="311">For much it greev'd her that the bright day-light,</l>
<l n="312">Should know the pleasure of this blessed night,</l>
<l n="313">And them like <name>Mars</name> and <name>Ericine</name> displayd,</l>
<l n="314">Both in each others armes chaind as they layd.</l>
<l n="315">Againe she knew not how to frame her looke,</l>
<l n="316">Or speake to him who in a moment tooke,</l>
<l n="317">That which so long so charily she kept,</l>
<l n="318">And fame by stealth away she would have crept,</l>
<l n="319">And to some corner secretly have gone,</l>
<l n="320">Leaving <name>Leander</name> in the bed alone.</l>
<l n="321">But as her naked feet were whipping out,</l>
<l n="322">He on the suddaine cling'd her so about,</l>
<l n="323">That Meremaid-like unto the floore she slid,</l>
<l n="324">One halfe appear'd, the other halfe was hid.</l>
<l n="325">Thus neere the bed she blushing stood upright,</l>
<l n="326">And from her countenance behold ye might,</l>
<l n="327">A kind of twilight breake, which through the heare,</l>
<l n="328">As from an orient cloud, glymse here and there.</l>
<l n="329">And round about the chamber this false morne,</l>
<l n="330">Brought foorth the day before the day was borne.</l>
<l n="331">So <name>Heroes</name> ruddie cheeke, <name>Hero</name> betrayd,</l>
<l n="332">And her all naked to his sight displayd.</l>
<l n="333">Whence his admiring eyes more pleasure tooke,</l>
<l n="334">Than <name>Dis</name>, on heapes of gold fixing his looke.</l>
<l n="335">By this <name>Apollos</name> golden harpe began,</l>
<l n="336">To sound foorth musicke to the <name>Ocean</name>,</l>
<l n="337">Which watchfull <name>Hesperus</name> no sooner heard,</l>
<l n="338">But he the days bright-bearing Car prepar'd.</l>
<l n="339">And ran before, as Harbenger of light,</l>
<l n="340">And with his flaring beames mockt ougly night,</l>
<l n="341">Till she o'recome with anguish, shame, and rage,</l>
<l n="342">Dang'd downe to hell her loathsome carriage.</l>
<l n="343"><gap reason="undefined"/></l></lg>
</div>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="part" n="2">
<div type="textpart">
<ab type="opener"><ab type="salute">TO MY BEST ESTEEMED
<lb/>AND WORTHELY HONORED
<lb/>LADY, THE LADY WALSINGHAM,
<lb/>one of the Ladies of her Majesties Bed-chamber.</ab></ab>

<p><lb/>I present your Ladiship with the last affections of the first two
<lb/>Lovers that ever <name>Muse</name> shrinde in the Temple of <name>Memorie</name>; being drawne
<lb/>by strange instigation to employ some of my serious time inso trifeling
<lb/>a subject, which yet made the first Author, divine <name>Musaeus</name>, eternall. <lb/>And were it not that wee must subject our accounts of these common <lb/>received conceits to servile custome; it goes much against my hand to
<lb/>signe that for a trifling subject, on which more worthines of soule hath
<lb/>been shewed, and weight of divine wit, than can vouchsafe residence in
<lb/>the leaden gravitie of any <name>Mony-Monger</name>; in whose profession all <lb/>serious subjects are concluded. But he that shuns trifles must shun the <lb/>world; out of whose reverend heapes of substance and austeritie, I can,
<lb/>and will, ere long, single, or tumble out as brainles and passionate
<lb/>fooleries, as ever panted in the bosome of the most ridiculous Lover.
<lb/>Accept it therfore (good Madam) though as a trifle, yet as a serious
<lb/>argument of my affection: for to bee thought thankefull for all free and <lb/>honourable favours, is a great summe of that riches my whole thrift
<lb/>intendeth.</p>
<p><lb/>Such uncourtly and sillie dispositions as mine, whose contentment
<lb/>hath other objects than profit or glorie; are as glad, simply for the
<lb/>naked merit of vertue, to honour such as advance her, as others that
<lb/>are hired to commend with deepeliest politique bountie.</p>
<p><lb/>It hath therefore adjoynde much contentment to my desire of your
<lb/>true honour to heare men of desert in Court, adde to mine owne know-
<lb/>ledge of your noble disposition, how glady you doe your best to preferre
<lb/>their desires; and have as absolute respect to their meere good parts,
<lb/>as if they came perfumed and charmed with golden incitements. And
<lb/>this most sweet inclination, that flowes from the truth and eternitie of <lb/>Nobles; assure your Ladiship doth more suite your other Ornaments,
<lb/>and makes more to the advancement of your Name, and happines of
<lb/>your proceedings, then if(like others) you displaied Ensignes of state
<lb/>and sowrenes in your forehead; made smooth with nothing but sensualitie
<lb/>and presents.</p>
<p><lb/>This poore Dedication (in figure of the other unitie betwixt Sir <lb/><name>Thomas</name>and your selfe) hath rejoynd you with him, my honoured best
<lb/>friend, whose continuance of ancient kindnes to my still-obscured
<lb/>estate, though it cannot encrease my love to him, which hath ever been <lb/>entirely circulare; yet shall it encourage my deserts to their utmost <lb/>requitall, and make my hartie gratitude speake; to which the
<lb/>unhappines of my life hath hetherto been
<lb/>uncomfortable and painfull dumbnes.</p>
<ab type="signed">By your Ladiships vowd in
<lb/>most wished service:
<lb/><name>George Chapman</name>.</ab>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="sestyad" n="3">
<argument><head>THE ARGUMENT OF THE THIRD SESTYAD</head>
<l n="1"><name>Leander</name> to the envious light</l>
<l n="2">Resignes his night-sports with the night,</l>
<l n="3">And swims the <name>Hellespont</name> againe;</l>
<l n="4"><name>Thesme</name> the Deitie soveraigne</l>
<l n="5">Of Customes and religious rites</l>
<l n="6">Appeares, improving his delites</l>
<l n="7">Since Nuptiall honors he neglected;</l>
<l n="8">Which straight he vowes shall be effected.</l>
<l n="9">Faire <name>Hero</name> left Devirginate</l>
<l n="10">Waies, and with furie wailes her state:</l>
<l n="11">But with her love and womans wit</l>
<l n="12">She argues, and approveth it.</l></argument>


<lg><l n="13">New light gives new directions, Fortunes new</l>
<l n="14">To fashion our indevours that ensue,</l>
<l n="15">More harsh (at lest more hard) more grave and hie</l>
<l n="16">Our subject runs, and our sterne <name>Muse</name> must flie.</l>
<l n="17">Loves edge is taken off, and that light flame,</l>
<l n="18">Those thoughts, joyes, longings, that before became</l>
<l n="19">High unexperienst blood, and maids sharpe plights,</l>
<l n="20">Must now grow staid, and censure the delights,</l>
<l n="21">That being enjoyd aske judgement; now we praise,</l>
<l n="22">As having parted: Evenings crowne the daies.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="23">And now ye wanton loves, and yong desires,</l>
<l n="24">Pied vanitie, the mint of strange Attires;</l>
<l n="25">Ye lisping Flatteries, and obsequious Glances,</l>
<l n="26">Relentfull Musicks, and attractive Dances,</l>
<l n="27">And you detested Charmes constraining love,</l>
<l n="28">Shun loves stolne sports by that these Lovers prove.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="29">By this the Soveraigne of Heavens golden fires,</l>
<l n="30">And yong <name>Leander</name>, Lord of his desires,</l>
<l n="31">Together from their lovers armes arose:</l>
<l n="32"><name>Leander</name> into <name>Hellespontus</name> throwes</l>
<l n="33">His Hero-handled bodie, whose delight</l>
<l n="34">Made him disdaine each other Epethite.</l>
<l n="35">And as amidst the enamourd waves he swims,</l>
<l n="36">The God of gold of purpose guilt his lims,</l>
<l n="37">That this word guilt, including double sence,</l>
<l n="38">The double guilt of his <name>Incontinence</name>,</l>
<l n="39">Might be exprest, that had no stay t'employ</l>
<l n="40">The treasure which the Love-god let him joy</l>
<l n="41">In his deare <name>Hero</name>, with such sacred thrift,</l>
<l n="42">As had beseemd so sanctified a gift:</l>
<l n="43">But like a greedie vulgar Prodigall</l>
<l n="44">Would on the stock dispend, and rudely fall</l>
<l n="45">Before his time, to that unblessed blessing,</l>
<l n="46">Which for lusts plague doth perish with possessing.</l>
<l n="47"><quote>Joy graven in sence, like snow in water wasts;</quote></l>
<l n="48"><quote>Without preserve of vertue, nothing lasts.</quote></l>
<l n="49">What man is he that with a welthie eie,</l>
<l n="50">Enjoyes a beautie richer than the skie,</l>
<l n="51">Through whose white skin, softer then soundest sleep,</l>
<l n="52">With damaske eyes, the rubie blood doth peep,</l>
<l n="53">And runs in branches through her azure vaines,</l>
<l n="54">Whose mixture and first fire, his love attaines;</l>
<l n="55">Whose both hands limit both Loves deities,</l>
<l n="56">And sweeten humane thoughts like Paradise;</l>
<l n="57">Whose disposition silken is and kinde,</l>
<l n="58">Directed with an earth-exempted minde;</l>
<l n="59">Who thinks not heaven with such a love is given?</l>
<l n="60">And who like earth would spend that dower of heaven,</l>
<l n="61">With ranke desire to joy it all at first?</l>
<l n="62">What simply kils our hunger, quencheth thirst,</l>
<l n="63">Clothes but our nakednes, and makes us live,</l>
<l n="64"><name>Praise</name> doth not any of her favours give:</l>
<l n="65">But what doth plentifully minister</l>
<l n="66">Beautious apparell and delicious cheere,</l>
<l n="67">So orderd that it still excites desire,</l>
<l n="68">And still gives pleasure freenes to aspire,</l>
<l n="69">The palme of <name>Bountie</name>, ever moyst preserving:</l>
<l n="70">To loves sweet life this is the courtly carving.</l>
<l n="71">Thus <name>Time</name>, and all-states-ordering <name>Ceremonie</name></l>
<l n="72">Had banisht all offence: <name>Times</name> golden <name>Thie</name></l>
<l n="73">Upholds the flowne bodie of the earth</l>
<l n="74">In sacred harmonie, and every birth</l>
<l n="75">Of men, and actions makes legitimate,</l>
<l n="76">Being usde aright; <quote>The use of time is Fate.</quote></l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="77">Yet did the gentle flood transfer once more,</l>
<l n="78">This prize of Love home to his fathers shore;</l>
<l n="79">Where he unlades himselfe of that false welth</l>
<l n="80">That makes few rich; treasures composde by stelth;</l>
<l n="81">And to his sister kinde <name>Hermione</name>,</l>
<l n="82">(Who on the shore kneeld, praying to the sea</l>
<l n="83">For his returne) he all Loves goods did show</l>
<l n="84">In <name>Hero</name> seasde for him, in him for <name>Hero</name>.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="85">His most kinde sister all his secrets knew,</l>
<l n="86">And to her singing like a shower he flew,</l>
<l n="87">Sprinkling the earth, that to their tombs tooke in</l>
<l n="88">Streames dead for love to leave his ivorie skin,</l>
<l n="89">Which yet a snowie fome did leave above,</l>
<l n="90">As soule to the dead water that did love;</l>
<l n="91">And from thence did the first white Roses spring,</l>
<l n="92">(For love is sweet and faire in every thing)</l>
<l n="93">And all the sweetned shore as he did goe,</l>
<l n="94">Was crownd with odrous roses white as snow.</l>
<l n="95">Love-blest <name>Leander</name> was with love so filled,</l>
<l n="96">That love to all that toucht him he instilled.</l>
<l n="97">And as the colours of all things we see,</l>
<l n="98">To our sights powers communicated bee:</l>
<l n="99">So to all objects that in compasse came</l>
<l n="100">of any sence he had, his sences flame</l>
<l n="101">Flowd from his parts, with force so virtuall,</l>
<l n="102">It fir'd with sence things meere insensuall.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="103">Now (with warme baths and odours comforted)</l>
<l n="104">When he lay downe he kindly kist his bed,</l>
<l n="105">As consecrating it to <name>Heros</name> right,</l>
<l n="106">And vowd thereafter that what ever sight</l>
<l n="107">Put him in minde of <name>Hero</name>, or her blisse,</l>
<l n="108">Should be her Altar to prefer a kisse.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="109">Then laid he forth his late inriched armes,</l>
<l n="110">In whose white circle Love writ all his charmes,</l>
<l n="111">And made his characters sweet <name>Heros</name> lims,</l>
<l n="112">When on his breasts warme sea she sideling swims.</l>
<l n="113">And as those armes (held up in circle) met,</l>
<l n="114">He said; see sister, <name>Heros</name> Carquenet,</l>
<l n="115">Which she had rather weare about her neck,</l>
<l n="116">Then all the jewels that dot <name>Juno</name> deck.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="117">But as he shooke with passionate desire,</l>
<l n="118">To put in flame his other secret fire,</l>
<l n="119">A musick so divine did pierce his eare,</l>
<l n="120">As never yet his ravisht sence did heare:</l>
<l n="121">When suddenly a light of twentie hews</l>
<l n="122">Brake through the roofe, and like the Rainbow views</l>
<l n="123">Amazd <name>Leander</name>; in whose beames came downe</l>
<l n="124">The Goddesse <name>Ceremonie</name>, with a Crowne</l>
<l n="125">Of all the stars, and heaven with her descended.</l>
<l n="126">Her flaming haire to her bright feete extended,</l>
<l n="127">By which hung all the bench of Deities;</l>
<l n="128">And in a chaine, compact of eares and eies,</l>
<l n="129">She led Religion; all her bodie was</l>
<l n="130">Cleere and transparent as the purest glasse:</l>
<l n="131">For she was all presented to the sence;</l>
<l n="132">Devotion, Order, State, and Reverence,</l>
<l n="133">Her shadowes were; Societie, Memorie;</l>
<l n="134">All which her sight made live, her absence die.</l>
<l n="135">A rich disparent Pentackle she weares,</l>
<l n="136">Drawne full of circles and strange characters:</l>
<l n="137">Her face was changeable to everie eie;</l>
<l n="138">One way lookt ill, another graciouslie;</l>
<l n="139">Which while men viewd, they cheerfull were and holy:</l>
<l n="140">But looking off, vicious, and melancholy:</l>
<l n="141">The snakie paths to each observed law,</l>
<l n="142">Did <name>Policie</name> in her broad bosome draw:</l>
<l n="143">One hand a Mathematique Christall swayes,</l>
<l n="144">Which gathering in one line a thousand rayes</l>
<l n="145">From her bright eyes, <name>Confusion</name> burnes to death,</l>
<l n="146">And all estates of men distinguisheth.</l>
<l n="147">By it <name>Morallitie</name> and <name>Comelinesse</name>,</l>
<l n="148">Themselves in all their sightly figures dresse.</l>
<l n="149">Her other hand a lawrell rod applies,</l>
<l n="150">To beate back <name>Barbarisme</name>, and <name>Avarice</name>,</l>
<l n="151">That followd eating earth, and excrement</l>
<l n="152">And humane lims; and would make proud ascent</l>
<l n="153">To seates of Gods, were <name>Ceremonie</name> slaine;</l>
<l n="154">The <name>Howrs</name> and <name>Graces</name> bore her glorious traine,</l>
<l n="155">And all the sweetes of our societie</l>
<l n="156">Were Spherde, and treasurde in her bountious eie.</l>
<l n="157">Thus she appeard, and sharply did reprove</l>
<l n="158"><name>Leanders</name> bluntnes in his violent love;</l>
<l n="159">Tolde him how poore was substance without rites,</l>
<l n="160">Like bils unsignd; desires without delites;</l>
<l n="161">Like meates unseasond; like ranke corne that growes</l>
<l n="162">On Cottages, that none or reapes or sowes:</l>
<l n="163">Not being with civill forms confirm'd and bounded,</l>
<l n="164">For humane dignities and comforts founded:</l>
<l n="165">But loose and secret all their glories hide,</l>
<l n="166">Feare fils the chamber, darknes decks the Bride.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="167">She vanisht, leaving pierst <name>Leanders</name> hart</l>
<l n="168">With sence of his unceremonious part,</l>
<l n="169">In which with plaine neglect of Nuptiall rites,</l>
<l n="170">He close and flatly fell to his delites:</l>
<l n="171">And instantly he vowd to celebrate</l>
<l n="172">All rites pertaining to his maried state.</l>
<l n="173">So up he gets and to his father goes,</l>
<l n="174">To whose glad eares he doth his vowes disclose:</l>
<l n="175">The Nuptials are resolv'd with utmost powre,</l>
<l n="176">And he at night would swim to <name>Heros</name> towre.</l>
<l n="177">From whence he ment to <name>Sestus</name> forked Bay</l>
<l n="178">To bring her covertly, where ships must stay,</l>
<l n="179">Sent by his father throughly rigd and mand,</l>
<l n="180">To waft her safely to <name>Abydus</name> Strand.</l>
<l n="181">There leave we him, and with fresh wing pursue</l>
<l n="182">Astonisht <name>Hero</name>, whose most wished view</l>
<l n="183">I thus long have forborne, because I left her</l>
<l n="184">So out of countuance, and her spirits bereft her.</l>
<l n="185"><quote>To looke of one abasht is impudence,</quote></l>
<l n="186"><quote>When of sleight faults he hath too deepe a sence.</quote></l>
<l n="187">Her blushing het her chamber: she lookt out,</l>
<l n="188">And all the ayre she purpled round about,</l>
<l n="189">And after it a foule black day befell,</l>
<l n="190">Which ever since a red morne doth foretell,</l>
<l n="191">And still renewes our woes for <name>Heros</name> wo:</l>
<l n="192">And foule it prov'd, because it figur'd so</l>
<l n="193">The next nights horror, which prepare to heare;</l>
<l n="194">I faile if it prophane your daintiest eare.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="195">Then thou most strangely-intellectuall fire,</l>
<l n="196">That proper to my soule hast power t'inspire</l>
<l n="197">Her burning faculties, and with the wings</l>
<l n="198">Of thy unspheared flame visitst the springs</l>
<l n="199">Of spirits immortall; Now (as swift as Time</l>
<l n="200">Doth follow Motion) finde th'eternall Clime</l>
<l n="201">Of his free soule, whose living subject stood</l>
<l n="202">Up to the chin in the <name>Pyerean</name> flood,</l>
<l n="203">And drunke to me halfe this <name>Musean</name> stone,</l>
<l n="204">Inscribing it to deathles Memorie:</l>
<l n="205">Confer with it, and make my pledge as deepe,</l>
<l n="206">That neithers draught be consecrate to sleepe.</l>
<l n="207">Tell it how much his late desires I tender,</l>
<l n="208">(If yet it know not) and to light surrender</l>
<l n="209">My soules darke ofspring, willing it should die</l>
<l n="210">To loves, to passions, and societie.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="211">Sweet <name>Hero</name> left upon her bed alone,</l>
<l n="212">Her maidenhead, her vowes, <name>Leander</name> gone,</l>
<l n="213">And nothing with her but a violent crew</l>
<l n="214">Of new come thoughts that yet she never knew,</l>
<l n="215">Even to her selfe a stranger; was much like</l>
<l n="216">Th'<name>Iberian</name> citie that wars hand did strike</l>
<l n="217">By English force in princely <name>Essex</name> guide,</l>
<l n="218">When peace assur'd her towres had fortifide;</l>
<l n="219">And golden-fingred <name>India</name> had bestowd</l>
<l n="220">Such wealth on her, that strength and Empire flowd</l>
<l n="221">Into her Turrets; and her virgin waste</l>
<l n="222">The wealthie girdle of the Sea embraste:</l>
<l n="223">Till our <name>Leander</name> that made <name>Mars</name> his <name>Cupid</name>,</l>
<l n="224">For soft love-sutes, with iron thunders chid:</l>
<l n="225">Swum to her Towers, dissolv'd her virgin zone;</l>
<l n="226">Lead in his power, and made Confusion</l>
<l n="227">Run through her streets amazd, that she supposde</l>
<l n="228">She had not been in her owne walls inclosde:</l>
<l n="229">But rapt by wonder to some forraine state,</l>
<l n="230">Seeing all her issue so disconsolate:</l>
<l n="231">And all her peacefull mansions possest</l>
<l n="232">With wars just spoyle, and many a forraine guest</l>
<l n="233">From every corner driving an enjoyer,</l>
<l n="234">Supplying it with power of a destroyer.</l>
<l n="235">So far'd fayre <name>Hero</name> in th'expugned fort</l>
<l n="236">Of her chast bosome, and of every sort</l>
<l n="237">Strange thoughts possest her, ransacking her brest</l>
<l n="238">For that that was not there, her wonted rest.</l>
<l n="239">She was a mother straight and bore with paine,</l>
<l n="240">Thoughts that spake straight and wisht their mother slaine;</l>
<l n="241">She hates their lives, and they their own and hers:</l>
<l n="242">Such strife still growes where sin the race prefers.</l>
<l n="243"><quote>Love is a golden bubble full of dreames,</quote></l>
<l n="244"><quote>That waking breakes, and fils us with extreames.</quote></l>
<l n="245">She mus'd how she could looke upon her Sire,</l>
<l n="246">And not shew that without, that was intire.</l>
<l n="247">For as a glasse is an inanimate eie,</l>
<l n="248">And outward formes imbraceth inwardlie:</l>
<l n="249">So is the eye an animate glasse that showes</l>
<l n="250">In-formes without us. And as <name>Phoebus</name> throwes</l>
<l n="251">His beames abroad, though he in clowdes be closde,</l>
<l n="252">Still glancing by them till he finde opposde,</l>
<l n="253">A loose and rorid vapour that is fit</l>
<l n="254">T'event his searching beames, and useth it</l>
<l n="255">To forme a tender twentie-coloured eie,</l>
<l n="256">Cast in a circle round about the skie.</l>
<l n="257">So when our fine soule, Our bodies starre,</l>
<l n="258">(That ever is in motion circulare)</l>
<l n="259">Conceives a forme; in seeking to display it,</l>
<l n="260">Through all Our clowdie parts, it doth convey it</l>
<l n="261">Forth at the eye, as the most pregnant place,</l>
<l n="262">And that reflects it round about the face.</l>
<l n="263">And this event uncourtly <name>Hero</name> thought,</l>
<l n="264">Her inward guilt would in her lookes have wrought:</l>
<l n="265">For yet the worlds stale cunning she resisted</l>
<l n="266">To beare foule thoughts, yet forge what lookes she listed,</l>
<l n="267">And held it for a very sillie sleight,</l>
<l n="268">To make a perfect mettall counterfeit:</l>
<l n="269">Glad to disclaime her selfe; proud of an Art,</l>
<l n="270">That makes the face a Pandar to the hart.</l>
<l n="271">Those be the painted Moones, whose lights prophane</l>
<l n="272">Beauties true Heaven, at full still in their wane.</l>
<l n="273">Those be the Lapwing faces that still crie,</l>
<l n="274">Here tis, when that they vow is nothing nie.</l>
<l n="275">Base fooles, when every moorish fowle can teach</l>
<l n="276">That which men thinke the height of humane reach.</l>
<l n="277">But custome that the Apoplexie is</l>
<l n="278">Of beddred nature and lives led amis,</l>
<l n="279">And takes away all feeling of offence,</l>
<l n="280">Yet brazde not <name>Heros</name> brow with impudence;</l>
<l n="281">And this she thought most hard to bring to pas,</l>
<l n="282">To seeme in counmance other then she was.</l>
<l n="283">As if she had two soules; one for the face,</l>
<l n="284">One for the hart; and that they shifted place</l>
<l n="285">As either list to utter, or conceale</l>
<l n="286">What they conceiv'd: or as one soule did deale</l>
<l n="287">With both affayres at once, keeps and ejects</l>
<l n="288">Both at an instant contrarie effects:</l>
<l n="289">Retention and ejection in her powrs</l>
<l n="290">Being acts alike: for this one vice of ours,</l>
<l n="291">That forms the thought, and swaies the countenance,</l>
<l n="292">Rules both our motion and our utterance.</l>
<l n="293">These and more grave conceits toyld <name>Heros</name> spirits:</l>
<l n="294">For though the light of her discoursive wits</l>
<l n="295">Perhaps might finde some little hole to pas</l>
<l n="296">Through all these worldly cinctures; yet (alas)</l>
<l n="297">There was a heavenly flame incompast her;</l>
<l n="298">Her Goddesse, in whose Phane she did prefer</l>
<l n="299">Her virgin vowes; from whose impulsive sight</l>
<l n="300">She knew the black shield of the darkest night</l>
<l n="301">Could not defend her, nor wits subtilst art:</l>
<l n="302">This was the point pierst <name>Hero</name> to the hart.</l>
<l n="303">Who heavie to the death, with a deep sigh</l>
<l n="304">And hand that languisht, tooke a robe was nigh,</l>
<l n="305">Exceeding large, and of black Cypres made,</l>
<l n="306">In which she sate, hid from the day in shade,</l>
<l n="307">Even over head and face downe to her feete;</l>
<l n="308">Her left hand made it at her bosome meete;</l>
<l n="309">Her right hand leand on her hart-bowing knee,</l>
<l n="310">Wrapt in unshapefull foulds twas death to see:</l>
<l n="311">Her knee stayd that, and that her falling face,</l>
<l n="312">Each limme helpt other to put on disgrace.</l>
<l n="313">No forme was seene, where forme held all her sight:</l>
<l n="314">But like an Embrion that saw never light:</l>
<l n="315">Or like a scorched statue made a cole</l>
<l n="316">With three-wingd lightning: or a wretched soule</l>
<l n="317">Muffled with endles darknes, she did sit:</l>
<l n="318">The night had never such a heavie spirit.</l>
<l n="319">Yet might an imitating eye well see,</l>
<l n="320">How fast her deere teares melted on her knee</l>
<l n="321">Through her black vaile, and turnd as black as it,</l>
<l n="322">Mourning to be her teares: then wrought her wit</l>
<l n="323">With her broke vow, her Goddesse wrath, her fame,</l>
<l n="324">All tooles that enginous despayre could frame:</l>
<l n="325">Which made her strow the floore with her torne haire,</l>
<l n="326">And spread her mantle peece-meale in the aire.</l>
<l n="327">Like <name>Joves</name> sons club, strong passion strooke her downe,</l>
<l n="328">And with a piteous shrieke inforst her swoune:</l>
<l n="329">Her shrieke, made with another shrieke ascend</l>
<l n="330">The frighted Matron that on her did tend:</l>
<l n="331">And as with her owne crie her sence was slaine,</l>
<l n="332">So with the other it was calde againe.</l>
<l n="333">She rose and to her bed made forced way,</l>
<l n="334">And layd her downe even where <name>Leander</name> lay:</l>
<l n="335">And all this while the red sea of her blood</l>
<l n="336">Ebd with <name>Leander</name>: but now turnd the flood,</l>
<l n="337">And all her fleete of sprites came swelling in</l>
<l n="338">With childe of saile, and did hot fight begin</l>
<l n="339">With those severe conceits, she too much markt,</l>
<l n="340">And here <name>Leanders</name> beauties were imbarkt.</l>
<l n="341">He came in swimming painted all with joyes,</l>
<l n="342">Such as might sweeten hell: his thought destroyes</l>
<l n="343">All her destroying thoughts: she thought she felt</l>
<l n="344">His heart in hers, with her contentions melt:</l>
<l n="345">And chid her soule that it could so much erre,</l>
<l n="346">To check the true joyes he deserv'd in her.</l>
<l n="347">Her fresh heat blood cast figures in her eyes,</l>
<l n="348">And she supposde she saw in <name>Neptunes</name> skyes</l>
<l n="349">How her star wandred, washt in smarting brine</l>
<l n="350">For her loves sake, that with immortall wine</l>
<l n="351">Should be embat'd, and swim in more hearts ease,</l>
<l n="352">Than there was water in the <name>Sestian</name> seas.</l>
<l n="353">Then said her <name>Cupid</name> prompted spirit; shall I</l>
<l n="354">Sing mones to such delightsome harmony?</l>
<l n="355">Shall slick-tongde fame patcht up with voyces rude,</l>
<l n="356">The drunken bastard of the multitude,</l>
<l n="357">(Begot when father Judgement is away,</l>
<l n="358">And gossip-like, sayes because others say,</l>
<l n="359">Takes newes as if it were too hot to eate,</l>
<l n="360">And spits it slavering forth for dog-fees meate)</l>
<l n="361">Make me for forging a phantastique vow,</l>
<l n="362">Presume to beare what makes grave matrons bow?</l>
<l n="363">Good vowes are never broken with good deedes,</l>
<l n="364">For then good deedes were bad: vowes are but seedes,</l>
<l n="365">And good deeds fruits; even those good deedes that grow</l>
<l n="366">From other stocks than from th'observed vow.</l>
<l n="367">That is a good deede that prevents a bad:</l>
<l n="368">Had I not yeelded, slaine my selfe I had.</l>
<l n="369"><name>Hero Leander</name> is, <name>Leander Hero</name>:</l>
<l n="370">Such vertue love hath to make one of two.</l>
<l n="371">If then <name>Leander</name> did my maydenhead git,</l>
<l n="372"><name>Leander</name> being my selfe I still retaine it.</l>
<l n="373">We breake chast vowes when we live loosely ever:</l>
<l n="374">But bound as we are, we live loosely never.</l>
<l n="375">Two constant lovers being joynd in one,</l>
<l n="376">Yeelding to one another, yeeld to none.</l>
<l n="377">We know not how to vow, till love unblinde us,</l>
<l n="378">And vowes made ignorantly never binde us.</l>
<l n="379">Too true it is that when t'is gone men hate</l>
<l n="380">The joyes as vaine they tooke in loves estate:</l>
<l n="381">But that's, since they have lost the heavenly light</l>
<l n="382">Should shew them way to judge of all things right.</l>
<l n="383">When life is gone death must implant his terror,</l>
<l n="384">As death is foe to life, so love to error.</l>
<l n="385">Before we love how range we through this sphere,</l>
<l n="386">Searching the sundrie fancies hunted here:</l>
<l n="387">Now with desire of wealth transported quite</l>
<l n="388">Beyond our free humanities delight:</l>
<l n="389">Now with ambition climing falling towrs,</l>
<l n="390">Whose hope to scale our feare to fall devours:</l>
<l n="391">Now rapt with pastimes, pomp, all joyes impure;</l>
<l n="392"><quote>In things without us no delight is sure.</quote></l>
<l n="393">But love with all joyes crownd, within doth sit;</l>
<l n="394">O Goddesse pitie love and pardon it.</l>
<l n="395">This spake she weeping: but her Goddesse eare</l>
<l n="396">Burnd with too sterne a heat, and would not heare.</l>
<l n="397">Aie me, hath heavens straight fingers no more graces</l>
<l n="398">For such as <name>Hero</name>, then for homeliest faces?</l>
<l n="399">Yet she hopte well, and in her sweet conceit</l>
<l n="400">Waying her arguments, she thought them weight:</l>
<l n="401">And that the logick of <name>Leanders</name> beautie,</l>
<l n="402">And them together would bring proofes of dutie.</l>
<l n="403">And if her soule, that was a skilfull glance</l>
<l n="404">Of Heavens great essence, found such imperance</l>
<l n="405">In her loves beauties; she had confidence</l>
<l n="406"><name>Jove</name> lov'd him too, and pardond her offence.</l>
<l n="407"><quote>Beautie in heaven and earth this grace doth win,</quote></l>
<l n="408"><quote>It supples rigor, and it lessens sin.</quote></l>
<l n="409">Thus, her sharpe wit, her love, her secrecie,</l>
<l n="410">Trouping together, made her wonder why</l>
<l n="411">She should not leave her bed, and to the Temple?</l>
<l n="412">Her health sayd she must live; her sex, dissemble.</l>
<l n="413">She viewd <name>Leanders</name> place, and wisht he were</l>
<l n="414">Turnd to his place, so his place were <name>Leander</name>.</l>
<l n="415">Aye me (sayd she) that loves sweet life and sence</l>
<l n="416">Should doe it harme! my love had not gone hence,</l>
<l n="417">Had he been like his place. O blessed place,</l>
<l n="418">Image of Constancie. Thus my loves grace</l>
<l n="419">Parts no where but it leaves some thing behinde</l>
<l n="420">Worth observation: he renowmes his kinde.</l>
<l n="421">His motion is like heavens Orbiculer:</l>
<l n="422">For where he once is, he is ever there.</l>
<l n="423">This place was mine: <name>Leander</name> now t'is thine;</l>
<l n="424">Thou being my selfe, then it is double mine:</l>
<l n="425">Mine, and <name>Leanders</name> mine, <name>Leanders</name> mine.</l>
<l n="426">O see what wealth it yeelds me, nay yeelds him:</l>
<l n="427">For I am in it, he for me doth swim.</l>
<l n="428">Rich, fruitfull love, that doubling selfe estates</l>
<l n="429"><name>Elixer-</name> likecontracts, though separates.</l>
<l n="430">Deare place I kisse thee, and doe welcome thee,</l>
<l n="431">As from <name>Leander</name> ever sent to mee.</l>
<!--trailer omitted--></lg>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="sestyad" n="4">
<argument><head>THE ARGUMENT OF THE FOURTH SESTYAD</head>
<l n="1"><name>Hero</name>, in sacred habit deckt,</l>
<l n="2">Doth private sacrifice effect.</l>
<l n="3">Her Skarfs description wrought byfate,</l>
<l n="4"><name>Ostents</name>, that threaten her estate.</l>
<l n="5">The strange, yet Phisicall events,</l>
<l n="6">Leanders counterfeit presents.</l>
<l n="7">In thunder, <name>Ciprides</name> descends,</l>
<l n="8">Presaging both the lovers ends.</l>
<l n="9"><name>Ecte</name> the Goddesse of remorce,</l>
<l n="10">With vocall and articulate force</l>
<l n="11">Inspires <name>Leucote</name>, <name>Venus</name> swan,</l>
<l n="12">T'excuse the beautious <name>Sestian</name>.</l>
<l n="13"><name>Venus</name>, to wreake her rites abuses,</l>
<l n="14">Creates the monster <name>Eronusis</name>;</l>
<l n="15">Enflaming <name>Heros</name> Sacrifice,</l>
<l n="16">With lightning darted from her eyes:</l>
<l n="17">And thereof springs the painted beast,</l>
<l n="18">That ever since taints every breast.</l></argument>

<lg><l n="19">Now from <name>Leanders</name> place she rose, and found</l>
<l n="20">Her haire and rent robe scattred on the ground:</l>
<l n="21">Which taking up, she every peece did lay</l>
<l n="22">Upon an Altar; where in youth of day</l>
<l n="23">She usde t'exhibite private Sacrifice:</l>
<l n="24">Those would she offer to the Deities</l>
<l n="25">Of her faire Goddesse, and her powerfull son,</l>
<l n="26">As relicks of her late-felt passion:</l>
<l n="27">And in that holy sort she vowd to end them,</l>
<l n="28">In hope her violent fancies that did rend them,</l>
<l n="29">Would as quite fade in her loves holy fire,</l>
<l n="30">As they should in the flames she ment t'inspire.</l>
<l n="31">Then put she on all her religious weedes,</l>
<l n="32">That deckt her in her secret sacred deedes:</l>
<l n="33">A crowne of Isickles, that sunne nor fire</l>
<l n="34">Could ever melt, and figur'd chast desire.</l>
<l n="35">A golden star shinde in her naked breast,</l>
<l n="36">In honour of the Queene-light of the East.</l>
<l n="37">In her right hand she held a silver wand,</l>
<l n="38">On whose bright top <name>Peristera</name> did stand,</l>
<l n="39">Who was a Nymph, but now transformd a Dove,</l>
<l n="40">And in her life was deare in <name>Venus</name> love:</l>
<l n="41">And for her sake she ever since that time,</l>
<l n="42">Chusde Doves to draw her Coach through heavens blew clime.</l>
<l n="43">Her plentious haire in curled billowes swims</l>
<l n="44">On her bright shoulder: her harmonious lims</l>
<l n="45">Sustainde no more but a most subtile vaile</l>
<l n="46">That hung on them, as it durst not assaile</l>
<l n="47">Their different concord: for the weakest ayre</l>
<l n="48">Could raise it swelling from her bewties fayre:</l>
<l n="49">Nor did it cover, but adumbrate onelie</l>
<l n="50">Her most heart-piercing parts, that a blest eie</l>
<l n="51">Might see (as it did shadow) fearfullie,</l>
<l n="52">All that all-love-deserving Paradise:</l>
<l n="53">It was as blew as the most freezing skies,</l>
<l n="54">Neere the Seas hew, for thence her Goddesse came:</l>
<l n="55">On it a skarfe she wore of wondrous frame;</l>
<l n="56">In midst whereof she wrought a virgins face,</l>
<l n="57">From whose each cheeke a fine blush did chace</l>
<l n="58">Two crimson flames, that did two waies extend,</l>
<l n="59">Spreading the ample skarfe to either end,</l>
<l n="60">Which figur'd the division of her minde,</l>
<l n="61">Whiles yet she rested bashfully inclinde,</l>
<l n="62">And stood not resolute to wed <name>Leander</name>.</l>
<l n="63">This serv'd her white neck for a purple sphere,</l>
<l n="64">And cast it selfe at full breadth downe her back.</l>
<l n="65">There (since the first breath that begun the wrack</l>
<l n="66">of her free quiet from <name>Leanders</name> lips)</l>
<l n="67">She wrought a Sea in one flame full of ships:</l>
<l n="68">But that one ship where all her wealth did passe</l>
<l n="69">(Like simple marchants goods) <name>Leander</name> was:</l>
<l n="70">For in that Sea she naked figured him;</l>
<l n="71">Her diving needle taught him how to swim,</l>
<l n="72">And to each thred did such resemblance give,</l>
<l n="73">For joy to be so like him, it did live.</l>
<l n="74"><quote>Things senceles live by art, and rationall die,</quote></l>
<l n="75"><quote>By rude contempt of art and industrie.</quote></l>
<l n="76">Scarce could she work, but in her strength of thought</l>
<l n="77">She feard she prickt <name>Leander</name> as she wrought:</l>
<l n="78">And oft would shrieke so, that her Guardian frighted,</l>
<l n="79">Would staring haste, as with some mischiefe cited.</l>
<l n="80"><quote>They double life that dead things griefs sustayne:</quote></l>
<l n="81"><quote>They kill that feele not their friends living payne.</quote></l>
<l n="82">Sometimes she feard he sought her infamie,</l>
<l n="83">And then as she was working of his eie,</l>
<l n="84">She thought to pricke it out to quench her ill:</l>
<l n="85">But as she prickt, it grew more perfect still.</l>
<l n="86"><quote>Trifling attempts no serious acts advance;</quote></l>
<l n="87"><quote>The fire of love is blowne by dalliance.</quote></l>
<l n="88">In working his fayre neck she did so grace it,</l>
<l n="89">She still was working her owne armes t'imbrace it:</l>
<l n="90">That, and his shoulders, and his hands were seene</l>
<l n="91">Above the streame, and with a pure Sea greene</l>
<l n="92">She did so queintly shadow every lim,</l>
<l n="93">All might be seene beneath the waves to swim. </l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="94">In this conceited skarfe she wrought beside</l>
<l n="95">A Moone in change, and shooting stars did glide</l>
<l n="96">In number after her with bloodie beames,</l>
<l n="97">Which figur'd her affects in their extreames,</l>
<l n="98">Pursiung Nature in her <name>Cynthian</name> bodie,</l>
<l n="99">And did her thoughts running on change implie:</l>
<l n="100">For maids take more delights when they prepare</l>
<l n="101">And thinke of wives states, than when wives they are.</l>
<l n="102">Beneath all these she wrought a Fisherman,</l>
<l n="103">Drawing his nets from forth that Ocean;</l>
<l n="104">Who drew so hard ye might discover well,</l>
<l n="105">The toughned sinewes in his neck did swell:</l>
<l n="106">His inward straines drave out his blood-shot eyes,</l>
<l n="107">And springs of sweat did in his forehead rise:</l>
<l n="108">Yet was of nought but of a Serpent sped,</l>
<l n="109">That in his bosome flew and stung him dead.</l>
<l n="110">And this by fate into her minde was sent,</l>
<l n="111">Not wrought by meere instinct of her intent.</l>
<l n="112">At the skarfs other end her hand did frame,</l>
<l n="113">Neere the forkt point of the devided flame,</l>
<l n="114">A countrie virgin keeping of a Vine,</l>
<l n="115">Who did of hollow bulrushes combine</l>
<l n="116">Snares for the stubble-loving Grashopper,</l>
<l n="117">And by her lay her skrip that nourisht her.</l>
<l n="118">Within a myrtle shade she sate and sung,</l>
<l n="119">And tufts of waving reedes about her sprung:</l>
<l n="120">Where lurkt two Foxes, that while she applide</l>
<l n="121">Her trifling snares, their theeveries did devide:</l>
<l n="122">One to the vine, another to her skrip,</l>
<l n="123">That she did negligently overslip:</l>
<l n="124">By which her fruitfull vine and holesome fare,</l>
<l n="125">She suffred spoyld to make a childish snare.</l>
<l n="126">These omenous fancies did her soule expresse,</l>
<l n="127">And every finger made a Prophetesse,</l>
<l n="128">To shew what death was hid in loves disguise,</l>
<l n="129">And make her judgement conquer destinies.</l>
<l n="130">O what sweet formes fayre Ladies soules doe shrowd,</l>
<l n="131">Were they made seene and forced through their blood,</l>
<l n="132">If through their beauties like rich work through lawn,</l>
<l n="133">They would set forth their minds with vertues drawn,</l>
<l n="134">In letting graces from their fingers flie,</l>
<l n="135">To still their yas thoughts with industrie:</l>
<l n="136">That their plied wits in numbred silks might sing</l>
<l n="137">Passions huge conquest, and their needels leading</l>
<l n="138">Affection prisoner through their own-built citties,</l>
<l n="139">Pinniond with stories and <name>Arachnean</name> ditties.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="140">Proceed we now with <name>Heros</name> sacrifice;</l>
<l n="141">She odours burnd, and from their smoke did rise</l>
<l n="142">Unsavorie fumes, that ayre with plagues inspired,</l>
<l n="143">And then the consecrated sticks she fired.</l>
<l n="144">On whose pale flame an angrie spirit flew,</l>
<l n="145">And beate it downe still as it upward grew.</l>
<l n="146">The virgin Tapers that on th'altar stood,</l>
<l n="147">When she inflam'd them burnd as red as blood:</l>
<l n="148">All sad ostents of that too neere successe,</l>
<l n="149">That made such moving beauties motionlesse.</l>
<l n="150">Then <name>Hero</name> wept; but her affrighted eyes</l>
<l n="151">She quickly wrested from the sacrifice:</l>
<l n="152">Shut them, and inwards for <name>Leander</name> lookt,</l>
<l n="153">Searcht her soft bosome, and from thence she pluckt</l>
<l n="154">His lovely picture: which when she had viewd,</l>
<l n="155">Her beauties were with all loves joyes renewd.</l>
<l n="156">The odors sweetned, and the fires burnd deere,</l>
<l n="157"><name>Leanders</name> forme left no ill object there.</l>
<l n="158">Such was his beautie that the force of light,</l>
<l n="159">Whose knowledge teacheth wonders infinite,</l>
<l n="160">The strength of number and proportion,</l>
<l n="161">Nature had plaste in it to make it knowne</l>
<l n="162">Art was her daughter, and what humane wits</l>
<l n="163">For studie lost, intombd in drossie spirits.</l>
<l n="164">After this accident (which for her glorie</l>
<l n="165"><name>Hero</name> could not but make a historie)</l>
<l n="166">Th'inhabitants of <name>Sestus</name>, and <name>Abydus</name>,</l>
<l n="167">Did every yeare with feasts propitious,</l>
<l n="168">To faire <name>Leanders</name> picture sacrifice,</l>
<l n="169">And they were persons of especiall prize</l>
<l n="170">That were allowd it, as an Ornament</l>
<l n="171">T'inrich their houses; for the continent</l>
<l n="172">of the strange vertues all approv'd it held:</l>
<l n="173">For even the very looke of it repeld</l>
<l n="174">All blastings, witchcrafts, and the strifes of nature</l>
<l n="175">In those diseases that no hearbs could cure.</l>
<l n="176">The woolfie sting of Avarice it would pull,</l>
<l n="177">And make the rankest miser bountifull.</l>
<l n="178">It kild the feare of thunder and of death;</l>
<l n="179">The discords that conceits ingendereth</l>
<l n="180">Twixt man and wife, it for the time would cease:</l>
<l n="181">The flames of love it quencht, and would increase:</l>
<l n="182">Held in a princes hand it would put out</l>
<l n="183">The dreadfulst Comet: it would ease all doubt</l>
<l n="184">of threatned mischiefes: it would bring asleepe</l>
<l n="185">Such as were mad: it would enforce to weepe</l>
<l n="186">Most barbarous eyes: and many more effects</l>
<l n="187">This picture wrought, and sprung <name>Leandrian</name> sects,</l>
<l n="188">Of which was <name>Hero</name> first: For he whose forme</l>
<l n="189">(Held in her hand) cleerd such a fatall storme,</l>
<l n="190">From hell she thought his person would defend her,</l>
<l n="191">Which night and <name>Hellespont</name> would quickly send her.</l>
<l n="192">With this confirmd, she vowd to banish quite</l>
<l n="193">All thought of any check to her delite:</l>
<l n="194">And in contempt of sillie bashfulnes,</l>
<l n="195">She would the faith of her desires professe:</l>
<l n="196">Where her Religion should be Policie,</l>
<l n="197">To follow love with zeale her pietie:</l>
<l n="198">Her chamber her Cathedrall Church should be,</l>
<l n="199">And her <name>Leander</name> her chiefe Deitie.</l>
<l n="200">For in her love these did the gods forego;</l>
<l n="201">And though her knowledge did not teach her so,</l>
<l n="202">Yet did it teach her this, that what her hart</l>
<l n="203">Did greatest hold in her selfe greatest part,</l>
<l n="204">That she did make her god; and t'was lesse nought</l>
<l n="205">To leave gods in profession and in thought,</l>
<l n="206">Than in her love and life: for therein lies</l>
<l n="207">Most of her duties, and their dignities.</l>
<l n="208">And raile the brain-bald world at what it will;</l>
<l n="209">Thats the grand Atheisme that raignes in it still.</l>
<l n="210">Yet singularitie she would use no more,</l>
<l n="211">For she was singular too much before:</l>
<l n="212">But she would please the world with fayre pretext;</l>
<l n="213">Love would not leave her conscience perplext.</l>
<l n="214">Great men that will have lesse doe for them, still</l>
<l n="215">Must beare them out though th'acts be nere so ill.</l>
<l n="216">Meannes must Pandar be to Excellence,</l>
<l n="217">Pleasure attones Falshood and Conscience:</l>
<l n="218">Dissembling was the worst (thought <name>Hero</name> then)</l>
<l n="219">And that was best now she must live with men.</l>
<l n="220">O vertuous love that taught her to doe best,</l>
<l n="221">When she did worst, and when she thought it lest.</l>
<l n="222">Thus would she still proceed in works divine,</l>
<l n="223">And in her sacred state of priesthood shine,</l>
<l n="224">Handling the holy rites with hands as bold,</l>
<l n="225">As if therein she did <name>Joves</name> thunder hold;</l>
<l n="226">And need not feare those menaces of error,</l>
<l n="227">Which she at others threw with greatest terror.</l>
<l n="228">O lovely <name>Hero</name>, nothing is thy sin,</l>
<l n="229">Wayd with those foule faults other Priests are in;</l>
<l n="230">That having neither faiths, nor works, nor bewties,</l>
<l n="231">T'engender any scuse for slubberd duties;</l>
<l n="232">With as much countnance fill their holie chayres,</l>
<l n="233">And sweat denouncements gainst prophane affayres,</l>
<l n="234">As if their lives were cut out by their places,</l>
<l n="235">And they the only fathers of the Graces.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="236">Now as with setled minde she did repaire,</l>
<l n="237">Her thoughts to sacrifice her ravisht haire,</l>
<l n="238">And her torne robe which on the altar lay,</l>
<l n="239">And only for Religions fire did stay;</l>
<l n="240">She heard a thunder by the Cyclops beaten,</l>
<l n="241">In such a volley as the world did threaten,</l>
<l n="242">Given <name>Venus</name> as she parted th'ayrie Sphere,</l>
<l n="243">Discending now to chide with <name>Hero</name> here:</l>
<l n="244">When suddenly the Goddesse waggoners,</l>
<l n="245">The Swans and Turtles that in coupled pheres,</l>
<l n="246">Through all worlds bosoms draw her influence,</l>
<l n="247">Lighted in <name>Heros</name> window, and from thence</l>
<l n="248">To her fayre shoulders flew the gentle Doves,</l>
<l n="249">Gracefull <name>Aedone</name> that sweet pleasure loves,</l>
<l n="250">And ruffoot <name>Chreste</name> with the tufted crowne,</l>
<l n="251">Both which did kisse her, though their Goddes frowne.</l>
<l n="252">The Swans did in the solid flood, her glasse,</l>
<l n="253">Proyne their fayre plumes; of which the fairest was</l>
<l n="254"><name>Jove-</name> lov'd <name>Leucote</name>, thatpure brightnes is;</l>
<l n="255">The other bountie-loving <name>Dapsilis</name>.</l>
<l n="256">All were in heaven, now they with <name>Hero</name> were:</l>
<l n="257">But <name>Venus</name>  lookes brought wrath, and urged feare.</l>
<l n="258">Her robe was skarlet, black her heads attire,</l>
<l n="259">And through her naked breast shinde streames of fire,</l>
<l n="260">As when the rarefied ayre is driven</l>
<l n="261">In flashing streames, and opes the darkned heaven.</l>
<l n="262">In her white hand a wreath of yew she bore,</l>
<l n="263">And breaking th'icie wreath sweet <name>Hero</name> wore,</l>
<l n="264">She forst about her browes her wreath of yew,</l>
<l n="265">And sayd; now minion to thy fate be trew,</l>
<l n="266">Though not to me, indure what this portends;</l>
<l n="267">Begin where lightnes will, in shame it ends.</l>
<l n="268">Love makes thee cunning; thou art currant now,</l>
<l n="269">By being counterfeit: thy broken vow,</l>
<l n="270">Deceit with her pide garters must rejoyne,</l>
<l n="271">And with her stampe thou countnances must coyne,</l>
<l n="272">Coynes, and pure deceits for purities:</l>
<l n="273">And still a mayd wilt seeme in cosoned eies,</l>
<l n="274">And have an antike face to laugh within,</l>
<l n="275">While thy smooth lookes make men digest thy sin.</l>
<l n="276">But since thy lips (lest thought forsworne) forswore,</l>
<l n="277">Be never virgins vow worth trusting more.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="278">When Beauties dearest did her Goddesse heare</l>
<l n="279">Breathe such rebukes gainst that she could not cleare;</l>
<l n="280">Dumbe sorrow spake alowd in teares, and blood</l>
<l n="281">That from her griefe-burst vaines in piteous flood,</l>
<l n="282">From the sweet conduits of her favor fell:</l>
<l n="283">The gentle Turtles did with moanes make swell</l>
<l n="284">Their shining gorges: the white black-eyde Swans</l>
<l n="285">Did sing as woflill Epicedians,</l>
<l n="286">As they would straightwaies dye: when pities Queene</l>
<l n="287">The Goddesse <name>Ecte</name>, that had ever beene</l>
<l n="288">Hid in a watrie clowde neere <name>Heros</name> cries,</l>
<l n="289">Since the first instant of her broken eies,</l>
<l n="290">Gave bright <name>Leucote</name> voyce, and made her speake,</l>
<l n="291">To ease her anguish, whose swolne breast did breake</l>
<l n="292">With anger at her Goddesse, that did touch</l>
<l n="293"><name>Hero</name> so neere for that she usde so much.</l>
<l n="294">And thrusting her white neck at <name>Venus</name>, sayd;</l>
<l n="295">Why may not amorous <name>Hero</name> seeme a mayd,</l>
<l n="296">Though she be none, as well as you suppresse</l>
<l n="297">In modest cheekes your inward wantonnesse?</l>
<l n="298">How often have wee drawne you from above,</l>
<l n="299">T'exchange with mortals, rites for rites in love?</l>
<l n="300">Why in your preist then call you that offence</l>
<l n="301">That shines in you, and is your influence?</l>
<l n="302">With this the furies stopt <name>Leucotes</name> lips,</l>
<l n="303">Enjoynd by <name>Venus</name>; who with Rosie whips</l>
<l n="304">Beate the kind Bird. Fierce lightning from her eyes</l>
<l n="305">Did set on fire faire <name>Heros</name> sacrifice,</l>
<l n="306">Which was her torne robe, and inforced hayre;</l>
<l n="307">And the bright flame became a mayd most faire</l>
<l n="308">For her aspect: her tresses were of wire,</l>
<l n="309">Knit like a net, where harts all set on fire,</l>
<l n="310">Strugled in pants and could not get releast:</l>
<l n="311">Her armes were all with golden pincers drest,</l>
<l n="312">And twentie fashiond knots, pullies, and brakes,</l>
<l n="313">And all her bodie girdled with painted Snakes.</l>
<l n="314">Her doune parts in a Scorpions taile combinde,</l>
<l n="315">Freckled with twentie colours; pyed wings shinde</l>
<l n="316">Out of her shoulders; Cloth had never die,</l>
<l n="317">Nor sweeter colours never viewed eie,</l>
<l n="318">In scorching <name>Turkie</name>, <name>Cares</name>, <name>Tartarie</name>,</l>
<l n="319">Than shinde about this spirit notorious;</l>
<l n="320">Nor was <name>Arachnes</name> web so glorious.</l>
<l n="321">Of lightning and of shreds she was begot;</l>
<l n="322">More hold in base dissemblers is there not.</l>
<l n="323">Her name was <name>Eronusis</name>. <name>Venus</name> flew</l>
<l n="324">From <name>Heros</name> sight, and at her Chariot drew</l>
<l n="325">This wondrous creature to so steepe a height,</l>
<l n="326">That all the world she might command with sleight</l>
<l n="327">of her gay wings: and then she bad her hast,</l>
<l n="328">Since <name>Hero</name> had dissembled, and disgrast</l>
<l n="329">Her rites so much, and every breast infect</l>
<l n="330">With her deceits; she made her Architect</l>
<l n="331">Of all dissimulation, and since then</l>
<l n="332">Never was any trust in maides nor men.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="333">O it spighted,</l>
<l n="334">Fayre <name>Venus</name> hart to see her most delighted,</l>
<l n="335">And one she chusde for temper of her minde,</l>
<l n="336">To be the only ruler of her kinde,</l>
<l n="337">So soone to let her virgin race be ended:</l>
<l n="338">Not simply for the fault a whit offended;</l>
<l n="339">But that in strife for chastnes with the Moone,</l>
<l n="340">Spitefull <name>Diana</name> bad her shew but one,</l>
<l n="341">That was her servant vowd, and liv'd a mayd,</l>
<l n="342">And now she thought to answer that upbrayd,</l>
<l n="343"><name>Hero</name> had lost her answer; who knowes not</l>
<l n="344"><name>Venus</name> would seeme as farre from any spot</l>
<l n="345">Of light demeanour, as the very skin</l>
<l n="346">Twixt <name>Cynthias</name> browes; Sin is asham'd of Sin.</l>
<l n="347">Up <name>Venus</name> flew, and scarce durst up for feare</l>
<l n="348">Of <name>Phoebes</name> laughter, when she past her Sphere:</l>
<l n="349">And so most ugly clowded was the light,</l>
<l n="350">That day was hid in day; night came ere night,</l>
<l n="351">And <name>Venus</name> could not through the thick ayre pierce,</l>
<l n="352">Till the dales king, god of undanted verse,</l>
<l n="353">Because she was so plentifull a theame,</l>
<l n="354">To such as wore his Lawrell <name>Anademe</name>:</l>
<l n="355">Like to a fine bullet made descent,</l>
<l n="356">And from her passage those fat vapours rent,</l>
<l n="357">That being not throughly rarefide to raine,</l>
<l n="358">Melted like pitch as blew as any vaine,</l>
<l n="359">And scalding tempests made the earth to shrinke</l>
<l n="360">Under their fervor, and the world did thinke</l>
<l n="361">In every drop a torturing Spirit flew,</l>
<l n="362">It pierst so deeply, and it burnd so blew.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="363">Betwixt all this and <name>Hero</name>, <name>Hero</name> held</l>
<l n="364"><name>Leanders</name> picture as a <name>Persean</name> shield:</l>
<l n="365">And she was free from feare of worst successe;</l>
<l n="366">The more ill threats us, we suspect the lesse;</l>
<l n="367">As we grow haples, violence subtle growes,</l>
<l n="368">Dumb, deafe, and	blind, and comes when no man knowes.</l>
<!--trailer omitted--></lg>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="sestyad" n="5">
<argument><head>THE ARGUMENT OF THE FIFT SESTYAD.</head>
<l n="1">Day doubles her accustomd date,</l>
<l n="2">As loth the night, incenst by fate,</l>
<l n="3">Should wrack our lovers; <name>Heros</name> plight,</l>
<l n="4">Longs for <name>Leander</name>, and the night:</l>
<l n="5">Which, ere her thirstie wish recovers,</l>
<l n="6">She sends for two betrothed lovers,</l>
<l n="7">And marries them, that (with their crew,</l>
<l n="8">Their sports and ceremonies due)</l>
<l n="9">She covertly might celebrate,</l>
<l n="10">With secret joy her owne estate.</l>
<l n="11">She makes a feast, at which appeares</l>
<l n="12">The wilde Nymph <name>Teras</name>, that still beares</l>
<l n="13">An Ivory Lute, tels Omenous tales,</l>
<l n="14">And sings at solemne festivales.</l></argument>

<lg><l n="15">Now was bright <name>Hero</name> weary of the day,</l>
<l n="16">Thought an Olympiad in <name>Leanders</name> stay.</l>
<l n="17"><name>Sol</name>  and the soft-foote <name>Howrs</name> hung on his armes,</l>
<l n="18">And would not let him swim, foreseeing his harmes:</l>
<l n="19">That day <name>Aurora</name> double grace obtainde</l>
<l n="20">Of her love <name>Phoebus</name>; she his Horses rainde,</l>
<l n="21">Set on his golden knee, and as she list</l>
<l n="22">She puld him back; and as she puld, she kist</l>
<l n="23">To have him turne to bed; he lov'd her more,</l>
<l n="24">To see the love <name>Leander Hero</name> bore.</l>
<l n="25">Examples profit much: ten times in one,</l>
<l n="26">In persons full of note, good deedes are done.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="27">Day was so long, men walking fell asleepe,</l>
<l n="28">The heavie humors that their eyes did steepe,</l>
<l n="29">Made them feare mischiefs. The hard streets were beds</l>
<l n="30">For covetous churles, and for ambitious heads,</l>
<l n="31">That spight of Nature would their busines plie.</l>
<l n="32">All thought they had the falling <name>Epilepsie</name>,</l>
<l n="33">Men groveld so upon the smotherd ground,</l>
<l n="34">And pittie did the hart of heaven confound.</l>
<l n="35">The Gods, the Graces, and the Muses came</l>
<l n="36">Downe to the Destinies, to stay the frame</l>
<l n="37">Of the true lovers deaths, and all worlds teares:</l>
<l n="38">But death before had stopt their cruell eares.</l>
<l n="39">All the Celestials parted mourning then,</l>
<l n="40">Pierst with our humane miseries more then men.</l>
<l n="41">Ah, nothing doth the world with mischiefe fill,</l>
<l n="42">But want of feeling one anothers ill.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="43">With their descent the day grew something fayre,</l>
<l n="44">And cast a brighter robe upon the ayre.</l>
<l n="45"><name>Hero</name> to shorten time with merriment,</l>
<l n="46">For yong <name>Alcmane</name>, and bright <name>Mya</name> sent,</l>
<l n="47">Two lovers that had long crav'd mariage dues</l>
<l n="48">At <name>Heros</name> hands: but she did still refuse,</l>
<l n="49">For lovely <name>Mya</name> was her consort vowd</l>
<l n="50">In her maids state, and therefore not allowd</l>
<l n="51">To amorous Nuptials: yet faire <name>Hero</name> now</l>
<l n="52">Intended to dispence with her cold vow,</l>
<l n="53">Since hers was broken, and to marrie her:</l>
<l n="54">The rites would pleasing matter minister</l>
<l n="55">To her conceits, and shorten tedious day.</l>
<l n="56">They came; sweet Musick usherd th'odorous way,</l>
<l n="57">And wanton Ayre in twentie sweet forms danst</l>
<l n="58">After her fingers; Beautie and Love advanst</l>
<l n="59">Their ensignes in the downles rosie faces</l>
<l n="60">Of youths and maids, led after by the Graces.</l>
<l n="61">For all these, <name>Hero</name> made a friendly feast,</l>
<l n="62">Welcomd them kindly, did much love protest,</l>
<l n="63">Winning their harts with all the meanes she might,</l>
<l n="64">That when her fault should chance t'abide the light,</l>
<l n="65">Their loves might cover or extenuate it,</l>
<l n="66">And high in her worst fate make pittie sit.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="67">She married them, and in the banquet came</l>
<l n="68">Borne by the virgins: <name>Hero</name> striv'd to frame</l>
<l n="69">Her thoughts to mirth. Aye me, but hard it is</l>
<l n="70">To imitate a false and forced blis.</l>
<l n="71">Ill may a sad minde forge a merrie face,</l>
<l n="72">Nor hath constrained laughter any grace.</l>
<l n="73">Then layd she wine on cares to make them sinke;</l>
<l n="74"><quote>Who fears the threats of fortune, let him drinke.</quote></l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="75">To these quick Nuptials entred suddenly</l>
<l n="76">Admired <name>Teras</name> with the Ebon Thye,</l>
<l n="77">A Nymph that haunted the greene <name>Sestyan</name> groves,</l>
<l n="78">And would consort soft virgins in their loves,</l>
<l n="79">At gaysome Triumphs, and on solemne dayes,</l>
<l n="80">Singing prophetike Elegies and Layes:</l>
<l n="81">And fingring of a silver Lute she tide,</l>
<l n="82">With black and purple skarfs by her left side.</l>
<l n="83"><name>Apollo</name> gave it, and her skill withall,</l>
<l n="84">And she was term'd his Dwarfe she was so small.</l>
<l n="85">Yet great in vertue, for his beames enclosde</l>
<l n="86">His vertues in her: never was proposde</l>
<l n="87">Riddle to her, or Augurie, strange or new,</l>
<l n="88">But she resolv'd it: never sleight tale flew</l>
<l n="89">From her charmd lips, without important sence,</l>
<l n="90">Shewne in some grave succeeding consequence.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="91">This little Silvane with her songs and tales,</l>
<l n="92">Gave such estate to feasts and Nuptiales,</l>
<l n="93">That though oft times she forewent Tragedies,</l>
<l n="94">Yet for her strangenes still she pleasde their eyes,</l>
<l n="95">And for her smalnes they admir'd her so,</l>
<l n="96">They thought her perfect borne and could not grow.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="97">All eyes were on her: <name>Hero</name> did command</l>
<l n="98">An Altar deckt with sacred state should stand,</l>
<l n="99">At the Feasts upper end close by the Bride,</l>
<l n="100">On which the pretie Nymph might sit espide.</l>
<l n="101">Then all were silent; every one so heares,</l>
<l n="102">As all their sences climbd into their eares:</l>
<l n="103">And first this amorous tale that fitted well</l>
<l n="104">Fayre <name>Hero</name> and the Nuptials she did tell:</l></lg>
<lg type="tale">
<head>The tale of <name>Teras</name>.</head>
<lg type="paragraph"><l n="105"><name>Hymen</name> that now is god of Nuptiall rites,</l>
<l n="106">And crownes with honor Love and his delights,</l>
<l n="107">Of <name>Athens</name> was, a youth so sweet of face,</l>
<l n="108">That many thought him of the femall race:</l>
<l n="109">Such quickning brightnes did his deere eyes dart,</l>
<l n="110">Warme went their beames to his beholders hart.</l>
<l n="111">In such pure leagues his beauties were combinde,</l>
<l n="112">That there your Nuptiall contracts first were signde.</l>
<l n="113">For as proportion, white and crimsine, meet</l>
<l n="114">In Beauties mixture, all right deere, and sweet;</l>
<l n="115">The eye responsible, the golden haire,</l>
<l n="116">And none is held without the other, faire:</l>
<l n="117">All spring together, all together fade;</l>
<l n="118">Such intermixt affections should invade</l>
<l n="119">Two perfect lovers: which being yet unseene,</l>
<l n="120">Their vertues and their comforts copied beene,</l>
<l n="121">In Beauties concord, subject to the eie;</l>
<l n="122">And that, in <name>Hymen</name>, pleasde so matchleslie,</l>
<l n="123">That lovers were esteemde in their full grace,</l>
<l n="124">Like forme and colour mixt in <name>Hymens</name> face;</l>
<l n="125">And such sweete concord was thought worthie then</l>
<l n="126">Of torches, musick, feasts, and greatest men:</l>
<l n="127">So <name>Hymen</name> lookt, that even the chastest minde</l>
<l n="128">He mov'd to joyne in joyes of sacred kinde:</l>
<l n="129">For onely now his chins first doune consorted</l>
<l n="130">His heads rich fleece, in golden curles contorted;</l>
<l n="131">And as he was so lov'd, he lov'd so too,</l>
<l n="132">So should best bewties, bound by Nuptialls doo.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="133">Bright <name>Eucharis</name>, who was by all men saide</l>
<l n="134">The noblest, fayrest, and the richest maide,</l>
<l n="135">Of all th'<name>Athenian</name> damzels, <name>Hymen</name> lov'd,</l>
<l n="136">With such transmission, that his heart remov'd</l>
<l n="137">From his white brest to hers; but her estate</l>
<l n="138">In passing his, was so interminate</l>
<l n="139">For wealth and honor, that his love durst feede</l>
<l n="140">On nought but sight and hearing, nor could breede</l>
<l n="141">Hope of requittall, the grand prise of love;</l>
<l n="142">Nor could he heare or see but he must prove</l>
<l n="143">How his rare bewties musick would agree</l>
<l n="144">With maids in consort: therefore robbed he</l>
<l n="145">His chin of those same few first fruits it bore,</l>
<l n="146">And clad in such attire, as Virgins wore,</l>
<l n="147">He kept them companie, and might right well,</l>
<l n="148">For he did all but <name>Eucharis</name> excell</l>
<l n="149">In all the fayre of Beautie: yet he wanted</l>
<l n="150">Vertue to make his owne desires implanted</l>
<l n="151">In his deare <name>Eucharis</name>; for women never</l>
<l n="152">Love beautie in their sex, but envie ever.</l>
<l n="153">His judgement yet (that durst not suite addresse,</l>
<l n="154">Nor past due meanes presume of due successe)</l>
<l n="155">Reason gat fortune in the end to speede</l>
<l n="156">To his best prayers: but strange it seemd indeede,</l>
<l n="157">That fortune should a chast affection blesse,</l>
<l n="158"><quote>Preferment seldome graceth bashfulnesse.</quote></l>
<l n="159">Nor grast it <name>Hymen</name> yet; but many a dart</l>
<l n="160">And many an amorous thought enthrald his hart,</l>
<l n="161">Ere he obtaind her; and he sick became,</l>
<l n="162">Forst to abstaine her sight, and then the flame</l>
<l n="163">Rag'd in his bosome. O what griefe did fill him:</l>
<l n="164">Sight made him sick, and want of sight did kill him.</l>
<l n="165">The virgins wondred where <name>Diatia</name> stayd,</l>
<l n="166">For so did <name>Hymen</name> terme himselfe a mayd.</l>
<l n="167">At length with sickly lookes he greeted them:</l>
<l n="168">Tis strange to see gainst what an extreame streame</l>
<l n="169">A lover strives; poore <name>Hymen</name> lookt so ill,</l>
<l n="170">That as in merit he increased still,</l>
<l n="171">By suffring much, so he in grace decreast.</l>
<l n="172">Women are most wonne when men merit least:</l>
<l n="173">If merit looke not well, love bids stand by,</l>
<l n="174">Loves speciall lesson is to please the eye.</l>
<l n="175">And <name>Hymen</name> soone recovering all he lost,</l>
<l n="176">Deceiving still these maids, but himselfe most,</l>
<l n="177">His love and he with many virgin dames,</l>
<l n="178">Noble by birth, noble by beauties <name>flames</name>,</l>
<l n="179">Leaving the towne with songs and hallowed lights,</l>
<l n="180">To doe great <name>Ceres Eleusina</name> rites</l>
<l n="181">Of zealous Sacrifice; were made a pray</l>
<l n="182">To barbarous Rovers that in ambush lay,</l>
<l n="183">And with rude hands enforst their shining spoyle,</l>
<l n="184">Farre from the darkned Citie, tir'd with toyle.</l>
<l n="185">And when the yellow issue of the skie</l>
<l n="186">Came trouping forth, jelous of crueltie</l>
<l n="187">To their bright fellowes of this under heaven,</l>
<l n="188">Into a double night they saw them driven,</l>
<l n="189">A horride Cave, the theeves black mansion,</l>
<l n="190">Where wearie of the journey they had gon,</l>
<l n="191">Their last nights watch, and drunke with their sweete gains,</l>
<l n="192">Dull <name>Morpheus</name> entred, laden with silken chains,</l>
<l n="193">Stronger then iron, and bound the swelling vaines</l>
<l n="194">And tyred sences of these lawles Swaines.</l>
<l n="195">But when the virgin lights thus dimly burnd;</l>
<l n="196">O what a hell was heaven in! how they mournd</l>
<l n="197">And wrung their hands, and wound their gentle forms</l>
<l n="198">Into the shapes of sorrow! Golden storms</l>
<l n="199">Fell from their eyes: As when the Sunne appeares,</l>
<l n="200">And yet it raines, so shewd their eyes their teares.</l>
<l n="201">And as when funerall dames watch a dead corse,</l>
<l n="202">Weeping about it, telling with remorse</l>
<l n="203">What paines he felt, how long in paine he lay,</l>
<l n="204">How little food he eate, what he would say;</l>
<l n="205">And then mixe mournfull tales of others deaths,</l>
<l n="206">Smothering themselves in clowds of their owne breaths;</l>
<l n="207">At length, one cheering other, call for wine,</l>
<l n="208">The golden boale drinks teares out of their eine,</l>
<l n="209">As they drinke wine from it; and round it goes,</l>
<l n="210">Each helping other to relieve their woes:</l>
<l n="211">So cast these virgins beauties mutuall raies,</l>
<l n="212">One lights another, face the face displaies;</l>
<l n="213">Lips by reflexion kist, and hands hands shooke,</l>
<l n="214">Even by the whitenes each of other tooke.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="215">But <name>Hymen</name> now usde friendly <name>Morpheus</name> aide,</l>
<l n="216">Slew every theefe, and rescude every maide.</l>
<l n="217">And now did his enamourd passion take</l>
<l n="218">Hart from his hartie deede, whose worth did make</l>
<l n="219">His hope of bounteous <name>Euckaris</name> more strong;</l>
<l n="220">And now came Love with <name>Proteus</name>, who had long</l>
<l n="221">Inggl'd the little god with prayers and gifts,</l>
<l n="222">Ran through all shapes, and varied all his shifts,</l>
<l n="223">To win Loves stay with him, and make him love him:</l>
<l n="224">And when he saw no strength of sleight could move him</l>
<l n="225">To make him love, or stay, he nimbly turnd</l>
<l n="226">Into Loves selfe, he so extreamely burnd.</l>
<l n="227">And thus came Love with <name>Proteus</name> and his powre,</l>
<l n="228">T'encounter <name>Eucharis</name>: first like the flowre</l>
<l n="229">That <name>Junos</name> milke did spring, the silver Lillie,</l>
<l n="230">He fell on <name>Hymens</name> hand, who straight did spie</l>
<l n="231">The bounteous Godhead, and with wondrous joy</l>
<l n="232">Offred it <name>Eucharis</name>. She wondrous coy</l>
<l n="233">Drew back her hand: the subtle flowre did woo it,</l>
<l n="234">And drawing it neere, mixt so you could not know it.</l>
<l n="235">As two deere Tapers mixe in one their light,</l>
<l n="236">So did the Lillie and the hand their white:</l>
<l n="237">She viewd it, and her view the forme bestowes</l>
<l n="238">Amongst her spirits: for as colour flowes</l>
<l n="239">From superficies of each thing we see,</l>
<l n="240">Even so with colours formes emitted bee:</l>
<l n="241">And where Loves forme is, Love is, Love is forme;</l>
<l n="242">He entred at the eye, his sacred storme</l>
<l n="243">Rose from the hand, Loves sweetest instrument:</l>
<l n="244">It stird her bloods sea so, that high it went,</l>
<l n="245">And beate in bashfull waves gainst the white shore</l>
<l n="246">Of her divided cheekes; it rag'd the more,</l>
<l n="247">Because the tide went gainst the haughtie winde</l>
<l n="248">Of her estate and birth: And as we finde</l>
<l n="249">In fainting ebs, the flowrie Zephire hurles</l>
<l n="250">The greene-hayrd <name>Hellespont</name>, broke in silver curles,</l>
<l n="251">Gainst <name>Heros</name> towre: but in his blasts retreate,</l>
<l n="252">The waves obeying him, they after beate,</l>
<l n="253">Leaving the chalkie shore a great way pale,</l>
<l n="254">Then moyst it freshly with another gale:</l>
<l n="255">So ebd and flowde the blood in <name>Eucharis</name> face,</l>
<l n="256">Coynesse and Love striv'd which had greatest grace.</l>
<l n="257">Virginitie did fight on Coynesse side;</l>
<l n="258">Feare of her parents frownes, and femall pride,</l>
<l n="259">Lothing the lower place, more then it loves</l>
<l n="260">The high contents, desert and vertue moves.</l>
<l n="261">With Love fought <name>Hymens</name> beautie and his valure,</l>
<l n="262">Which scarce could so much favour yet allure</l>
<l n="263">To come to strike, but fameles idle stood,</l>
<l n="264"><quote>Action is firie valours soveraigne good.</quote></l>
<l n="265">But Love once entred, wisht no greater ayde</l>
<l n="266">Then he could find within; thought, thought betrayd.</l>
<l n="267">The bribde, but incorrupted Garrison,</l>
<l n="268">Sung <name>Io Hymen</name>; there those songs begun,</l>
<l n="269">And Love was growne so rich with such a game,</l>
<l n="270">And wanton with the ease of his free raigne,</l>
<l n="271">That he would turne into her roughest frownes</l>
<l n="272">To turne them out; and thus he <name>Hymen</name> crownes</l>
<l n="273">King of his thoughts, mans greatest Emperie:</l>
<l n="274">This was his first brave step to deitie.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="275">Home to the mourning cittie they repayre,</l>
<l n="276">With newes as holesome as the morning ayre,</l>
<l n="277">To the sad parents of each saved maid:</l>
<l n="278">But <name>Hymen</name> and his <name>Eucharis</name> had laid</l>
<l n="279">This plat, to make the flame of their delight</l>
<l n="280">Round as the Moone at full, and full as bright.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="281">Because the parents of chast <name>Eucharis</name></l>
<l n="282">Exceeding <name>Hymens</name> so, might crosse their blis;</l>
<l n="283">And as the world rewards deserts, that law</l>
<l n="284">Cannot assist with force: so when they saw</l>
<l n="285">Their daughter safe, take vantage of their owne,</l>
<l n="286">Praise <name>Hymens</name> valour much, nothing bestowne:</l>
<l n="287"><name>Hymen</name> must leave the virgins in a Grove</l>
<l n="288">Farre off from <name>Athens</name>, and go first to prove</l>
<l n="289">If to restore them all with fame and life,</l>
<l n="290">He should enjoy his dearest as his wife.</l>
<l n="291">This told to all the maids; the most agree:</l>
<l n="292">The riper sort knowing what t'is to bee</l>
<l n="293">The first mouth of a newes so farre deriv'd,</l>
<l n="294">And that to heare and beare newes brave folks liv'd,</l>
<l n="295">As being a carriage speciall hard to beare</l>
<l n="296">Occurrents, these occurrents being so deare,</l>
<l n="297">They did with grace protest, they were content</l>
<l n="298">T'accost their friends with all their complement,</l>
<l n="299">For <name>Hymens</name> good: but to incurre their harme,</l>
<l n="300">There he must pardon them. This wit went warme</l>
<l n="301">To <name>Adolesches</name> braine, a Nymph borne hie,</l>
<l n="302">Made all of voyce and fire, that upwards flie:</l>
<l n="303">Her hart and all her forces nether traine</l>
<l n="304">Climbd to her tongue, and thither fell her braine,</l>
<l n="305">Since it could goe no higher, and it must go:</l>
<l n="306">All powers she had, even her tongue, did so.</l>
<l n="307">In spirit and quicknes she much joy did take,</l>
<l n="308">And lov'd her tongue, only for quicknes sake,</l>
<l n="309">And she would hast and tell. The rest all stay,</l>
<l n="310"><name>Hymen</name> goes one, the Nymph another way:</l>
<l n="311">And what became of her Ile tell at last:</l>
<l n="312">Yet take her visage now: moyst lipt, long fa'st,</l>
<l n="313">Thin like an iron wedge, so sharpe and tart,</l>
<l n="314">As twere of purpose made to cleave Loves hart.</l>
<l n="315">Well were this lovely Beautie rid of her,</l>
<l n="316">And <name>Hymen</name> did at <name>Athens</name> now prefer</l>
<l n="317">His welcome suite, which he with joy aspirde:</l>
<l n="318">A hundred princely youths with him retirde</l>
<l n="319">To fetch the Nymphs: Chariots and Musick went,</l>
<l n="320">And home they came: heaven with applauses rent.</l>
<l n="321">The Nuptials straight proceed, whiles all the towne,</l>
<l n="322">Fresh in their joyes might doe them most renowne.</l>
<l n="323">First gold-lockt <name>Hymen</name> did to Church repaire,</l>
<l n="324">Like a quick offring burnd in flames of haire.</l>
<l n="325">And after, with a virgin firmament,</l>
<l n="326">The Godhead-proving Bride, attended went</l>
<l n="327">Before them all; she lookt in her command,</l>
<l n="328">As if forme-giving <name>Cyprias</name> silver hand</l>
<l n="329">Gripte all their beauties, and crusht out one flame;</l>
<l n="330">She blusht to see how beautie overcame</l>
<l n="331">The thoughts of all men. Next before her went</l>
<l n="332">Five lovely children deckt with ornament</l>
<l n="333">Of her sweet colours, bearing Torches by,</l>
<l n="334">For light was held a happie Augurie</l>
<l n="335">Of generation, whose efficient right</l>
<l n="336">Is nothing else but to produce to light.</l>
<l n="337">The od disparent number they did chuse,</l>
<l n="338">To shew the union married loves should use,</l>
<l n="339">Since in two equall parts it will not sever,</l>
<l n="340">But the midst holds one to rejoyne it ever,</l>
<l n="341">As common to both parts: men therfore deeme,</l>
<l n="342">That equall number Gods does not esteeme,</l>
<l n="343">Being authors of sweet peace and unitie,</l>
<l n="344">But pleasing to th'infernall Emperie,</l>
<l n="345">Under whose ensignes Wars and Discords fight,</l>
<l n="346">Since an even number you may disunite</l>
<l n="347">In two parts equall, nought in middle left,</l>
<l n="348">To reunite each part from other reft:</l>
<l n="349">And five they hold in most especiall prise,</l>
<l n="350">Since t'is the first od number that doth rise</l>
<l n="351">From the two formost numbers unitie</l>
<l n="352">That od and even are; which are two, and three,</l>
<l n="353">For one no number is: but thence doth flow</l>
<l n="354">The powerfull race of number. Next did go</l>
<l n="355">A noble Matron that did spinning beare</l>
<l n="356">A huswifes rock and spindle, and did weare</l>
<l n="357">A Weathers skin, with all the snowy fleece,</l>
<l n="358">To intimate that even the daintiest peece,</l>
<l n="359">And noblest borne dame should industrious bee:</l>
<l n="360">That which does good disgraceth no degree.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="361">And now to <name>Junos</name> Temple they are come,</l>
<l n="362">Where her grave Priest stood in the mariage rome.</l>
<l n="363">On his right arme did hang a skarlet vaile,</l>
<l n="364">And from his shoulders to the ground did traile,</l>
<l n="365">On either side, Ribands of white and blew;</l>
<l n="366">With the red vaile he hid the bashfull hew</l>
<l n="367">Of the chast Bride, to shew the modest shame,</l>
<l n="368">In coupling with a man should grace a dame.</l>
<l n="369">Then tooke he the disparent Silks, and tide</l>
<l n="370">The Lovers by the wasts, and side to side,</l>
<l n="371">In token that thereafter they must binde</l>
<l n="372">In one selfe sacred knot each others minde.</l>
<l n="373">Before them on an Altar he presented</l>
<l n="374">Both fire and water: which was first invented,</l>
<l n="375">Since to ingenerate every humane creature,</l>
<l n="376">And every other birth produ'st by Nature,</l>
<l n="377">Moysture and heate must mixe: so man and wife</l>
<l n="378">For humane race must joyne in Nuptiall life.</l>
<l n="379">Then one of <name>Junos</name> Birds, the painted Jay,</l>
<l n="380">He sacrifisde, and tooke the gall away.</l>
<l n="381">All which he did behinde the Altar throw,</l>
<l n="382">In signe no bitternes of hate should grow</l>
<l n="383">Twixt maried loves, nor any least disdaine.</l>
<l n="384">Nothing they spake, for twas esteemd too plaine</l>
<l n="385">For the most silken mudnes of a maid,</l>
<l n="386">To let a publique audience heare it said</l>
<l n="387">She boldly tooke the man: and so respected</l>
<l n="388">Was bashfulnes in <name>Athens</name>: it erected</l>
<l n="389">To chast <name>Agneja</name>, which is Shamefastnesse,</l>
<l n="390">A sacred Temple, holding her a Goddesse.</l>
<l n="391">And now to Feasts, Masks, and triumphant showes,</l>
<l n="392">The shining troupes returnd, even till earths throwes</l>
<l n="393">Brought forth with joy the thickest part of night,</l>
<l n="394">When the sweet Nuptiall song that usde to cite</l>
<l n="395">All to their rest, was by <name>Phemonoe</name> sung:</l>
<l n="396">First <name>Delphian</name> Prophetesse, whose graces sprung</l>
<l n="397">Out of the <name>Muses</name> well, she sung before</l>
<l n="398">The Bride into her chamber: at which dore</l>
<l n="399">A Matron and a Torch-bearer did stand;</l>
<l n="400">A painted box of Confits in her hand</l>
<l n="401">The Matron held, and so did other some</l>
<l n="402">That compast round the honourd Nuptiall rome.</l>
<l n="403">The custome was that every maid did weare,</l>
<l n="404">During her maidenhead, a silken Sphere</l>
<l n="405">About her waste, above her inmost weede,</l>
<l n="406">Knit with <name>Minervas</name> knot, and that was freede</l>
<l n="407">By the faire Bridegrome on the manage night,</l>
<l n="408">With many ceremonies of delight:</l>
<l n="409">And yet eternisde <name>Hymens</name> tender Bride,</l>
<l n="410">To suffer it dissolv'd so sweetly cride,</l>
<l n="411">The maids that heard, so lov'd, and did adore her,</l>
<l n="412">They wisht with all their hearts to suffer for her.</l>
<l n="413">So had the Matrons, that with Confits stood</l>
<l n="414">About the chamber, such affectionate blood,</l>
<l n="415">And so true feeling of her harmeles paines,</l>
<l n="416">That every one a showre of Confits raines.</l>
<l n="417">For which the Brideyouths scrambling on the ground,</l>
<l n="418">In noyse of that sweet haile her cryes were drownd.</l>
<l n="419">And thus blest <name>Hymen</name> joyde his gracious Bride,</l>
<l n="420">And for his joy was after deifide.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="421">The Saffron mirror by which <name>Phoebus</name> love,</l>
<l n="422">Greene <name>Tellus</name> decks her, now he held above</l>
<l n="423">The dowdy mountaines: and the noble maide,</l>
<l n="424">Sharp-visag'd <name>Adolesche</name>, that was straide</l>
<l n="425">Out of her way, in hasting with her newes,</l>
<l n="426">Not till this houre th'<name>Athenian</name> turrets viewes:</l>
<l n="427">And now brought home by guides, she heard by all</l>
<l n="428">That her long kept occurrents would be stale,</l>
<l n="429">And how faire <name>Hymens</name> honors did excell</l>
<l n="430">For those rare newes, which she came short to tell.</l>
<l n="431">To heare her deare tongue robd of such a joy,</l>
<l n="432">Made the well-spoken Nymph take such a toy,</l>
<l n="433">That downe she sunke: when lightning from above,</l>
<l n="434">Shrunk her leane body, and for meere free love,</l>
<l n="435">Turnd her into the pied-plum'd <name>Psittacus</name>,</l>
<l n="436">That now the Parrat is surnam'd by us,</l>
<l n="437">Who still with counterfeit confusion prates,</l>
<l n="438">Nought but newes common to the commonst mates.</l>
<l n="439">This tolde, strange <name>Teras</name> toucht her Lute and sung</l>
<l n="440">This dittie, that the Torchie evening sprung.</l></lg>
<lg type="song">
<head>Epithalamion Teratos.</head>
<lg type="paragraph"><l n="441">Come come deare night, Loves Mart of kisses,</l>
<l n="442">Sweet close of his ambitious line,</l>
<l n="443">The fruitfull summer of his blisses,</l>
<l n="444">Loves glorie doth in darknes shine.</l>
<l n="445">O come soft rest of Cares, come night,</l>
<l n="446">Come naked vertues only tire,</l>
<l n="447">The reaped harvest of the light,</l>
<l n="448">Bound up in sheaves of sacred fire.</l></lg>
<lg><l n="449">Love cals to warre,</l>
<l n="450">Sighs his Alarmes,</l>
<l n="451">Lips his swords are,</l>
<l n="452">The field his Armes.</l></lg>
<lg><l n="453">Come Night and lay thy velvet hand</l>
<l n="454">On glorious Dayes outfacing face;</l>
<l n="455">And all thy crouned flames command,</l>
<l n="456">For Torches to our Nuptiall grace.</l></lg>
<lg><l n="457">Love cals to warre,</l>
<l n="458">Sighs his Alarmes,</l>
<l n="459">Lips his swords are,</l>
<l n="460">The field his Armes.</l></lg>
<lg><l n="461">No neede have we of factious Day,</l>
<l n="462">To cast in envie of thy peace,</l>
<l n="463">Her bals of Discord in thy way:</l>
<l n="464">Here beauties day doth never cease,</l>
<l n="465">Day is abstracted here,</l>
<l n="466">And varied in a triple sphere.</l>
<l n="467"><name>Hero</name>, <name>Alcmane</name>, <name>Mya</name>, so outshine thee,</l>
<l n="468">Ere thou come here let <name>Thetis</name> thrice refine thee.</l></lg>
<lg><l n="469">Love cals to warre,</l>
<l n="470">Sighs his Alarmes,</l>
<l n="471">Lips his swords are,</l>
<l n="472">The field his Armes.</l></lg>
<lg><l n="473">The Evening starre I see:</l>
<l n="474">Rise youths, the Evening starre</l>
<l n="475">Helps Love to summon warre,</l>
<l n="476">Both now imbracing bee.</l>
<l n="477">Rise youths, Loves right claims more then banquets, rise.</l>
<l n="478">Now the bright Marygolds that deck the skies,</l>
<l n="479"><name>Phoebus</name> celestiall flowrs, that (contrarie</l>
<l n="480">To his flowers here) ope when he shuts his eie,</l>
<l n="481">And shut when he doth open, crowne your sports:</l>
<l n="482">Now love in night, and night in love exhorts</l>
<l n="483">Courtship and Dances: All your parts employ,</l>
<l n="484">And suite nights rich expansure with your joy,</l>
<l n="485">Love paints his longings in sweet virgins eyes:</l>
<l n="486">Rise youths, Loves right claims more then banquets, rise.</l>
<l n="487">Rise virgins, let fayre Nuptiall loves enfolde</l>
<l n="488">Your fruitles breasts: the maidenheads ye holde</l>
<l n="489">Are not your owne alone, but parted are;</l>
<l n="490">Part in disposing them your Parents share,</l>
<l n="491">And that a third part is: so must ye save</l>
<l n="492">Your loves a third, and you your thirds must have.</l>
<l n="493">Love paints his longings in sweet virgins eyes:</l>
<l n="494">Rise youths, Loves right claims more then banquets, rise.</l></lg>
</lg>
<lg><l n="495">Herewith the amorous spirit that was so kinde</l>
<l n="496">To <name>Teras</name> haire, and combd it downe with winde,</l>
<l n="497">Still as it Comet-like brake from her braine,</l>
<l n="498">Would needes have <name>Teras</name> gone, and did refraine</l>
<l n="499">To blow it downe: which staring up, dismaid</l>
<l n="500">The timorous feast, and she no longer staid:</l>
<l n="501">But bowing to the Bridegrome and the Bride,</l>
<l n="502">Did like a shooting exhalation glide</l>
<l n="503">Out of their sights: the turning of her back</l>
<l n="504">Made them all shrieke, it lookt so ghastly black.</l>
<l n="505">O haples <name>Hero</name>, that most haples clowde,</l>
<l n="506">Thy soone-succeeding Tragedie foreshowde.</l>
<l n="507">Thus all the Nuptiall crew to joyes depart,</l>
<l n="508">But much-wrongd <name>Hero</name> stood Hels blackest dart:</l>
<l n="509">Whose wound because I grieve so to display,</l>
<l n="510">I use digressions thus t'encrease the day.</l></lg>
<!--trailer omitted--></lg>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="sestyad" n="6">
<argument><head>THE ARGUMENT OF THE SIXT SESTYAD.</head>
<l n="1"><name>Leucote</name> flyes to all the windes,</l>
<l n="2">And from the fates their outrage bindes,</l>
<l n="3">That <name>Hero</name> and her love may meete.</l>
<l n="4"><name>Leander</name> (with <name>Loves</name> compleate Fleete</l>
<l n="5">Mand in himselfe) puts forth to Seas,</l>
<l n="6">When straight the ruthles Destinies,</l>
<l n="7">With <name>Ate</name> stirre the windes to warre</l>
<l n="8">Upon the <name>Hellespont</name>: Their jarre</l>
<l n="9">Drownes poore <name>Leander</name>. <name>Heros</name> eyes</l>
<l n="10">Wet witnesses of his surprise,</l>
<l n="11">Her Torch blowne out. Griefe casts her downe</l>
<l n="12">Upon her love, and both doth drowne.</l>
<l n="13">In whose just ruth the God of Seas</l>
<l n="14">Transformes them to th'<name>Acanthides</name>.</l></argument>

<lg><l n="15">No longer could the day nor Destinies</l>
<l n="16">Delay the night, who now did frowning rise</l>
<l n="17">Into her Throne; and at her humorous brests,</l>
<l n="18">Visions and Dreames lay sucking: all mens rests</l>
<l n="19">Fell like the mists of death upon their eyes,</l>
<l n="20">Dayes too long darts so kild their faculties.</l>
<l n="21">The windes yet, like the flowrs to cease began:</l>
<l n="22">For bright <name>Leucote</name>, <name>Venus</name> whitest Swan,</l>
<l n="23">That held sweet <name>Hero</name> deare, spread her fayre wings,</l>
<l n="24">Like to a field of snow, and message brings</l>
<l n="25">From <name>Venus</name> to the Fates, t'entreate them lay</l>
<l n="26">Their charge upon the windes their rage to stay,</l>
<l n="27">That the sterne battaile of the Seas might cease,</l>
<l n="28">And guard <name>Leander</name> to his love in peace.</l>
<l n="29">The Fates consent, (aye me dissembling Fates)</l>
<l n="30">They shewd their favours to conceale their hates,</l>
<l n="31">And draw <name>Leander</name> on, least Seas too hie</l>
<l n="32">Should stay his too obsequious destinie:</l>
<l n="33">Who like a fleering slavish Parasite,</l>
<l n="34">In warping profit or a traiterous sleight,</l>
<l n="35">Hoopes round his rotten bodie with devotes,</l>
<l n="36">And pricks his descant face full of false notes,</l>
<l n="37">Praysing with open throte (and othes as fowle</l>
<l n="38">As his false heart) the beautie of an Owle,</l>
<l n="39">Kissing his skipping hand with charmed skips,</l>
<l n="40">That cannot leave, but leapes upon his lips</l>
<l n="41">Like a cock-sparrow, or a shameles queane</l>
<l n="42">Sharpe at a red-lipt youth, and nought doth meane</l>
<l n="43">Of all his antick shewes, but doth repayre</l>
<l n="44">More tender fawnes, and takes a scattred hayre</l>
<l n="45">From his tame subjects shoulder; whips, and cals</l>
<l n="46">For every thing he lacks; creepes gainst the wals</l>
<l n="47">With backward humblesse, to give needles way:</l>
<l n="48">Thus his false fate did with <name>Leander</name> play.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="49">First to black <name>Eurus</name> flies the white <name>Leucote</name>,</l>
<l n="50">Borne mongst the <name>Negros</name> in the <name>Levant</name> Sea,</l>
<l n="51">On whose curld head the glowing Sun doth rise,</l>
<l n="52">And shewes the soveraigne will of Destinies,</l>
<l n="53">To have him cease his blasts, and downe he lies.</l>
<l n="54">Next, to the fennie <name>Notus</name>, course she holds,</l>
<l n="55">And found him leaning with his armes in folds</l>
<l n="56">Upon a rock, his white hayre full of showres,</l>
<l n="57">And him she chargeth by the fatall powres,</l>
<l n="58">To hold in his wet cheekes his clowdie voyce.</l>
<l n="59">To <name>Zephire</name> then that doth in flowres rejoyce.</l>
<l n="60">To snake-foote <name>Boreas</name> next she did remove,</l>
<l n="61">And found him tossing of his ravisht love,</l>
<l n="62">To heate his frostie bosome hid in snow,</l>
<l n="63">Who with <name>Leucotes</name> sight did cease to blow.</l>
<l n="64">Thus all were still to <name>Heros</name> harts desire,</l>
<l n="65">Who with all speede did consecrate a fire</l>
<l n="66">Of flaming Gummes, and comfortable Spice,</l>
<l n="67">To light her Torch, which in such curious price</l>
<l n="68">She held, being object to <name>Leanders</name> sight,</l>
<l n="69">That nought but fires perfilm'd must give it light.</l>
<l n="70">She lov'd it so, she griev'd to see it burne,</l>
<l n="71">Since it would waste and soone to ashes turne:</l>
<l n="72">Yet if it burnd not, twere not worth her eyes,</l>
<l n="73">What made it nothing, gave it all the prize.</l>
<l n="74">Sweet Torch, true Glasse of our societie;</l>
<l n="75">What man does good, but he consumes thereby?</l>
<l n="76">But thou wert lov'd for good, held high, given show:</l>
<l n="77">Poore vertue loth'd for good, obscur'd, held low.</l>
<l n="78">Doe good, be pinde; be deedles good, disgrast:</l>
<l n="79">Unles we feede on men, we let them fast.</l>
<l n="80">Yet <name>Hero</name> with these thoughts her Torch did spend.</l>
<l n="81">When Bees makes waxe, Nature doth not intend</l>
<l n="82">It shall be made a Torch: but we that know</l>
<l n="83">The proper vertue of it make it so,</l>
<l n="84">And when t'is made we light it: nor did Nature</l>
<l n="85">Propose one life to maids, but each such creature</l>
<l n="86">Makes by her soule the best of her free state,</l>
<l n="87">Which without love is rude, disconsolate,</l>
<l n="88">And wants Loves fire to make it milde and bright,</l>
<l n="89">Till when, maids are but Torches wanting light.</l>
<l n="90">Thus gainst our griefe, not cause of griefe we fight,</l>
<l n="91">The right of nought is gleande, but the delight.</l>
<l n="92">Up went she, but to tell how she descended,</l>
<l n="93">Would God she were not dead, or my verse ended.</l>
<l n="94">She was the rule of wishes, summe and end</l>
<l n="95">For all the parts that did on love depend:</l>
<l n="96">Yet cast the Torch his brightues further forth;</l>
<l n="97">But what shines neerest best, holds truest worth.</l>
<l n="98"><name>Leander</name> did not through such tempests swim</l>
<l n="99">To kisse the Torch, although it lighted him:</l>
<l n="100">But all his powres in her desires awaked,</l>
<l n="101">Her love and vertues cloth'd him richly naked.</l>
<l n="102">Men kisse but fire that only shewes pursue,</l>
<l n="103">Her Torch and <name>Hero</name>, figure shew, and vertue.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="104">Now at opposde <name>Abydus</name> nought was heard,</l>
<l n="105">But bleating flocks, and many a bellowing herd,</l>
<l n="106">Slaine for the Nuptials, cracks of falling woods,</l>
<l n="107">Blowes of broad axes, powrings out of floods.</l>
<l n="108">The guiltie <name>Hellespont</name> was mixt and stainde</l>
<l n="109">With bloodie Torrents, that the shambles raind;</l>
<l n="110">Not arguments of feast, but shewes that bled,</l>
<l n="111">Foretelling that red night that followed.</l>
<l n="112">More blood was spilt, more honors were addrest,</l>
<l n="113">Then could have graced any happie feast.</l>
<l n="114">Rich banquets, triumphs, every pomp employes</l>
<l n="115">His sumptuous hand: no misers nuptiall joyes.</l>
<l n="116">Ayre felt continuall thunder with the noyse,</l>
<l n="117">Made in the generall manage violence.</l>
<l n="118">And no man knew the cause of this expence,</l>
<l n="119">But the two haples Lords, <name>Leanders</name> Sire,</l>
<l n="120">And poore <name>Leander</name>, poorest where the fire</l>
<l n="121">Of credulous love made him most rich surmisde.</l>
<l n="122">As short was he of that himselfe he prisde,</l>
<l n="123">As is an emptie Gallant full of forme,</l>
<l n="124">That thinks each looke an act, each drop a storme,</l>
<l n="125">That fals from his brave breathings; most brought up</l>
<l n="126">In our <name>Metropolis</name>, and hath his cup</l>
<l n="127">Brought after him to feasts; and much Palme beares,</l>
<l n="128">For his rare judgement in th'attire he weares;</l>
<l n="129">Hath seene the hot Low Countries, not their heat,</l>
<l n="130">Observes their rampires and their buildings yet.</l>
<l n="131">And for your sweet discourse with mouthes is heard</l>
<l n="132">Giving instructions with his very beard.</l>
<l n="133">Hath gone with an Ambassadour, and been</l>
<l n="134">A great mans mate in travailing, even to <name>Rhene</name>,</l>
<l n="135">And then puts all his worth in such a face,</l>
<l n="136">As he saw brave men make, and strives for grace</l>
<l n="137">To get his newes forth; as when you descrie</l>
<l n="138">A ship with all her sayle contends to flie</l>
<l n="139">Out of the narrow <name>Thames</name> with windes unapt,</l>
<l n="140">Now crosseth here, then there, then this way rapt,</l>
<l n="141">And then hath one point reacht; then alters all,</l>
<l n="142">And to another crooked reach doth fall</l>
<l n="143">Of halfe a burdbolts shoote; keeping more coyle,</l>
<l n="144">Then if she danst upon the Oceans toyle:</l>
<l n="145">So serious is his trifling companie,</l>
<l n="146">In all his swelling ship of vacantrie.</l>
<l n="147">And so short of himselfe in his high thought,</l>
<l n="148">Was our <name>Leander</name> in his fortunes brought,</l>
<l n="149">And in his fort of love that he thought won.</l>
<l n="150">But otherwise he skornes comparison.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="151">O sweet <name>Leander</name>, thy large worth I hide</l>
<l n="152">In a short grave; ill favourd stormes must chide</l>
<l n="153">Thy sacred favour; I, in floods of inck</l>
<l n="154">Must drowne thy graces, which white papers drink,</l>
<l n="155">Even as thy beauties did the foule black Seas:</l>
<l n="156">I must describe the hell of thy disease,</l>
<l n="157">That heaven did merit: yet I needes must see</l>
<l n="158">Our painted fooles and cockhorse Pessantrie</l>
<l n="159">Still still usurp, with long lives, loves, and lust,</l>
<l n="160">The seates of vertue, cutting short as dust</l>
<l n="161">Her deare bought issue; ill, to worse converts,</l>
<l n="162">And tramples in the blood of all deserts.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="163">Night close and silent now goes fast before</l>
<l n="164">The Captaines and their souldiers to the shore,</l>
<l n="165">On whom attended the appointed Fleete</l>
<l n="166">At <name>Sestus</name> Bay, that should <name>Leander</name> meete.</l>
<l n="167">Who fainde he in another ship would passe:</l>
<l n="168">Which must not be, for no one meane there was</l>
<l n="169">To get his love home, but the course he tooke.</l>
<l n="170">Forth did his beautie for his beautie looke,</l>
<l n="171">And saw her through her Torch, as you beholde</l>
<l n="172">Sometimes within the Sunne, a face of golde,</l>
<l n="173">Form'd in strong thoughts, by that traditions force,</l>
<l n="174">That saies a God sits there and guides his course.</l>
<l n="175">His sister was with him, to whom he shewd</l>
<l n="176">His guide by Sea: and sayd; Oft have you viewd</l>
<l n="177">In one heaven many starres, but never yet</l>
<l n="178">In one starre many heavens till now were met.</l>
<l n="179">See lovely sister, see, now <name>Hero</name> shines</l>
<l n="180">No heaven but her appeares: each star repines,</l>
<l n="181">And all are clad in clowdes, as if they mournd,</l>
<l n="182">To be by influence of Earth out-burnd.</l>
<l n="183">Yet doth she shine, and teacheth vertues traine,</l>
<l n="184">Still to be constant in Hels blackest raigne:</l>
<l n="185">Though even the gods themselves do so entreat them</l>
<l n="186">As they did hate, and Earth as she would eate them.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="187">Off went his silken robe, and in he leapt;</l>
<l n="188">Whom the kinde waves so licorously cleapt,</l>
<l n="189">Thickning for haste one in another so,</l>
<l n="190">To kisse his skin, that he might almost go</l>
<l n="191">To <name>Heros</name> Towre, had that kind minuit lasted.</l>
<l n="192">But now the cruell fates with <name>Ate</name> hasted</l>
<l n="193">To all the windes, and made them battaile fight</l>
<l n="194">Upon the <name>Hellespont</name>, for eithers right</l>
<l n="195">Pretended to the windie monarchie.</l>
<l n="196">And forth they brake, the Seas mixt with the side,</l>
<l n="197">And tost distrest <name>Leander</name>, being in hell,</l>
<l n="198">As high as heaven; Blisse not in height doth dwell.</l>
<l n="199">The Destinies sate dancing on the waves,</l>
<l n="200">To see the glorious windes with mutuall braves</l>
<l n="201">Consume each other: O true glasse to see,</l>
<l n="202">How ruinous ambitious Statists bee</l>
<l n="203">To their owne glories! Poore <name>Leander</name> cried</l>
<l n="204">For help to Sea-borne <name>Venus</name>; she denied:</l>
<l n="205">To <name>Boreas</name>, that for his <name>Atthoeas</name> sake,</l>
<l n="206">He would some pittie on his <name>Hero</name> take,</l>
<l n="207">And for his owne loves sake, on his desires:</l>
<l n="208">But Glorie never blowes cold Pitties fires.</l>
<l n="209">Then calde he <name>Neptune</name>, who through all the noise,</l>
<l n="210">Knew with affright his wrackt <name>Leanders</name> voice:</l>
<l n="211">And up he rose, for haste his forehead hit</l>
<l n="212">Gainst heavens hard Christall; his proud waves he smit</l>
<l n="213">With his forkt scepter, that could not obay,</l>
<l n="214">Much greater powers then <name>Neptunes</name> gave them sway.</l>
<l n="215">They lov'd <name>Leander</name> so, in groanes they brake</l>
<l n="216">When they came neere him; and such space did take</l>
<l n="217">Twixt one another, loth to issue on,</l>
<l n="218">That in their shallow furrowes earth was shone,</l>
<l n="219">And the poore lover tooke a little breath:</l>
<l n="220">But the curst Fates sate spinning of his death</l>
<l n="221">On every wave, and with the servile windes</l>
<l n="222">Tumbled them on him: And now <name>Hero</name> findes</l>
<l n="223">By that she felt, her deare <name>Leanders</name> state.</l>
<l n="224">She wept and prayed for him to every fate,</l>
<l n="225">And every winde that whipt her with her haire</l>
<l n="226">About the face, she kist and spake it faire,</l>
<l n="227">Kneeld to it, gave it drinke out of her eyes</l>
<l n="228">To quench his thirst: but still their cruelties</l>
<l n="229">Even her poore Torch envied, and rudely beate</l>
<l n="230">The bating flame from that deare foode it eate:</l>
<l n="231">Deare, for it nourisht her <name>Leanders</name> life,</l>
<l n="232">Which with her robe she rescude from their strife:</l>
<l n="233">But silke too soft was, such hard hearts to breake,</l>
<l n="234">And she deare soule, even as her silke, faint, weake,</l>
<l n="235">Could not preserve it: out, O out it went.</l>
<l n="236"><name>Leander</name> still cald <name>Neptune</name>, that now rent</l>
<l n="237">His brackish curles, and tore his wrinckled face</l>
<l n="238">Where teares in billowes did each other chace,</l>
<l n="239">And (burst with ruth) he hurld his marble Mace</l>
<l n="240">At the sterne Fates: it wounded <name>Lachesis</name></l>
<l n="241">That drew <name>Leanders</name> thread, and could not misse</l>
<l n="242">The thread it selfe, as it her hand did hit,</l>
<l n="243">But smote it full and quite did sunder it.</l>
<l n="244">The more kinde <name>Neptune</name> rag'd, the more he raste</l>
<l n="245">His loves lives fort, and kild as he embraste.</l>
<l n="246">Anger doth still his owne mishap encrease;</l>
<l n="247">If any comfort live, it is in peace.</l>
<l n="248">O theevish Fates, to let Blood, Flesh, and Sence</l>
<l n="249">Build two fayre Temples for their Excellence,</l>
<l n="250">To rob it with a poysoned influence.	</l>
<l n="251">Though soules gifts starve, the bodies are held dear</l>
<l n="252">In ugliest things; Sence-sport preserves a Beare.</l>
<l n="253">But here nought serves our turnes; O heaven and earth,</l>
<l n="254">How most most wretched is our humane birth?</l>
<l n="255">And now did all the tyrannous crew depart,</l>
<l n="256">Knowing there was a storme in <name>Heros</name> hart,</l>
<l n="257">Greater then they could make, and skornd their smart.</l>
<l n="258">She bowd her selfe so low out of her Towre,</l>
<l n="259">That wonder twas she fell not ere her howre,</l>
<l n="260">With searching the lamenting waves for him;</l>
<l n="261">Like a poore Snayle, her gentle supple lim</l>
<l n="262">Hung on her Turrets top so most downe right,</l>
<l n="263">As she would dive beneath the darknes quite,</l>
<l n="264">To finde her Jewell; Jewell, her <name>Leander</name>,</l>
<l n="265">A name of all earths Jewels pleasde not her,</l>
<l n="266">Like his deare name: <name>Leander</name>, still my choice,</l>
<l n="267">Come nought but my <name>Leander</name>; O my voice</l>
<l n="268">Turne to <name>Leander</name>: hence-forth be all sounds,</l>
<l n="269">Accents, and phrases that shew all griefes wounds,</l>
<l n="270">Analisde in <name>Leander</name>. O black change!</l>
<l n="271">Trumpets doe you with thunder of your clange,</l>
<l n="272">Drive out this changes horror, my voyce faints:</l>
<l n="273">Where all joy was, now shrieke out all complaints.</l>
<l n="274">Thus cryed she, for her mixed soule could tell</l>
<l n="275">Her love was dead: And when the morning fell</l>
<l n="276">Prostrate upon the weeping earth for woe,</l>
<l n="277">Blushes that bled out of her cheekes did show,</l>
<l n="278"><name>Leander</name> brought by <name>Neptune</name>, brusde and torne</l>
<l n="279">With Citties ruines he to Rocks had worne,</l>
<l n="280">To filthie usering Rocks that would have blood,</l>
<l n="281">Though they could get of him no other good.</l>
<l n="282">She saw him, and the sight was much much more,</l>
<l n="283">Then might have serv'd to kill her; should her store</l>
<l n="284">Of giant sorrowes speake? Burst, dye, bleede,</l>
<l n="285">And leave poore plaints to us that shall succeede.</l>
<l n="286">She fell on her loves bosome, hugg'd it fast,</l>
<l n="287">And with <name>Leanders</name> name she breath'd her last.</l>
</lg>
<lg><l n="288"><name>Neptune</name> for pittie in his armes did take them,</l>
<l n="289">Flung them into the ayre, and did awake them</l>
<l n="290">Like two sweet birds surnam'd th'<name>Acanthides</name>,</l>
<l n="291">Which we call Thistle-warps, that neere no Seas</l>
<l n="292">Dare ever come, but still in couples flie,</l>
<l n="293">And feede on Thistle tops, to testifie</l>
<l n="294">The hardnes of their first life in their last:</l>
<l n="295">The first in thornes of love, and sorrowes past.</l>
<l n="296">And so most beautifull their colours show,</l>
<l n="297">As none (so little) like them: her sad brow</l>
<l n="298">A sable velvet feather covers quite,</l>
<l n="299">Even like the forehead cloths that in the night,</l>
<l n="300">Or when they sorrow, Ladies use to weare:</l>
<l n="301">Their wings blew, red and yellow mixt appeare,</l>
<l n="302">Colours, that as we construe colours paint</l>
<l n="303">Their states to life; the yellow shewes their saint,</l>
<l n="304">The devill <name>Venus</name>, left them; blew their truth,</l>
<l n="305">The red and black, ensignes of death and ruth.</l>
<l n="306">And this true honor from their love-deaths sprung,</l>
<l n="307">They were the first that ever Poet sung.</l></lg>
</div>
</div>
<!--trailer omitted-->
</body>
</text>
</TEI>