<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng"	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title> The Trew Law Of Free Monarchies: Or The Reciprock And Mvtvall Dvetie Betwixt A Free
     King, And His Naturall Subjects. </title>
    <author>James I</author>
    <editor role="editor">Charles Howard McIlwain</editor>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
     <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
     <name>Anne Mahoney</name>
     <name>David Smith</name>
     <name>Clifford Wulfman</name>
    </respStmt>
    <funder n="org:Tufts">Tufts University</funder>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent/>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
    <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
    <date type="release" when="2001" cert="high">Perseus 3.0</date>
    <idno type="filename">james1.basilikon-doron.perseus-eng1.xml</idno>
    <availability>
     <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative
      Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblStruct>
     <monogr>
      <title>The Politial Works of James I: Reprinted from the Edition of 1616</title>
      <author>James I</author>
      <editor role="editor">Charles Howard McIlwain</editor>
      <imprint>
       <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
       <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
       <date>1918</date>
      </imprint>
     </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <refsDecl n="CTS">
    <cRefPattern matchPattern="(.+)" n="work" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])"/>
   </refsDecl>
   



  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <langUsage>
    <language ident="eng">English</language>
    <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
   </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2000-03-29" who="Tony Lilly">markup</change>

  </revisionDesc>

 </teiHeader>

 <text>
  <front>
   <div subtype="subsection" type="textpart">
    <head>AN ADVERTISEMENT
    <lb/><hi rend="smallcap">To the Reader.</hi></head>
    
    <p><hi rend="italic">ACCEPT, I pray you (my deare countreymen) as thankefully this Pamphlet
     that I offer vnto you, as louingly it is written for your weale. I would be loath
     both to be faschious, and fectlesse: And therefore, if it be not sententious, at least it is
     short. It may be yee misse many things that yee looke for in it: But for excuse thereof,
     consider rightly that I onely lay downe herein the trew grounds, to teach you the right-
     way, without wasting time vpon refuting the aduersaries. And yet I trust, if ye will
     take narrow tent, ye shall finde most of their great gunnes payed home againe, either
     with contrary conclusions, or tacite obiections, suppose in a dairned forme, and in-
     directly: For my intention is to instruct, and not irritat, if I may eschew it. The
     profite I would wish you to make of it, is, as well so to frame all your actions accord-
     ing to these grounds, as may confirme you in the course of honest and obedient Sub-
     iects to your King in all times comming, as also, when ye shall fall in purpose with
     any that shall praise or excuse the by-past rebellions that brake foorth either in this
     countrey, or in any other, ye shall herewith bee armed against their Sirene songs,
     laying their particular examples to the square of these grounds. Whereby yee shall
     soundly keepe the course of righteous Iudgement, decerning wisely of euery action
     onely according to the qualitie thereof, and not according to your pre-iudged conceits
     of the committers: So shall ye, by reaping profit to your selues, turne my paine into
     pleasure. But least the whole Pamphlet runne out at the gaping mouth of this Preface,
     if it were any more enlarged; I end, with committing you to God, and me to your
     charitable censures.</hi>
    </p></div>  
  </front>
  <body>
   <div type="edition" n="urn:cts:engLit:james1.trewlaw.perseus-eng1" xml:lang="eng">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="work" n="1">
     <head>THE TREW LAW OF FREE MONARCHIES: OR THE RECIPROCK
AND MVTVALL DVETIE BETWIXT A FREE KING AND HIS NATURALL SUBJECTS.</head>

<p>As there is not a thing so necessarie to be knowne by the people of any land, next
the knowledge of their God, as the right knowledge of their alleageance, according
to the forme of gouernement established among them, especially in a <hi rend="italic">Monarchie</hi>
(which forme of gouernment, as resembling the Diuinitie, approacheth nearest to
perfection, as all the learned and wise men from the beginning haue agreed vpon;
Vnitie being the perfection of all things,) So hath the ignorance, and (which is
worse) the seduced opinion of the multitude blinded by them, who thinke them-
selues able to teach and instruct the ignorants, procured the wracke and ouer-

<pb n="54"/>

throw of sundry flourishing Common-wealths; and heaped heauy calamities,
threatning vtter destruction vpon others. And the smiling successe, that vnlaw-
full rebellions haue oftentimes had against Princes in aages past (such hath bene
the misery, and iniquitie of the time) hath by way of practise strengthned many
in their errour: albeit there cannot be a more deceiueable argument; then to
iudge ay the iustnesse of the cause by the euent thereof; as hereafter shall be
proued more at length. And among others, no Commonwealth, that euer hath
bene since the beginning, hath had greater need of the trew knowledge of this
ground, then this our so long disordered, and distracted Common-wealth hath:
the misknowledge hereof being the onely spring, from whence haue flowed so
many endlesse calamities, miseries, and confusions, as is better felt by many,
then the cause thereof well knowne, and deepely considered. The naturall zeale
therefore, that I beare to this my natiue countrie, with the great pittie I haue to
see the so-long disturbance thereof for lacke of the trew knowledge of this ground
(as I haue said before) hath compelled me at last to breake silence, to discharge
my conscience to you my deare country men herein, that knowing the ground
from whence these your many endlesse troubles haue proceeded, as well as ye
haue already too-long tasted the bitter fruites thereof, ye may by knowledge,
and eschewing of the cause escape, and diuert the lamentable effects that euer
necessarily follow thereupon. I haue chosen then onely to set downe in this short
Treatise, the trew grounds of the mutuall duetie, and alleageance betwixt a free
and absolute <hi rend="italic">Monarche</hi>, and his people; not to trouble your patience with answer-
ing the contrary propositions, which some haue not bene ashamed to set downe
in writ, to the poysoning of infinite number of simple soules, and their owne per-
petuall, and well deserued infamie: For by answering them, I could not haue
eschewed whiles to pick, and byte wel saltly their persons; which would rather
haue bred contentiousnesse among the readers (as they had liked or misliked)
then sound instruction of the trewth: Which I protest to him that is the searcher
of all hearts, is the onely marke that I shoot at herein.
</p>
<p>First then, I will set downe the trew grounds, whereupon I am to build, out
of the Scriptures, since <hi rend="italic">Monarchie</hi> is the trew paterne of Diuinitie, as I haue
already said: next, from the fundamental Lawes of our owne Kingdome, which
nearest must concerne vs: thirdly, from the law of Nature, by diuers similitudes
drawne out of the same: and will conclude syne by answering the most waighty
and appearing incommodities that can be obiected.
</p>
<p>The Princes duetie to his Subiects is so clearely set downe in many places of
the Scriptures, and so openly confessed by all the good Princes, according to their
oath in their Coronation, as not needing to be long therein, I shall as shortly
as I can runne through it.
</p>
<p>Kings are called Gods <note anchored="true" place="foot">Psal. 82. 6.</note> by the propheticall King <hi rend="italic">Dauid</hi>, because they sit vpon
GOD his Throne in the earth, and haue the count of their administration to giue


<pb n="55"/>
 vnto him. Their office is, <hi rend="italic">To minister Iustice and Iudgement to the people,</hi><note anchored="true" place="foot">Psal. 101.</note> as the
 same <hi rend="italic">Dauid</hi> saith: <hi rend="italic">To aduance the good, and punish the euill</hi>,<note anchored="true" place="foot">Psal. 101.</note> as he likewise saith:
 <hi rend="italic">To establish good Lawes to his people, and procure obedience to the same</hi>,<note anchored="true" place="foot">2. King. 18.</note> as diuers
 good Kings of <hi rend="italic">Iudah</hi><note anchored="true" place="foot">2. Chron. 29; 2. King. 22; and 23. 2; chro. 34, &amp; 35.</note> did: <hi rend="italic">To procure the peace of the people</hi>, as the same <hi rend="italic">Dauid</hi>
 saith:<note anchored="true" place="foot">Psal. 72.</note> <hi rend="italic">To decide all controuersies that can arise among them <note anchored="true" place="foot">I. King 3.</note> as Salomon</hi> did: <hi rend="italic">To
 be the Minister of God for the weale of them that doe well, and as the minister of God,
 to take vengeance vpon them that doe euill</hi>,<note anchored="true" place="foot">Rom. 13.</note> as S. <hi rend="italic">Paul</hi> saith. And finally, <hi rend="italic">As a good
 Pastour, to goe out and in before his people</hi> <note anchored="true" place="foot">I. Sam. 8.</note> as is said in the first of <hi rend="italic">Samuel: That
 through the Princes prosperitie, the peoples peace may be procured</hi><note anchored="true" place="foot">Ierem. 29.</note>, as <hi rend="italic">Ieremie</hi>
 saith.
</p>
<p>And therefore in the Coronation of our owne Kings, as well as of euery Chris-
 tian <hi rend="italic">Monarche</hi> they giue their Oath, first to maintaine the Religion presently
 professed within their countrie, according to their lawes, whereby it is established,
 and to punish all those that should presse to alter, or disturbe the profession
 thereof; And next to maintaine all the lowable and good Lawes made by their
 predecessours: to see them put in execution, and the breakers and violaters
 thereof, to be punished, according to the tenour of the same: And lastly, to main-
 taine the whole countrey, and euery state therein, in all their ancient Priuiledges
 and Liberties, as well against all forreine enemies, as among themselues: And
 shortly to procure the weale and flourishing of his people, not onely in maintain-
 ing and putting to execution the olde lowable lawes of the countrey, and by estab-
 lishing of new (as necessitie and euill maners will require) but by all other meanes
 possible to fore-see and preuent all dangers, that are likely to fall vpon them, and
 to maintaine concord, wealth, and ciuilitie among them, as a louing Father, and
 careful watchman, caring for them more then for himselfe, knowing himselfe to
 be ordained for them, and they not for him; and therefore countable to that great
 God, who placed him as his lieutenant ouer them, vpon the perill of his soule to
 procure the weale of both soules and bodies, as farre as in him lieth, of all them
 that are committed to his charge. And this oath in the Coronation is the clearest,
 ciuill, and fundamentall Law, whereby the Kings office is properly defined.
</p>
<p>By the Law of Nature the King becomes a naturall Father to all his Lieges at
his Coronation: And as the Father of his fatherly duty is bound to care for the
nourishing, education, and vertuous gouernment of his children; euen so is the
king bound to care for all his subiects. As all the toile and paine that the father
can take for his children, will be thought light and well bestowed by him, so that
the effect thereof redound to their profite and weale; so ought the Prince to doe
towards his people. As the kindly father ought to foresee all inconuenients and
dangers that may arise towards his children, and though with the hazard of his
owne person presse to preuent the same; so ought the King towards his people.
As the fathers wrath and correction vpon any of his children that offendeth, ought

<pb n="56"/>
to be by a fatherly chastisement seasoned with pitie, as long as there is any hope
of amendment in them; so ought the King towards any of his Lieges that offend
in that measure. And shortly, as the Fathers chiefe ioy ought to be in procuring
his childrens welfare, reioycing at their weale, sorrowing and pitying at their
euill, to hazard for their safetie, trauell for their rest, wake for their sleepe; and
in a word, to thinke that his earthly felicitie and life standeth and liueth more in
them, nor in himselfe; so ought a good Prince thinke of his people.
</p>
<p>As to the other branch of this mutuall and reciprock band, is the duety and
alleageance that the Lieges owe to their King: the ground whereof, I take out
of the words of <hi rend="italic">Samuel</hi>, dited by Gods Spirit, when God had giuen him com-
mandement to heare the peoples voice in choosing and annointing them a King.
And because that place of Scripture being well understood, is so pertinent for
our purpose, I haue insert herein the very words of the Text.
<list type="simple">
<item>      9<hi rend="italic"> Now therefore hearken to their voice: howbeit yet testifie vnto them, and shew
          them the maner of the King, that shall raigne ouer them.</hi></item>
<item>     10 <hi rend="italic">So</hi> Samuel <hi rend="italic">tolde all the wordes of the Lord vnto the people that asked a King of
          him.</hi></item>
<item>      11   <hi rend="italic">And he said, This shall be the maner of the King that shall raigne ouer you: he
          will take your sonnes, and appoint them to his Charets, and to be his horsemen,
          and some shall runne before his Charet.</hi></item>
<item>      12 <hi rend="italic">Also, hee will make them his captaines ouer thousands, and captaines ouer fif-
          ties, and to eare his ground, and to reape his haruest, and to make instruments
          of warre and the things that serue for his charets:</hi></item>
<item>      13 <hi rend="italic">Hee will also take your daughters, and make them Apothicaries, and Cookes,
          and Bakers.</hi></item>
<item>      14 <hi rend="italic">And hee will take your fields, and your vineyards, and your best Oliue trees,
          and giue them to his seruants.</hi></item>
<item>      15 <hi rend="italic">And he will take the tenth of your seed, and of your Vineyards, and giue it to his
          Eunuches, and to his seruants.</hi></item>
<item>      16 <hi rend="italic">And he will take your men seruants, and your maid-seruants, and the chiefe of
          your young men, and your asses, and put them to his worke.</hi></item>
<item>      17 <hi rend="italic">He will take the tenth of your sheepe: and ye shall be his seruants.</hi></item>
<item>      18 <hi rend="italic">And ye shall cry out at that day, because of your King, whom ye haue chosen
          you: and the Lord God will not heare you at that day.</hi></item>
<item>      19 <hi rend="italic">But the people would not heare the voice of</hi> Samuel, <hi rend="italic">but did say: Nay, but
          there shalbe a King ouer vs.</hi></item>
<item>      20 <hi rend="italic">And we also willbe all like other Nations, and our King shall iudge vs, and
          goe out before vs, and fight our battels.</hi></item>
</list></p>
<p>That these words, and discourses of <hi rend="italic">Samuel</hi> were dited by Gods Spirit, it
needs no further probation, but that it is a place of Scripture; since the whole
Scripture is dited by that inspiration, as <hi rend="italic">Paul</hi> saith: which ground no good

<pb n="57"/>
Christian will, or dare denie. Whereupon it must necessarily follow, that these
speeches proceeded not from any ambition in <hi rend="italic">Samuel</hi>, as one loath to quite the
reines that he so long had ruled, and therefore desirous, by making odious the
gouernment of a King, to disswade the people from their farther importunate
crauing of one: For, as the text proueth it plainly, he then conueened them to giue
them a resolute grant of their demand, as God by his owne mouth commanded
him, saying,
         <hi rend="blockquote"> <hi rend="italic">Hearken to the voice of the people.</hi></hi>
And to presse to disswade them from that, which he then came to grant vnto them,
were a thing very impertinent in a wise man; much more in the Prophet of the
most high God. And likewise, it well appeared in all the course of his life after,
that so long refusing of their sute before came not of any ambition in him: which
he well proued in praying, &amp; as it were importuning God for the weale of <hi rend="italic">Saul.</hi>
Yea, after God had declared his reprobation vnto him, yet he desisted not, while
God himselfe was wrath at his praying, and discharged his fathers suit in that
errand. And that these words of <hi rend="italic">Samuel</hi> were not vttered as a prophecie of <hi rend="italic">Saul</hi>
their first Kings defection, it well appeareth, as well because we heare no mention
made in the Scripture of any his tyrannie and oppression, (which, if it had beene,
would not haue been left vnpainted out therein, as well as his other faults were,
as in a trew mirrour of all the Kings behauiours, whom it describeth) as likewise
in respect that <hi rend="italic">Saul</hi> was chosen by God for his vertue, and meet qualities to
gouerne his people: whereas his defection sprung after-hand from the corruption
of his owne nature, &amp; not through any default in God, whom they that thinke so,
would make as a step-father to his people, in making wilfully a choise of the
vnmeetest for gouerning them, since the election of that King lay absolutely and
immediatly in Gods hand. But by the contrary it is plaine, and euident, that this
speech of <hi rend="italic">Samuel</hi> to the people, was to prepare their hearts before the hand to the
due obedience of that King, which God was to giue vnto them; and therefore
opened vp vnto them, what might be the intollerable qualities that might fall in
some of their kings, thereby preparing them to patience, not to resist to Gods
ordinance: but as he would haue said; Since God hath granted your importunate
suit in giuing you a king, as yee haue else committed an errour in shaking off Gods
yoke, and ouer-hastie seeking of a King; so beware yee fall not into the next, in
casting off also rashly that yoke, which God at your earnest suite hath laid vpon
you, how hard that euer it seeme to be: For as ye could not haue obtained one
without the permission and ordinance of God, so may yee no more, fro hee be
once set ouer you, shake him off without the same warrant. And therefore in
time arme your selues with patience and humilitie, since he that hath the only
power to make him, hath the onely power to vnmake him; and ye onely to obey,
bearing with these straits that I now foreshew you, as with the finger of God,
which lieth not in you to take off.

<pb n="58"/>
</p>
<p>And will ye consider the very wordes of the text in order, as they are set downe,
it shall plainely declare the obedience that the people owe to their King in all
respects.
</p>
<p>First, God commandeth <hi rend="italic">Samuel</hi> to doe two things: the one, to grant the people
their suit in giuing them a king; the other, to forewarne them, what some kings
will doe vnto them, that they may not thereafter in their grudging and murmur-
ing say, when they shal feele the snares here fore-spoken; We would neuer haue
had a king of God, in case when we craued him, hee had let vs know how wee
would haue beene vsed by him, as now we finde but ouer-late. And this is meant
by these words:
     </p><p><hi rend="italic">Now therefore hearken vnto their voice: howbeit yet testifie vnto them, and shew
them the maner of the King that shall rule ouer them.</hi>
</p>
<p>And next, <hi rend="italic">Samuel</hi> in execution of this commandement of God, hee likewise
doeth two things.
</p>
<p>First, hee declares vnto them, what points of iustice and equitie their king will
breake in his behauiour vnto them: And next he putteth them out of hope, that
wearie as they will, they shall not haue leaue to shake off that yoke, which God
through their importunitie hath laide vpon them. The points of equitie that the
King shall breake vnto them, are expressed in these words:
     <list type="simple"><item>11<hi rend="italic"> He will take your sonnes, and appoint them to his Charets, and to be his horse-
          men, and some shall run before his Charet.</hi>
     </item><item>12 <hi rend="italic">Also he will make them his captaines ouer thousands, and captaines ouerfifties,
          and to eare his ground, and to reape his haruest, and to make instruments of
          warre, and the things that serue for his charets.</hi>
     </item><item>13 <hi rend="italic">He will also take your daughters, and make them Apothecaries, and Cookes,
          and Bakers.</hi></item>
</list></p>
<p>The points of Iustice, that hee shall breake vnto them, are expressed in these
wordes:
     <list type="simple"><item>14 <hi rend="italic">Hee will take your fields, and your vineyards, and your best Oliue trees, and
          giue them to his seruants.</hi></item>
<item>     15 <hi rend="italic">And he will take the tenth of your seede, and of your vineyards, and giue it to
          his Eunuches and to his seruants: and also the tenth of your sheepe.</hi></item>
</list></p>
<p>As if he would say; The best and noblest of your blood shall be compelled in
slauish and seruile offices to serue him: and not content of his owne patrimonie,
will make vp a rent to his owne vse out of your best lands, vineyards, orchards,
and store of cattell: So as inuerting the Law of nature, and office of a King, your
persons and the persons of your posteritie, together with your lands, and all that
ye possesse shall serue his priuate vse, and inordinate appetite.
</p>
<p>And as vnto the next point (which is his fore-warning them, that, weary as
 they will, they shall not haue leaue to shake off the yoke, which God thorow their
 importunity hath laid vpon them) it is expressed in these words:

<pb n="59"/>
 <list type="simple"><item>    18 <hi rend="italic">And yee shall crie out at that day, because of your King whom yee haue chosen
          you: and the Lord will not heare you at that day.</hi></item>
</list></p>
<p>As he would say; When ye shall finde these things in proofe that now I fore-
warne you of, although you shall grudge and murmure, yet it shal not be lawful
to you to cast it off, in respect it is not only the ordinance of God, but also your
selues haue chosen him vnto you, thereby renouncing for euer all priuiledges, by
your willing consent out of your hands, whereby in any time hereafter ye would
claime, and call backe vnto your selues againe that power, which God shall not
permit you to doe. And for further taking away of all excuse, and retraction of
this their contract, after their consent to vnder-lie this yoke with all the burthens
that hee hath declared vnto them, he craues their answere, and consent to his
proposition: which appeareth by their answere, as it is expressed in these words:
     <list type="simple"><item>19 <hi rend="italic">Nay, but there shall be a King ouer vs. 20 And we also will be like all other
          nations: and our king shall iudge vs, and goe out before vs and fight our battels.</hi></item></list>
</p>
<p>As if they would haue said; All your speeches and hard conditions shall not
skarre vs, but we will take the good and euill of it vpon vs, and we will be content
to beare whatsoeuer burthen it shal please our King to lay vpon vs, aswell as other
nations doe. And for the good we will get of him in fighting our battels, we will
more patiently beare any burden that shall please him to lay on vs.
</p>
<p>Now then, since the erection of this Kingdome and Monarchie among the
Iewes, and the law thereof may, and ought to bee a paterne to all Christian and
well founded Monarchies, as beeing founded by God himselfe, who by his Oracle,
and out of his owne mouth gaue the law thereof: what liberty can broiling spirits,
and rebellious minds claime iustly to against any Christian Monarchie; since
they can claime to no greater libertie on their part, nor the people of God might
haue done, and no greater tyranny was euer executed by any Prince or tyrant,
whom they can obiect, nor was here fore-warned to the people of God, (and yet
all rebellion countermanded vnto them) if tyrannizing ouer mens persons, sonnes,
daughters and seruants; redacting noble houses, and men, and women of noble
blood, to slauish and seruile offices; and extortion, and spoile of their lands and
goods to the princes owne priuate vse and commoditie, and of his courteours, and
seruants, may be called a tyrannie ?
</p>
<p>And that this proposition grounded vpon the Scripture, may the more clearly
 appeare to be trew by the practise oft prooued in the same booke, we neuer reade,
 that euer the Prophets perswaded the people to rebell against the Prince, how
 wicked soeuer he was.
</p>
<p>When <hi rend="italic">Samuel</hi> by Gods command pronounced to the same king <hi rend="italic">Saul</hi>, that his
 kingdome was rent from him, and giuen to another (which in effect was a degrad-
 ing of him) yet his next action following that, was peaceably to turne home, and
 with floods of teares to pray to God to haue some compassion vpon him.<note anchored="true" place="foot">I. Sam. 15.</note>


<pb n="60"/>

</p>
<p>And <hi rend="italic">David</hi>, notwithstanding hee was inaugurate in that same degraded Kings
 roome, not onely (when he was cruelly persecuted, for no offence; but good
 seruice done vnto him) would not presume, hauing him in his power, skantly, but
 with great reuerence, to touch the garment of the annoynted of the Lord, and in
 his words blessed him:<note anchored="true" place="foot"> I. Sam. 24.</note>  but likewise, when one came to him vanting himselfe
 vntrewly to haue slaine <hi rend="italic">Saul</hi>, hee, without forme of proces, or triall of his guilt,
 caused onely for guiltinesse of his tongue, put him to sodaine death.<note anchored="true" place="foot">2. Sam. 1 </note>
</p>
<p>And although there was neuer a more monstrous persecutor, and tyrant nor
 <hi rend="italic">Achab</hi> was: yet all the rebellion, that <hi rend="italic">Elias</hi> euer raised against him, was to flie to
 the wildernes: where for fault of sustentation, he was fed with the Corbies. And
 I thinke no man will doubt but <hi rend="italic">Samuel, Dauid</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Elias</hi>, had as great power to
 perswade the people, if they had like to haue employed their credite to vproares
 &amp; rebellions against these wicked kings, as any of our seditious preachers in these
 daies of whatsoeuer religion, either in this countrey or in France, had, that busied
 themselues most to stir vp rebellion vnder cloake of religion. This farre the only
 loue of veritie, I protest, without hatred at their persons, haue mooued me to
 be somewhat satyricke.
</p>
<p>And if any will leane to the extraordinarie examples of degrading or killing of
 kings in the Scriptures, thereby to cloake the peoples rebellion, as by the deed of
 <hi rend="italic">Iehu</hi>, and such like extraordinaries: I answere, besides that they want the like
 warrant that they had, if extraordinarie examples of the Scripture shall bee
 drawne in daily practise; murther vnder traist as in the persons of <hi rend="italic">Ahud</hi>, and
 <hi rend="italic">Iael</hi>; theft, as in the persons of the <hi rend="italic">Israelites</hi> comming out of <hi rend="italic">Egypt</hi>; lying to their
 parents to the hurt of their brother, as in the person of Iacob, shall all be counted
 as lawfull and allowable vertues, as rebellion against Princes. And to conclude,
 the practise through the whole Scripture prooueth the peoples obedience giuen
 to that sentence in the law of God:
          <hi rend="blockquote"><hi rend="italic">Thou shalt not rayle vpon the Iudges, neither speake euill of the ruler of
                  thy people.</hi></hi>
</p>
<p>To end then the ground of my proposition taken out of the Scripture, let two
 speciall, and notable examples, one vnder the law, another vnder the Euangel,
 conclude this part of my alleageance. Vnder the lawe, Ieremie threatneth the
 people of God with vtter destruction for rebellion to <hi rend="italic">Nabuchadnezar</hi> the king of
 Babel:<note anchored="true" place="foot">Ier. 27.</note> who although he was an idolatrous persecuter, a forraine King, a Tyrant,
 and vsurper of their liberties; yet in respect they had once receiued and acknowl-
 edged him for their king, he not only commandeth them to obey him, but euen
 to pray for his prosperitie, adioyning the reason to it; because in his prosperitie
 stood their peace.<note anchored="true" place="foot">Iere. 29.</note>
</p>
<p>And vnder the Euangel, that king, whom <hi rend="italic">Paul</hi> bids the <hi rend="italic">Romanes obey</hi> and
<hi rend="italic">serue for conscience sake</hi>, was <hi rend="italic">Nero</hi> that bloody tyrant, an infamie to his aage, and

 <pb n="61"/>

 a monster to the world, being also an idolatrous persecuter, as the King of <hi rend="italic">Babel</hi>
 was. If then Idolatrie and defection from God, tyranny ouer their people, and
 persecution of the Saints, for their profession sake, hindred not the Spirit of God
 to command his people vnder all highest paine to giue them all due and heartie
 obedience for conscience sake, giuing to <hi rend="italic">Caesar</hi> that which was <hi rend="italic">Caesars</hi>, and to God
 that which was Gods, as Christ saith; and that this practise throughout the booke
 of God agreeth with this lawe, which he made in the erection of that Monarchie
 (as is at length before deduced) what shamelesse presumption is it to any Chris-
 tian people now adayes to claime to that vnlawfull libertie, which God refused to
 his owne peculiar and chosen people ? <note anchored="true" place="foot">Iere. 13.</note> Shortly then to take vp in two or three
 sentences, grounded vpon all these arguments, out of the lawe of God, the duetie,
 and alleageance of the people to their lawfull king, their obedience, I say, ought
 to be to him, as to Gods Lieutenant in earth, obeying his commands in all thing,
 except directly against God, as the commands of Gods Minister, acknowledging
 him a Iudge set by GOD ouer them, hauing power to iudge them, but to be iudged
 onely by GOD, whom to onely hee must giue count of his iudgement; fearing him
 as their Iudge, louing him as their father; praying for him as their protectour;
 for his continuance, if he be good; for his amendement, if he be wicked; following
 and obeying his lawfull commands, eschewing and flying his fury in his vnlawfull,
 without resistance, but by sobbes and teares to God, according to that sentence
 vsed in the primitiue Church in the time of the persecution.
                            <hi rend="blockquote"><hi rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="lat">Preces, &amp; Lachrymae sunt arma Ecclesiae.</foreign></hi></hi>
</p>
<p>Now, as for the describing the allegeance, that the lieges owe to their natiue
 King, out of the fundamentall and ciuill Lawe, especially of this contrey, as I
 promised, the ground must first be set downe of the first maner of establishing the
 Lawes and forme of gouernement among vs; that the ground being first right
 laide, we may thereafter build rightly thereupon. Although it be trew (according
 to the affirmation of those that pryde themselues to be the scourges of Tyrants)
 that in the first beginning of Kings rising among the Gentiles, in the time of the
 first aage, diuers commonwealths and societies of men choosed out one among
 themselues, who for his vertues and valour, being more eminent then the rest, was
 chosen out by them, and set vp in that roome, to maintaine the weakest in their
 right, to throw downe oppressours, and to foster and continue the societie among
 men; which could not otherwise, but by vertue of that vnitie be wel done: yet
 these examples are nothing pertinent to vs; because our Kingdome and diuers
 other Monarchies are not in that case, but had their beginning in a farre contrary
 fashion.
</p>
<p>For as our Chronicles beare witnesse, this Ile, and especially our part of it,
being scantly inhabited, but by very few, and they as barbarous and scant of
ciuilitie, as number, there comes our first King <hi rend="italic">Fergus</hi>, with a great number with

<pb n="62"/>

him, out of <hi rend="italic">Ireland</hi>, which was long inhabited before vs, and making himself
master of the countrey, by his owne friendship, and force, as well of the <hi rend="italic">Ireland-
men</hi> that came with him, as of the countrey-men that willingly fell to him, hee
made himselfe King and Lord, as well of the whole landes, as of the whole inhabi-
tants within the same. Thereafter he and his successours, a long while after their
being Kinges, made and established their lawes from time to time, and as the
occasion required. So the trewth is directly contrarie in our state to the false
affirmation of such seditious writers, as would perswade vs, that the Lawes and
state of our countrey were established before the admitting of a king: where by
the countrarie ye see it plainely prooued, that a wise king comming in among
barbares, first established the estate and forme of gouernement, and thereafter
made lawes by himselfe, and his successours according thereto.
</p>
<p>The kings therefore in <hi rend="italic">Scotland</hi> were before any estates or rankes of men within
the same, before any Parliaments were holden, or lawes made: and by them was
the land distributed (which at the first was whole theirs) states erected and
decerned, and formes of gouernement deuised and established: And so it followes
of necessitie, that the kings were the authors and makers of the Lawes, and not
the Lawes of the kings. And to prooue this my assertion more clearly, it is eui-
dent by the rolles of our Chancellery (which containe our eldest and fundamentall
Lawes) that the King is <hi rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="lat">Dominus omnium bonorum</foreign></hi>, and <hi rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="lat">Dominus directus totius
Dominij</foreign></hi>, the whole subiects being but his vassals, and from him holding all their
lands as their ouer-lord, who according to good seruices done vnto him, chaungeth
their holdings from tacke to few, from ward to blanch, erecteth new Baronies,
and vniteth olde, without aduice or authoritie of either Parliament or any other
subalterin iudiciall seate: So as if wrong might bee admitted in play (albeit I
grant wrong should be wrong in all persons) the King might haue a better colour
for his pleasure, without further reason, to take the land from his lieges, as ouer-
lord of the whole, and doe with it as pleaseth him, since all that they hold is of
him, then, as foolish writers say, the people might vnmake the king, and put an
other in his roome: But either of them as vnlawful, and against the ordinance of
God, ought to be alike odious to be thought, much lesse put in practise.
</p>
<p>And according to these fundamentall Lawes already alledged, we daily see
that in the Parliament (which is nothing else but the head Court of the king and
his vassals) the lawes are but craued by his subiects, and onely made by him at
their rogation, and with their aduice: For albeit the king make daily statutes and
ordinances, enioyning such paines thereto as hee thinkes meet, without any
aduice of Parliament or estates; yet it lies in the power of no Parliament, to make
any kinde of Lawe or Statute, without his Scepter be to it, for giuing it the force
of a Law: And although diuers changes haue beene in other countries of the blood
Royall, and kingly house, the kingdome being reft by conquest from one to
another, as in our neighbour countrey in <hi rend="italic">England</hi>, (which was neuer in ours) yet
the same ground of the kings right ouer all the land, and subiects thereof re-

<pb n="63"/>

 maineth alike in all other free Monarchies, as well as in this: For when the
 Bastard of <hi rend="italic">Normandie</hi> came into <hi rend="italic">England</hi>, and made himselfe king, was it not by
 force, and with a mighty army ? Where he gaue the Law, and tooke none,
 changed the Lawes, inuerted the order of gouernement, set downe the strangers
 his followers in many of the old possessours roomes, as at this day well appeareth
 a great part of the Gentlemen in <hi rend="italic">England</hi>, beeing come of the <hi rend="italic">Norman</hi> blood, and
 their old Lawes, which to this day they are ruled by, are written in his language,
 and not in theirs: And yet his successours haue with great happinesse enioyed the
 Crowne to this day; Whereof the like was also done by all them that conquested
 them before.
</p>
<p>And for conclusion of this point, that the king is ouer-lord ouer the whole
lands, it is likewise daily proued by the Law of our hoordes, of want of Heires,
and of Bastardies: For if a hoord be found vnder the earth, because it is no more
in the keeping or vse of any person, it of the law pertains to the king. If a person,
inheritour of any lands or goods, dye without any sort of heires, all his landes and
goods returne to the king. And if a bastard die vnrehabled without heires of his
bodie (which rehabling onely lyes in the kings hands) all that hee hath likewise
returnes to the king. And as ye see it manifest, that the King is ouer-Lord of the
whole land: so is he Master ouer euery person that inhabiteth the same, hauing
power ouer the life and death of euery one of them: For although a iust Prince
will not take the life of any of his subiects without a cleare law; yet the same
lawes whereby he taketh them, are made by himselfe, or his predecessours; and
so the power flowes alwaies from him selfe; as by daily experience we see, good
and iust Princes will from time to time make new lawes and statutes, adioyning
the penalties to the breakers thereof, which before the law was made, had beene
no crime to the subiect to haue committed. Not that I deny the old definition of
a King, and of a law; which makes the king to bee a speaking law, and the Law a
dumbe king: for certainely a king that gouernes not by his lawe, can neither be
countable to God for his administration, nor haue a happy and established raigne:
For albeit it be trew that I haue at length prooued, that the King is aboue the
law, as both the author and giuer of strength thereto; yet a good king will not
onely delight to rule his subiects by the lawe, but euen will conforme himselfe in
his owne actions thereuneto, alwaies keeping that ground, that the health of the
common-wealth be his chiefe lawe: And where he sees the lawe doubtsome or
rigorous, hee may interpret or mitigate the same, lest otherwise <hi rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="lat">Summum ius</foreign></hi> bee
<hi rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="lat">summa iniuria</foreign></hi>: And therefore generall lawes, made publikely in Parliament, may
vpon knowen respects to the King by his authoritie bee mitigated, and suspended
vpon causes onely knowen to him.
</p>
<p>As likewise, although I haue said, a good king will frame all his actions to be
according to the Law; yet is hee not bound thereto but of his good will, and for
good example-giuing to his subiects: For as in the law of abstaining from eating
of flesh in <hi rend="italic">Lenton</hi>, the king will, for examples sake, make his owne house to obserue

<pb n="64"/>
the Law; yet no man will thinke he needs to take a licence to eate flesh. And
although by our Lawes, the bearing and wearing of hag-buts, and pistolets be
forbidden, yet no man can find any fault in the King, for causing his traine vse
them in any raide vpon the Borderers, or other malefactours or rebellious subiects.
So as I haue alreadie said, a good King, although hee be aboue the Law, will subiect
and frame his actions thereto, for examples sake to his subiects, and of his owne
free-will, but not as subiect or bound thereto.
</p>
<p>Since I haue so clearly prooued then out of the fundamentall lawes and prac-
tise of this country, what right &amp; power a king hath ouer his land and subiects, it
is easie to be vnderstood, what allegeance &amp; obedience his lieges owe vnto him;
I meane alwaies of such free Monarchies as our king is, and not of electiue kings,
and much lesse of such sort of gouernors, as the dukes of <hi rend="italic">Venice</hi> are, whose
Aristocratick and limited gouernment, is nothing like to free Monarchies; al-
though the malice of some writers hath not beene ashamed to mis-know any
difference to be betwixt them. And if it be not lawfull to any particular Lordes
tenants or vassals, vpon whatsoeuer pretext, to controll and displace their Master,
and ouer-lord (as is clearer nor the Sunne by all Lawes of the world) how much lesse
may the subiects and vassals of the great ouer-lord the KING controll or displace
him ? And since in all inferiour iudgements in the land, the people may not vpon
any respects displace their Magistrates, although but subaltern: for the people
of a borough, cannot displace their Prouost before the time of their election: nor
in Ecclesiasticall policie the flocke can vpon any pretence displace the Pastor, nor
iudge of him: yea euen the poore Schoolemaster cannot be displaced by his
schollers: If these, I say (whereof some are but inferiour, subaltern, and tem-
porall Magistrates, and none of them equall in any sort to the dignitie of a King)
cannot be displaced for any occasion or pretext by them that are ruled by them:
how much lesse is it lawfull vpon any pretext to controll or displace the great
Prouost, and great Schoole-master of the whole land: except by inuerting the
order of all Law and reason, the commanded may be made to command their
commander, the iudged to iudge their Iudge, and they that are gouerned, to
gouerne their time about their Lord and gouernour.
</p>
<p>And the agreement of the Law of nature in this our ground with the Lawes
and constitutions of God, and man, already alledged, will by two similitudes
easily appeare. The King towards his people is rightly compared to a father of
children, and to a head of a body composed of diuers members: For as fathers,
the good Princes, and Magistrates of the people of God acknowledged themselues
to their subiects. And for all other well ruled Common-wealths, the stile of <hi rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="lat">Pater
patriae</foreign></hi> was euer, and is commonly vsed to Kings. And the proper office of a King
towards his Subiects, agrees very wel with the office of the head towards the body,
and all members thereof: For from the head, being the seate of Iudgement, pro-
ceedeth the care and foresight of guiding, and preuenting all euill that may come
to the body or any part thereof. The head cares for the body, so doeth the King

<pb n="65"/>

for his people. As the discourse and direction flowes from the head, and the
execution according thereunto belongs to the rest of the members, euery one
according to their office: so it is betwixt a wise Prince, and his people. As the
iudgement comming from the head may not onely imploy the members, euery one
in their owne office, as long as they are able for it; but likewise in case any of them
be affected with any infirmitie must care and prouide for their remedy, in-case it
be curable, and if otherwise, gar cut them off for feare of infecting of the rest:
euen so is it betwixt the Prince, and his people. And as there is euer hope of
curing any diseased member by the direction of the head, as long as it is whole;
but by the contrary, if it be troubled, all the members are partakers of that paine,
so is it betwixt the Prince and his people.
</p>
<p>And now first for the fathers part (whose naturall loue to his children I
described in the first part of this my discourse, speaking of the dutie that Kings
owe to their Subiects) consider, I pray you what duetie his children owe to him, &amp;
whether vpon any pretext whatsoeuer, it wil not be thought monstrous and vn-
naturall to his sons, to rise vp against him, to control him at their appetite, and
when they thinke good to sley him, or to cut him off, and adopt to themselues
any other they please in his roome: Or can any pretence of wickednes or rigor on
his part be a iust excuse for his children to put hand into him ? And although
wee see by the course of nature, that loue vseth to descend more then to ascend,
in case it were trew, that the father hated and wronged the children neuer so
much, will any man, endued with the least sponke of reason, thinke it lawfull for
them to meet him with the line ? Yea, suppose the father were furiously follow-
ing his sonnes with a drawen sword, is it lawfull for them to turne and strike
againe, or make any resistance but by flight ? I thinke surely, if there were no
more but the example of bruit beasts &amp; vnreasonable creatures, it may serue well
enough to qualifie and proue this my argument. We reade often the pietie that
the Storkes haue to their olde and decayed parents: And generally wee know,
that there are many sorts of beasts and fowles, that with violence and many
bloody strokes will beat and banish their yong ones from them, how soone they
perceiue them to be able to fend themselues; but wee neuer read or heard of any
resistance on their part, except among the vipers; which prooues such persons, as
ought to be reasonable creatures, and yet vnnaturally follow this example, to be
endued with their viperous nature.
</p>

<p>And for the similitude of the head and the body, it may very well fall out that
 the head will be forced to garre cut off some rotten members (as I haue already
 said) to keep the rest of the body in integritie: but what state the body can be in,
 if the head, for any infirmitie that can fall to it, be cut off, I leaue it to the readers
 iudgement.
</p>
<p>So as (to conclude this part) if the children may vpon any pretext that can be
 imagined, lawfully rise vp against their Father, cut him off, &amp; choose any other
 whom they please in his roome; and if the body for the weale of it, may for any

<pb n="66"/>

infirmitie that can be in the head, strike it off, then I cannot deny that the people
may rebell, controll, and displace, or cut off their king at their owne pleasure, and
vpon respects moouing them. And whether these similitudes represent better the
office of a King, or the offices of Masters or Deacons of crafts, or Doctors in
Physicke (which iolly comparisons are vsed by such writers as maintaine the
contrary proposition) I leaue it also to the readers discretion.
</p>
<p>And in case any doubts might arise in any part of this treatise, I wil (according
 to my promise) with the solution of foure principall and most weightie doubts,
 that the aduersaries may obiect, conclude this discourse. And first it is casten vp
 by diuers, that employ their pennes vpon Apologies for rebellions and treasons,
 that euery man is borne to carry such a naturall zeale and duety to his common-
 wealth, as to his mother; that seeing it so rent and deadly wounded, as whiles it
 will be by wicked and tyrannous Kings, good Citizens will be forced, for the
 naturall zeale and duety they owe to their owne natiue countrey, to put their
 hand to worke for freeing their common-wealth from such a pest.
</p>
<p>Whereunto I giue two answeres: First, it is a sure Axiome in <hi rend="italic">Theologie</hi>, that
euill should not be done, that good may come of it: The wickednesse therefore of
the King can neuer make them that are ordained to be iudged by him, to become
his Iudges. And if it be not lawfull to a priuate man to reuenge his priuate iniury
vpon his priuate aduersary (since God hath onely giuen the sword to the Magis-
trate) how much lesse is it lawfull to the people, or any part of them (who all are
but priuate men, the authoritie being alwayes with the Magistrate, as I haue
already proued) to take vpon them the vse of the sword, whom to it belongs not,
against the publicke Magistrate, whom to onely it belongeth.
</p>
<p>Next, in place of relieuing the common-wealth out of distresse (which is their
onely excuse and colour) they shall heape double distresse and desolation vpon it;
and so their rebellion shall procure the contrary effects that they pretend it for:
For a king cannot be imagined to be so vnruly and tyrannous, but the common-
wealth will be kept in better order, notwithstanding thereof, by him, then it can
be by his way-taking. For first, all sudden mutations are perillous in common-
wealths, hope being thereby giuen to all bare men to set vp themselues, and flie
with other mens feathers, the reines being loosed to all the insolencies that dis-
ordered people can commit by hope of impunitie, because of the loosenesse of
all things.
</p>
<p>And next, it is certaine that a king can neuer be so monstrously vicious, but
hee will generally fauour iustice, and maintaine some order, except in the par-
ticulars, wherein his inordinate lustes and passions cary him away; where by the
contrary, no King being, nothing is vnlawfull to none: And so the olde opinion
of the Philosophers prooues trew, That better it is to liue in a Common-wealth,
where nothing is lawfull, then where all things are lawfull to all men; the Com-
mon-wealth at that time resembling an vndanted young horse that hath casten
his rider: For as the diuine Poet <hi rend="smallcap">Dv Bartas</hi> sayth, <hi rend="italic">Better it were to suffer some</hi>

<pb n="67"/>
<hi rend="italic">disorder in the estate, and some spots in the Common-wealth, then in pretending to
reforme, vtterly to ouerthrow the Republicke.</hi>
</p>
<p>The second obiection they ground vpon the curse that hangs ouer the common-
wealth, where a wicked king reigneth: and, say they, there cannot be a more
acceptable deed in the sight of God, nor more dutiful to their common-weale,
then to free the countrey of such a curse, and vindicate to them their libertie,
which is naturall to all creatures to craue.
</p>
<p>Whereunto for answere, I grant indeed, that a wicked king is sent by God for
a curse to his people, and a plague for their sinnes: but that it is lawfull to them
to shake off that curse at their owne hand, which God hath laid on them, that I
deny, and may so do iustly. Will any deny that the king of <hi rend="italic">Babel</hi> was a curse to
the people of God, as was plainly fore-spoken and threatned vnto them in the
prophecie of their captiutie ? And what was <hi rend="italic">Nero</hi> to the Christian Church in his
time ? And yet <hi rend="italic">Ieremy</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Paul</hi> (as yee haue else heard) commanded them not
onely to obey them, but heartily to pray for their welfare.
</p>
<p>It is certaine then (as I haue already by the Law of God sufficiently proued)
that patience, earnest prayers to God, and amendment of their liues, are the
onely lawful means to moue God to relieue them of that heauie curse. As for
vindicating to themselues their owne libertie, what lawfull power haue they to
reuoke to themselues againe those priuiledges, which by their owne consent before
were so fully put out of their hands ? for if a Prince cannot iustly bring backe
againe to himself the priuiledges once bestowed by him or his predecessors vpon
any state or ranke of his subiects; how much lesse may the subiects reaue out of
the princes hand that superioritie, which he and his Predecessors haue so long
brooked ouer them ?
</p>
<p>But the vnhappy iniquitie of the time, which hath oft times giuen ouer good
successe to their treasonable attempts, furnisheth them the ground of their third
obiection: For, say they, the fortunate successe that God hath so oft giuen to
such enterprises, prooueth plainely by the practise, that God fauoured the
iustnesse of their quarrell.
</p>
<p>To the which I answere, that it is trew indeed, that all the successe of battels,
as well as other wordly things, lyeth onely in Gods hand: And therefore it is that
in the Scripture he takes to himselfe the style of God of Hosts. But vpon that
generall to conclude, that hee euer giues victory to the iust quarrell, would prooue
the <hi rend="italic">Philistims</hi>, and diuers other neighbour enemies of the people of God to haue
oft times had the iust quarrel against the people of God, in respect of the many
victories they obtained against them. And by that same argument they had also
iust quarrell against the Arke of God: For they wan it in the field, and kept it
long prisoner in their countrey. As likewise by all good Writers, as well Theo-
logues, as other, the Duels and singular combats are disallowed; which are onely
made vpon pretence, that GOD will kith thereby the iustice of the quarrell: For
wee must consider that the innocent partie is not innocent before God: And

<pb n="68"/>
  therefore God will make oft times them that haue the wrong side reuenge iustly
  his quarrell; and when he hath done, cast his scourge in the fire; as he oft times
  did to his owne people, stirring vp and strengthening their enemies, while they
  were humbled in his sight, and then deliuered them in their hands. So God, as
  the great Iudge may iustly punish his Deputie, and for his rebellion against him
  stir vp his rebels to meet him with the like: And when it is done, the part of the
  instrument is no better then the diuels part is in tempting and torturing such as
  God committeth to him as his hangman to doe: Therefore, as I said in the begin-
  ning, it is oft times a very deceiueable argument, to iudge of the cause by the euent.
</p>
<p>And the last obiection is grounded vpon the mutuall paction and adstipulation
  (as they call it) betwixt the King and his people, at the time of his coronation:
  For there, say they, there is a mutuall paction, and contract bound vp, and
  sworne betwixt the king, and the people: Whereupon it followeth, that if the one
  part of the contract or the Indent bee broken vpon the Kings side, the people are
  no longer bound to keep their part of it, but are thereby freed of their oath: For
  (say they) a contract betwixt two parties, of all Law frees the one partie, if the
  other breake vnto him.
</p>
<p>As to this contract alledged made at the coronation of a King, although I deny
 any such contract to bee made then, especially containing such a clause irritant
 as they alledge; yet I confesse, that a king at his coronation, or at the entry to his
 kingdome, willingly promiseth to his people, to discharge honorably and trewly
 the office giuen him by God ouer them: But presuming that thereafter he breaks
 his promise vnto them neuer so inexcusable; the question is, who should bee
 iudge of the breake, giuing vnto them, this contract were made vnto them neuer
 so sicker, according to their alleageance. I thinke no man that hath but the
 smallest entrance into the ciuill Law, will doubt that of all Law, either ciuil or
 municipal of any nation, a contract cannot be thought broken by the one partie,
 and so the other likewise to be freed therefro, except that first a lawfull triall and
 cognition be had by the ordinary Iudge of the breakers thereof: Or else euery
 man may be both party and Iudge in his owne cause; which is absurd once to be
 thought. Now in this contract (I say) betwixt the king and his people, God is
 doubtles the only Iudge, both because to him onely the king must make count of
 his administration (as is oft said before) as likewise by the oath in the coronation,
 God is made iudge and reuenger of the breakers: For in his presence, as only
 iudge of oaths, all oaths ought to be made. Then since God is the onely Iudge
 betwixt the two parties contractors, the cognition and reuenge must onely apper-
 taine to him: It followes therefore of necessitie, that God must first giue sentence
 vpon the King that breaketh, before the people can thinke themselues freed of
 their oath. What iustice then is it, that the partie shall be both iudge and partie,
 vsurping vpon himselfe the office of God, may by this argument easily appeare:
 And shall it lie in the hands of headlesse multitude, when they please to weary off
subiection, to cast off the yoake of gouernement that God hath laid vpon them, to

<pb n="69"/>
  iudge and punish him, whom-by they should be iudged and punished, and in that
  case, wherein by their violence they kythe themselues to be most passionate
  parties, to vse the office of an vngracious Iudge or Arbiter ? Nay, to speak
  trewly of that case, as it stands betwixt the king and his people, none of them
  ought to iudge of the others break: For considering rightly the two parties at the
  time of their mutuall promise, the king is the one party, and the whole people in
  one body are the other party. And therfore since it is certaine, that a king, in
  case so it should fal out, that his people in one body had rebelled against him, hee
  should not in that case, as thinking himselfe free of his promise and oath, become
  an vtter enemy, and practise the wreake of his whole people and natiue country:
  although he ought iustly to punish the principall authours and bellowes of that
  vniuersall rebellion: how much lesse then ought the people (that are alwaies
  subiect vnto him, and naked of all authoritie on their part) presse to iudge and
  ouer-throw him ? otherwise the people, as the one partie contracters, shall no
  sooner challenge the king as breaker, but hee assoone shall iudge them as breakers:
  so as the victors making the tyners the traitors (as our prouerbe is) the partie
  shall aye become both iudge and partie in his owne particular, as I haue alreadie
  said.
</p>
<p>And it is here likewise to be noted, that the duty and alleageance, which the
 people sweareth to their prince, is not only bound to themselues, but likewise to
 their lawfull heires and posterity, the lineall succession of crowns being begun
 among the people of God, and happily continued in diuers christian common-
 wealths: So as no obiection either of heresie, or whatsoeuer priuate statute or
 law may free the people from their oath-giuing to their king, and his succession,
 established by the old fundamentall lawes of the kingdome: For, as hee is their
 heritable ouer-lord, and so by birth, not by any right in the coronation, commeth
 to his crowne; it is a like vnlawful (the crowne euer standing full) to displace
 him that succeedeth thereto, as to eiect the former: For at the very moment of
 the expiring of the king reigning, the nearest and lawful heire entreth in his place:
 And so to refuse him, or intrude another, is not to holde out vncomming in, but to
 expell and put out their righteous King. And I trust at this time whole <hi rend="italic">France</hi>
 acknowledgeth the superstitious rebellion of the liguers, who vpon pretence of
 heresie, by force of armes held so long out, to the great desolation of their whole
 countrey, their natiue and righteous king from possessing of his owne crowne and
 naturall kingdome.
</p>
<p>Not that by all this former discourse of mine, and Apologie for kings, I meane
that whatsoeuer errors and intollerable abominations a souereigne prince commit,
hee ought to escape all punishment, as if thereby the world were only ordained for
kings, &amp; they without controlment to turne it vpside down at their pleasure: but
by the contrary, by remitting them to God (who is their onely ordinary Iudge)
I remit them to the sorest and sharpest schoolemaster that can be deuised for
them: for the further a king is preferred by God aboue all other ranks &amp; degrees

<pb n="70"/>
of men, and the higher that his seat is aboue theirs, the greater is his obligation
to his maker. And therfore in case he forget himselfe (his vnthankfulnes being
in the same measure of height) the sadder and sharper will his correction be; and
according to the greatnes of the height he is in, the weight of his fall wil recompense
the same: for the further that any person is obliged to God, his offence becomes
and growes so much the greater, then it would be in any other. <hi rend="italic">Ioues</hi> thunder-
claps light oftner and sorer vpon the high &amp; stately oakes, then on the low and
supple willow trees: and the highest bench is sliddriest to sit vpon. Neither is it
euer heard that any king forgets himselfe towards God, or in his vocation; but
God with the greatnesse of the plague reuengeth the greatnes of his ingratitude:
Neither thinke I by the force and argument of this my discourse so to perswade
the people, that none will hereafter be raised vp, and rebell against wicked Princes.
But remitting to the iustice and prouidence of God to stirre vp such scourges as
pleaseth him, for punishment of wicked kings (who made the very vermine and
filthy dust of the earth to bridle the insolencie of proud <hi rend="italic">Pharaoh</hi>) my onely pur-
pose and intention in this treatise is to perswade, as farre as lieth in me, by these
sure and infallible grounds, all such good Christian readers, as beare not onely
the naked name of a Christian, but kith the fruites thereof in their daily forme of
life, to keep their hearts and hands free from such monstrous and vnnaturall
rebellions, whensoeuer the wickednesse of a Prince shall procure the same at Gods
hands: that, when it shall please God to cast such scourges of princes, and in-
struments of his fury in the fire, ye may stand vp with cleane handes, and vn-
spotted consciences, hauing prooued your selues in all your actions trew Chris-
tians toward God, and dutifull subiects towards your King, hauing remitted the
judgement and punishment of all his wrongs to him, whom to onely of right it
appertaineth.
</p>
<p>But crauing at God, and hoping that God shall continue his blessing with vs,
in not sending such fearefull desolation, I heartily wish our kings behauiour so to
be, and continue among vs, as our God in earth, and louing Father, endued with
such properties as I described a King in the first part of this Treatise. And that
ye (my deare countreymen, and charitable readers) may presse by all means to
procure the prosperitie and welfare of your King; that as hee must on the one
part thinke all his earthly felicitie and happinesse grounded vpon your weale,
caring more for himselfe for your sake then for his owne, thinking himselfe onely
ordained for your weale; such holy and happy emulation may arise betwixt him
and you, as his care for your quietnes, and your care for his honour and preserua-
tion, may in all your actions daily striue together, that the Land may thinke
themselues blessed with such a King, and the king may thinke himselfe most
happy in ruling ouer so louing and obedient subiects.

                                                      FINIS.

<pb n="71"/>
</p>

    
   </div>
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
