<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng"	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Garden of Eloquence (1593): Tropes</title>
                <author>Henry Peacham.</author>

            </titleStmt>
            <extent/>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>later</p>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <title>The Garden of Eloquence (1593)</title>
                        <author>Henry Peacham</author>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Delmar, New York 12054</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Scholars' Facsimiles &amp; Reprints, Inc.</publisher>
                            <date>1977</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>

                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>
            
            <refsDecl n="CTS">
                <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+).(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2']/tei:div[@n='$3'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts act and scene and line.</p>
                </cRefPattern>
                <cRefPattern n="chapter" matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts book and chapter.</p>
                </cRefPattern>
                <cRefPattern n="book" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts book.</p>
                </cRefPattern>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
                <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
                <language ident="deu">German</language>
                <language ident="fra">French</language>
                <language ident="ita">Italian</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>

        <revisionDesc><change><ab>converted to EpiDoc</ab></change></revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <front>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">

                <ab type="opener">TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE SIR JOHN Puckering Knight, Lord keeper of the great
                    seale of England.</ab>

                <p>Albeit (Right Honorable) it may seeme to some men at the first sight, a matter
                    importunate to interrupt your Lordships grave, deep, and weightie
                    considerations, sitting as you do at the sterne of the commonwelth in these
                    daies of danger, yet seeing the infimitie of our mortall estate cannot possiblie
                    indure to stand continually bent, no, not in the contemplation of the most
                    excellent subject, or matter of greatest importance, May it therefore please
                    your good Lordship (if for no other cause yet) partly for your owne ease,
                    release, and recreation, and partly for patronage to poore and painfull
                    studentes, to lend your honorable view to those my simple labours, hoping that
                    as you are not wont either to close your eies, or stop your eares to the meanest
                    or the poorest, so your Lordship wil not refuse to spare some time (when your
                    leasure may best permit) to cast your eie uppon these meane and simple frutes of
                    my studies: The argument whereof albeit I confesse it subject to the exceptions
                    of many, and peradventure to the reprehensions of some, which seeme to make a
                    divorce betweene nature and art, and a seperation betweene pollicie and
                    humanitie: yet Cicero being both a most excellent Orator and prudent politick,
                    doth mightily support, and defend it against all objections, as we may plainly
                    see in one short sentence of his (among many other tending to this purpose)
                    where he saith: Ut hominis decus est ingenium, sic ingenii lumen, est
                    eloquentia: <note place="marg" anchored="false">De claris oratoribum.</note> that
                    is, as wit is mans worship, or wisedome man honor, so eloquence is the light and
                    brightnesse of wisedome, in which sentence, he both expresseth the singular
                    praises of two most worthie vertues, and also enforceth the necessitie, and
                    commendeth the utilitie of their excellent conjunction. And true it is that if
                    we joine with this prudent Orator in a diligent inquisition and contemplation of
                    wisedome, and in a deliberate consideration of art, we shal see that verified
                    which he hath here affirmed. For if we enquire what wisedome is, we shall find
                    that it is the knowledge of divine and humane thinges, if whose gift it is, we
                    shall find that it is the knowledge of divine and humane thinges, if whose gift
                    it is, we shalbe certified, that it is the gift of God, if we consider the
                    inventions thereof they are woonderfull, if the works they are infinit, if the
                    frutes, they are in use sweete, in nature necessarie, both for the search of
                    truth and for the direction of humane life. Brieflie this vertue is the loving
                    &amp; provident mother of mankind, whom shee nourisheth with the sweete milke of
                    prosperitie, defendeth against manifolde dangers, instructeth with her counsell,
                    and prefereth to the imperiall dominion over all earthly creatures: and lest
                    dissenting with himselfe, he should by his owne contention worke his owne
                    confusion: she deviseth lawes to support equitie, and appointeth punishments to
                    represse injurie, she inventeth the art and skill of warre, to resist violence
                    offending against peace, she maintaineth the one, and directeth the other, and
                    is the mightie Empresse of them both.</p>

                <p>Finallie, by her the true felicitie of man is found out and held up, without her
                    it falleth by a sudden, and wofull ruine: by her it falleth by a sudden, and
                    wofull ruine: by her his honor is highly advaunced, without her it sinketh into
                    shame and reproach, and is utterlie confounded: by her hee is indued with a
                    blessed state of life, without her he perisheth in miserie and death. Now lest
                    so excellent a gift of the divine goodnesse (as wisedome here appeareth to be,
                    and is) should lye supprest by silence, and so remaine hid in darkenesse,
                    almightie God the deep sea of wisedome, and bright sunne of majestie, hath
                    opened the mouth of man, as the mouth of a plentifull fountaine, both to powre
                    forth the inward pasions of his heart, and also as a heavenly planet to shew
                    foorth, by the shining beames of speech) the privie thoughts and secret
                    conceites of his mind. By the benefit of this excellent gift, (I meane of apt
                    speech given by nature, and guided by Art) wisedome appeareth in her beautie,
                    sheweth her majestie, and exerciseth her power, working in the minde of the
                    hearer, partly by a pleasant proportion, &amp; as it were by a sweet &amp;
                    musicall harmonie, and partly by the secret and mightie power of perswasion
                    after a most wonderfull manner. This then is the vertue which the Orator in his
                    praise before mentioned calleth eloquence, &amp; the brightnesse of wisedome,
                    for that by the mean hereof, as well the rare inventions &amp; pleasant devises,
                    as the deepe understanding, the secret counselles, &amp; politick considerations
                    of wisedome, are most effectually expressed, and most comely beautified, for
                    even as by the power of the Sun beames, the nature of the roote is shewed in the
                    blossome, &amp; the goodnesse of the sap tasted in the sweetnesse of the frute,
                    even so the precious nature, and wonderfull power of wisedome, is by the
                    commendable ARt and use of eloquence, produced and brought into open light. So
                    that hereby plainlie appeareth, both the great necessitie &amp; singular
                    utilitie of their conjunction before commended, for the one without the other,
                    do finde both great want, and shew great imperfection, for to possesse great
                    knowledge without apt utterance, is, as to possesse great treasure without use:
                    contrariwise to affect eloquence without the discretion of wisdom, is, as to
                    handle a sweete instrument of musicke without skill. But the man which is well
                    furnished with both: I meane with ample knowledge and excellent speech, hath
                    bene judged able, and esteemed fit to rule the world with counsell, provinces
                    with lawes, cities with pollicy, &amp; multitudes with persuasion: such were
                    those men in times past, who by their singular wisdom and eloquence, made savage
                    nations civil, wild people tame, and cruell tyrants not only to become meeke,
                    but likewise mercifull. Hence it was, that in ancient time men did attribute so
                    great opinion of wisedome to the eloquent Orators of those daies, that they
                    called them sacred, holy, divine, &amp; the interpreters of the goddes, for so
                    doth Horace commending Orpheus, his words be these.</p>

                <quote rend="block">
                    <lg xml:lang="la">
                        <l>Agrestes homines sacer interpresque Deorum.</l>
                        <l>Caecibus, &amp; faedo victu deterruit Orpheus.</l>
                        <l>Dictus ob id, lenire tigres rigidosque leones.</l>
                    </lg></quote>

                <p>The Poet here under the name of tigres and lions, meant not beasts but men, &amp;
                    such men as by their savage nature &amp; cruell manners, might well be compared
                    to fierce tigres and devouring lions, which notwithstanding by the mightie power
                    of wisdome, and prudent art of perswasion were converted from that most brutish
                    condition of life, to the love of humanitie, &amp; polliticke government, so
                    might is the power of this happie union. (I meane of wisdom &amp; eloquence)
                    that by the one the Orator forceth, and by the other he allureth, and by both so
                    worketh, that what he commendeth is beloved, what he dispraiseth is abhorred,
                    what he perswadeth is obeied, &amp; what he disswadeth is avoided: so that he is
                    in a maner the emperour of mens minds &amp; affections, and next to the
                    omnipotent God in the power of perswasion, by grace, &amp; divine assistance.
                    The principal instruments of mans help in this wonderfull effect, are those
                    figures and formes of speech conteined in this booke, which are the frutefull
                    branches of eloquution, and the mightie streames of eloquence: whose utilitie,
                    power, and vertue, I cannot sufficiently commend, but speaking by similitude, I
                    say they are as stars to give light, as cordials to comfort, as harmony to
                    delight, as pitiful spectacles to move sorrow full passions, and as orient
                    colours to beautifie reason. Finally they are as martiall instruments both of
                    defence &amp; invasion, and being so, what may be either more necessary, or more
                    profitable for us, then to hold those weapons alwaies readie in our handes,
                    wherewith we may defend our selves, invade our enemies, revenge our wrongs, ayd
                    the weake, deliver the simple from danges, conserve true religion, &amp; confute
                    idolatry? for looke what the sword may do in war, for that with violence, this
                    with perswasion, that with shedding of blood, this with pearcing the sffections,
                    that with desire of death, this with speciall regard of life.</p>

                <p>Now, lest this part should seeme an emptie art of wordes, without wisedome or
                    substance of matter, I have gathered out of the most excellent Orators, &amp;
                    best approved authors, varietie of fit examples for everie figure by it selfe:
                    which figures or formes of speech, I have disposed into orders, described by
                    their properties, distinguished by their differences, noted their singular uses,
                    &amp; added certain Cautions to compasse them for feare of abuse. And now Right
                    Honourable, having finished this little booke (alhtough with no little labor) I
                    hope to the good of many, and hurt of none, with sincere affection, &amp; with
                    most humble dutie, I present it to your good Lordship, as to a lover &amp;
                    favourer of learning, in hope of your favourable acceptation, being mooved
                    hereunto by long experience of your lordships excellent wisdome, &amp; constant
                    goodnes, ready at al time to lend your helping hand (in good causes) to them
                    which by necessitie &amp; distresse, stood in need therof, among which, I am one
                    that have tasted of your goodnes &amp; comfort: the remembrance wherof, hath bin
                    one principall motive, of taking this labor in hand, to the end that I among the
                    rest which love and honour your Lordship, might have somewhat to signifie my
                    gratitude and bound dutie: beseeching your Honor, albeit this worke be such as
                    your Lordship shall litle need, being so richly furnished by nature, yet for
                    their sakes who may take benefit by it, you will please to shadow and protect it
                    under the wings of your honourable favour. That I may not trouble your Lordship
                    any further, I commend your Honour with my hartie praiers, to the mercifull
                    protection of the Almightie, beseeching him, that by his grace and mercy you may
                    long continue, to her most excellent Majestie a most faithfull and prudent
                    Counsellour, to the oppressed a reliefe, to innocents a sure protection, to your
                    country a treasure, to your friends a sure protection, to your country a
                    treasure, to your friends a comfort, to godlie and painfull students a gracious
                    Mecaenas, and to the posteritie of many ages, a renowmed president of
                    equitie.</p>
                <note type="closer">
                    <ab type="dateline">At North Mymmes the 3. of February. 1593.</ab>
                    <ab type="salute">Your Honors most humble to be commanded,</ab>
                    <ab type="signed">Henry Peacham.</ab>
                </note>
            </div>
        </front>

        <body> <head>The Garden of Eloquence</head>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="part" n="1">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="subpart" n="1"> <head>The Names of figures.</head>

                    <p>Figure of the Grecians are called Tropes and Schemates, and of the Latines,
                        figures, exornations, lights, colours and ornaments. Cicero who supposing
                        them to be named of the Grecians <term>Schemates</term>, as gestures and
                        countenances of speech, called them <term>Concinnitie</term> that is,
                        proprietie, aptnesse, comlinesse, formes and conformations, comprissing all
                        ornaments under one name.</p>
                </div>

                <div type="textpart" subtype="subpart" n="2"> <head>A Figure what it is.</head>

                    <p>A Figure is a forme of words, oration, or sentence, made new by art,
                        differing from the vulgar maner and custome of writing or speaking.</p>
                </div>

                <div type="textpart" subtype="subpart" n="3"> <head>A Figure how it is devided.</head>

                    <p>A figure is either A <term>Trope</term> or A <term>Schemate</term>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <!-- of part "Figures" -->

            <div type="textpart" subtype="part" n="2"> <!-- Tropes -->
                <div type="textpart" subtype="subpart" n="1"> <head>A <term>Trope</term> what it is.</head>

                    <p>A <term>Trope</term> is an artificall alteration of a word, or a sentence,
                        from the proper and natural signification to another not proper, but yet
                        nigh, and likely.</p>
                </div>

                <div type="textpart" subtype="subpart" n="2"> <head>The beginning, and causes of <term>Tropes</term>.</head>

                    <p>The causes of <term>Tropes</term> are three, neccessitie will and arte, &amp;
                        of these three necessity was the first, for where there wanted words <note place="marg" anchored="false">1. Necessity.</note> to expresse the nature
                        and propertie of diverse things, men were urged and constrained to seeke
                        remedie for the supply of so great a want, whereupon wise men calling to
                        remembrance that many things were verie like one to another in some respect
                        of nature though it good to borow ye name of one thing, to signifie another,
                        which did in some part or property of nature resemble it, &amp; thus began
                        they to use translated speech: declaring their meaning by similitudes and
                        compared significations. Ant then, seeing that by this meanes matter were
                        well expressed, their meanings more largely uttered, and their invention
                        well commended, men in their private speech, and Orators <note place="marg" anchored="false">2. Will</note> in their publike orations, refused such
                        words as were proper, and had litle sweetnesse, or could not declare the
                        nature of the thing so well, and used other wordes borrowed from like
                        things, both for the grace sake of the similitude, and also for the cause of
                        perspicuitie of the thing expressed.</p>

                    <p>Since upon good liking, and confirmed judgement, the wisdome of man hath
                        invented and found out an Art, not onely teaching where apt translations may
                        be found, but also giving excellent rules and certaine directions, how they
                        should be most aptly and properly applyed.</p>

                    <p>The places from whence translations may be taken, are infinite, not
                        withstanding there be certaine that be verie usuall, readie, apt and
                        pleasant, which I purpose hereafter to observe and note, as the most
                        plentifull fields, yeeldinrg such proffitable and pleasant flowers.</p>

                    <p>This excellent Art of translating, among other profitable rules commendeth to
                        us this necessarie observation to begin with, that is to say, that those
                        things ought to be equal in proportion, which we purpose to compare by
                        translation, that is, of foure things two ought always to be compared to
                        two, as for example, we say the flower of age, here in this translation the
                        herbe and the flower is compared to man and his youth, for the same that the
                        flower is in the herbe, the same is youth in man. By the same proportion the
                        Poet saith, unhappy Dido enflamed is, in this example Dido and her love is
                        compared to the wood and the fire.</p>

                    <p>This rule is alwayes most diligently observed of wise and learned men, whose
                        words and works are by this singular forme of speech both pleasantly
                        beautified, and brightly adorned. The special commendation of translated
                        speech I will referre it to the proper use of everie singular
                            <term>Trope</term>.</p>
                </div>

                <div type="textpart" subtype="subpart" n="3"> <head>The division of <term>Tropes</term>.</head>

                    <p>Tropes are either of Words or Sentences.</p>
                </div>

                <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="4"> <head>Tropes of words are these.</head>

                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item n="1"><term>Metaphora.</term></item>
                        <item n="2"><term>Onomatopoeia.</term></item>
                        <item n="3"><term>Catachresis.</term></item>
                        <item n="4"><term>Synecdoche.</term></item>
                        <item n="5"><term>Metonymia.</term></item>
                        <item n="6"><term>Antonomasia.</term></item>
                        <item n="7"><term>Metalepsis.</term></item>
                        <item n="8"><term>Antiphrasis.</term></item>
                    </list>



                    <div type="textpart" subtype="subpart" n="1"> <head>Metaphora</head>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="1">
                            <p><term>Metaphora</term> is artifical translation of one word, from the
                                proper signification, to another not proper, but yet nigh and
                                like.</p>
                        </div>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="2"> <head>The efficient cause of a <term>Metaphore</term>.</head>

                            <p>It is apparant that memorie is the principall efficient of a
                                    <term>Metaphore</term>, for being the retentive power of the
                                mind, it is the treasure house of mans knowledge, which as it
                                possesseth the formes of knowen things, so is it readie at all times
                                to present them to mans use, as often as occasion, and cuase doth
                                necessarily require. As for example, he that hath seene a
                                caterpiller eating and devouring the tender buds and blossomes of
                                trees and plants, and ater this shall see an idle person living by
                                the spoyle of other mens labours, is put in mind to call him a
                                caterpiller: he that hath seene a gulph or gaping sinke, swallowing
                                a continuall streame or mightie quantitie of water and afterward
                                shall see a man consuming his substance and patrimonie in
                                prodigalitie and riot, is put in mind to call him a gulph of
                                patrimonie or a fluke of wealth.</p>


                            <p>It is to be confessed notwithstanding, that memorie worketh not all
                                alone in the framing of translations but hath erant judgements
                                alwayes to helpe her, for memorie presenteth the former part of the
                                comparison, and judgement applieth the later, for a man may castly
                                remember what he hath soene, but yet if he want discreete judgement,
                                he cannot aptly compare to it the thing that he now seeth although
                                there be some fit similitude betweene them, and also some
                                neccessarie occasion to use it: and therefore ample knowledge,
                                perfect memorie, and exact judgement joyning together in one mind,
                                are the principall and especiall causes of all apt and excellent
                                translations.</p>

                            <p>The places from whence translations may be taken are infinite, yet of
                                the infinite, yet of that infinite number certaine are chosen out,
                                as most apt, most usual, &amp; most commendable, which are these
                                following.</p>

                            <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="1"> <head>From man him selfe, and first from his senses.</head>
                                <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="1"> <head>1. From the sight.</head>

                                    <p>As the sight among the rest of the senses is most sharpe, and
                                        pierceth furthest, so is it proved most sure, and least
                                        deceived, and therefore is very nigh to the mind in the
                                        affinitie of nature, so farre foorth as an externall sense
                                        of the bodie may be compared to an internall vertue of the
                                        mind. The consideration hereof causeth men to use the words
                                        which are proper to this sense and that very often, as fit
                                        to signifie many vertues of the mind, as the understanding,
                                        knowledge, providence, carfulnesse, hope, opinion, judgement
                                        and such like. Hence it is that a man may say, I see your
                                        meaning, I see your malice, here the translation is from the
                                        sight to the mind: for to speakes properly we can not say,
                                        we see mens meanings, or mens malice, which are invisible in
                                        respect of our bodily sight. But yet in respect of our minds
                                        we may perciue, and understand them, as by some probable
                                        conjectures, or likely tokens collected by reason and
                                        judgement. An example of the holy Scripture, <cit>
                                            <quote>when the Queene of Saba had seene the wisedome of
                                                Salomon</quote>
                                            <bibl> 2.Chron 9.</bibl>
                                        </cit>: now to speake properly she proued &amp; understood
                                        the wisedome of Salomon, but see it she could not. Another <cit>
                                            <quote>The king that looketh well about him driveth away
                                                all evil</quote>
                                            <bibl>Prov.2</bibl>
                                        </cit>: here the word, looketh well about is the
                                        translation, and signifieth the regard and carefull
                                        gouernement of his kingdome. Another. <cit>
                                            <quote>You looked for much, and lo it is come to litle </quote>
                                            <bibl>Agge 1.</bibl>
                                        </cit>: here to looke for, signifieth to hope for. </p>
                                    <p><cit>
                                            <quote>In the sight of the unwise they appeare to
                                                die,</quote>
                                            <bibl>Sap.4</bibl>
                                        </cit> that is, in the opinion or judgement of the unwise. </p>
                                    <p><cit>
                                            <quote>He that putteth his hand to the plough and
                                                looketh backe, is unweete for the kingdom of
                                                God</quote>
                                            <bibl>Luke 9.</bibl>
                                        </cit>: by looking back is meant unconstancie or wavering of
                                        mind. </p>
                                    <p>In like maner by this place we may signifie, by looking up,
                                        heauenly meditation, for so both our Saviour Christ use it,
                                        where he saith, <cit>
                                            <quote>then looke up, for your redemption draweth
                                                nigh.</quote>
                                            <bibl>Luke 21</bibl>
                                        </cit> Also by high lookes is very often signified pride and
                                        disdaine, by winking partialitie, by circumspection wisdom
                                        and providence, by looking away displeasure, by looking
                                        downe discomfort, and sometime view and suvay, by looking
                                        upon due and deliberate consideration. Now as the sense of
                                        sight both aptly expresse many vertues of the mind, so the
                                        privation hereof, which we call blindnesse, may be fitly
                                        used to signifie the contraries, as for example, <cit>
                                            <quote>Gifts blind the wise</quote>
                                            <bibl>Deut.16</bibl>
                                        </cit>, that is, gifts obscureth the understanding, and
                                        seduceth the will of wise men: blind are they are the guides
                                        of the blind, that is, altogether ignorant and destitute of
                                        knowledge. </p>
                                </div>

                                <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="2"> <head>From the hearing.</head>

                                    <p>From the hearing are diverse translations taken, not so much
                                        serving to signifie the powers of the mind, as to expresse
                                        the affections of the heart. An example. Heare the complaint
                                        of the fatherlesse and window, that is, do them justice,
                                        pitie them, and tender their distressed estate. </p>
                                    <p><cit>
                                            <quote>He that is scornfull will not heare when he is
                                                reproved,</quote>
                                            <bibl>Prov.13</bibl>
                                        </cit> in this translation refusing to heare signifieth
                                        disdaine of correction, and hatred of doctrine. </p>
                                    <p><cit>
                                            <quote>Heare no counsell against innocent blood,</quote>
                                            <bibl>Esa.33</bibl>
                                        </cit> that is, consent not to that counsell which induceth
                                        to shed the blood of innocent persons. </p>
                                    <p>My sonne heare thy fathers doctrine, that is, obey it. </p>
                                    <p><cit>
                                            <quote>Heare the small as well as the great,</quote>
                                            <bibl>Deut.7</bibl>
                                        </cit> the word heare in this place signifieth the action
                                        and execution equitie. </p>
                                    <p>Talke thou with us and we wil heare, that is, we will attend
                                        and imbrace thy doctrine. </p>
                                    <p><cit>
                                            <quote>The noise of horses is heard from Dan,</quote>
                                            <bibl>Ier.8</bibl>
                                        </cit> that is, foreseene by the the Prophet. </p>
                                    <p><cit>
                                            <quote>Concerning Ismael I haue heard thee,</quote>
                                            <bibl>Gen 17.20</bibl>
                                        </cit> signifying by hearing, a graunting to abrams
                                        petition. Thus from this sense as you see translations be
                                        taken to signifie pitie, compassion, ayd, succour, consent,
                                        obedience, equitie, attention, foresight, and granting. And
                                        by the privation of this sense many things contrary to these
                                        former significations may be expressed, They are deaffe and
                                        can not heare, signifying that they are unapt to accept
                                        doctrine. Againe, They will not heare, that is, they are
                                        obstinate, and hardened against all good counsell. </p>
                                </div>

                                <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="3"> <head>From the smelling.</head>

                                    <p>From smelling these translations and such like may be taken.
                                        Being wise &amp; provident, by his singular foresight did
                                        timely smell out the ungratious practices, and private
                                        conspiracies of the enemies bent against the citie and
                                        common wealth. Here by smelling out, is signified knowledge
                                        gathered by prudent suspition, and wittie conjectures. An
                                        example of the holy Scripture, <cit>
                                            <quote>A sacrifice of a sweet favour,</quote>
                                            <bibl>Ephes.5.2.</bibl>
                                        </cit> that is, a sacrifice acceptable to God. </p>
                                    <p>The things which do please this sense, are sweete favours,
                                        and pleasant odors, and therfore the use of this sense in
                                        translation is commonly used to signifie the pleasure of the
                                        mind, as the contraries are used to expresse the hatred and
                                        offence of mans heart, as when it is said, that abominations
                                        of sinne do stinke and are odious to God and all good men. </p>
                                    <p>As also the property of smelling findeth oftentimes the
                                        effect before the eye can discerne the cause: so providence
                                        and foresight, which this sense doth most aptly signifie in
                                        translation, do manie times espie and prevent secret
                                        practices and privie conspiracies before they take effect.
                                    </p>
                                </div>

                                <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="4"> <head>From feeling or touching.</head>

                                    <p><note place="marg" anchored="false">Job.1.</note> From this
                                        sense are sundrie Metaphors taken. An example of the holy
                                        Scripture, Stretch out thy hand new, and touch him selfe and
                                        his flesh: here to touch doth signifie another thing than it
                                        doth in the proper signification, for Sathan by touching
                                        understandeth a piercing, and plaguing of Jobs bodie with
                                        grievous and lothsome diseases. In the same signification
                                        Job afterwards useth the same word, saying, the hand of God
                                        hath touched me, that is, hath grievously smitten and
                                        wounded me. </p>
                                    <p>Another example, <cit>
                                            <quote>And they were pricked in thier hearts,</quote>
                                            <bibl>Act.2</bibl>
                                        </cit> meaning, pierced with sorrow and repentance. </p>
                                    <p>Art thous so senslesse, that thou neither feeleth hurt by thy
                                        foe, nor benefit by thy friend? Here by feeling is signified
                                        understanding, and by the want of feeling is understood the
                                        stonishment of mind or lacke of wit. Briefly by this place
                                        these translations are used, by touching is understood
                                        provoking, by feeling understanding, by nipping taunting or
                                        privie mocking, by wounding confusion, by pricking remorse
                                        of conscience, by renting extreame griefe, by somoothnesse
                                        faire speech or flatterie, by coldnesse want of affection,
                                        by heat vehement displeasure or fervent zeale, by driness
                                        defect, by embracing love or possession of pleasure. </p>
                                </div>

                                <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="5"> <head>From the tasting.</head>

                                    <p>From this sense and his subjects, these kinds of translations
                                        are taken. Cicero to Atticus: you may tast that man, that
                                        is, you may trye &amp; prove him. Man is borne to tast as
                                        wel the sower as the sweete, that is, as well to suffer
                                        adversitie as to enjoy prosperitie. </p>

                                    <p>Moreover by this place we may by sweetnesse signifie
                                        pleasure, by bitternesse griefe of mind, or crueltie of
                                        speech, and by sowernesse severitie. </p>
                                    <p>Examples of the sacred Scripture, <cit>
                                            <quote>Tast and see how gracious the Lord is.</quote>
                                            <bibl>Psal.54</bibl>
                                        </cit> Another: <cit>
                                            <quote>There are certaine of them which stand here, that
                                                shall not tast of death till they see the kingdom of
                                                God.</quote>
                                            <bibl>Luke 9.27</bibl>
                                        </cit> Another: <cit>
                                            <quote>And having once tasted of the heavenly
                                                gifts,</quote>
                                            <bibl>Heb.6.5.</bibl>
                                        </cit> in these examples tasting is put Metaphorically,
                                        &amp; signifieth experience, but yet in sundry respects. </p>



                                    <p>Hitherto I have noted those places which do serve from the
                                        bodie to the mind: and now next I will observe those
                                        translations that are taken from the mind and applyed to the
                                        bodie. </p>
                                </div>
                            </div>

                            <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="2"> <head>From the mind to the bodie.</head>

                                <p>From things in the minde to the parts of the bodie, as to call a
                                    wound angrie, or wofull: a tongue malicious, and also when we
                                    say, a pitifull eye, a liberall hand, a wise eare. Now these
                                    words angrie, wofull, malicious, pitifull, and wise, do belong
                                    properly to the mind, yet by this forme of speaking, they
                                    signifie passions and properties of the bodie.</p>

                                <p>An example of holy Scripture, <cit>
                                        <quote>whatsoever mine eyes desired I let them have
                                            it.</quote>
                                        <bibl>Eccles.2.</bibl>
                                    </cit> Here Salomon attributeth desire to the eyes, which is a
                                    word properly belonging to the mind and not to the eyes, which
                                    are parts of the body.</p>

                                <p>Also in like sense he saith, <cit>
                                        <quote>The eye is not satisfied with light, nor the eare
                                            with hearing</quote>
                                        <bibl>Eccles.1.</bibl>
                                    </cit>: by the eye and eare he understandeth the desire of the
                                    mind kindled by those senses.</p>

                            </div>

                            <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="3"> <head>From living creatures without reason, to man partaker of
                                    reason.</head>

                                <p>From the creatures without reason <term>Metaphors</term> are
                                    taken, and applied to men, by which forme of speech mens
                                    qualities &amp; conditions are described by the properties of
                                    dumbe beasts: by this place, a tyrant is called a lyon, an
                                    extortioner a wolfe, a man without mercie a tigre, he that is
                                    deceitfull and subtle a foxe, and shamelesse rayler a barking
                                    dogge. In praise, the innocent is called a dove, the meeke and
                                    patient man a lambe, the faithfull in love and wedlocke a
                                    turtle. The particular properties of the dumbe creatures are
                                    very significent, especially in their Verbes and Verbals, for by
                                    whining we signifie murmuration &amp; grudging, by stinging
                                    secret mischief, by crowing proud and arrogant insulting, by
                                    swimming possession of abundance, or fruition of great
                                    felicitie, by roaring impatient miserie, by hissing terrible
                                    threatening, or bitter cursing, by hovering attending
                                    oportunitie, by devouring consumption, and by fawning
                                    flatterie.</p>
                            </div>

                            <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="4"> <head>From man to the brute creature.</head>

                                <p>From the reasonable to the unreasonable the usuall translations
                                    are these and such like, as to say, the mourning dove, the
                                    musicall mightingale, the proud peacocke, the flattering dogge.
                                    By the same forme of speech we may call the emmet provident, the
                                    cat circumspect, the spider diligent, the toade mistrustfull,
                                    the raven wise, the serpent subtle. These particular
                                    translations serve to shew how neare these creatures do come to
                                    man in these rehearsed properties. </p>
                            </div>

                            <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="5"> <head>From the living to things without life.</head>

                                <p>This part of translation is also very apt and significant, by
                                    this place the sea is sayd to swallow, the wind or tempests to
                                    rage, the frost to bite, the ground to thirst, field and flowers
                                    to rejoyce. Also we say, that waters do roare. Also in maner, as
                                    if I should say, Doest thou not know that fortune is fleeting?
                                    that avarice is insatiable, that love is blind, that envie
                                    stingeth where she is fostered, that malice thirsteth after
                                    blood? </p>
                                <p>This place is very copious both to Poets and Orators, &amp; also
                                    to private speech. this place for the most part is the fountaine
                                    of the figure called <term>Prosopocia</term> hence it is that
                                    Poets and Orators do attribute to things which are without life,
                                    not only life, but also reason and affection, and sometime
                                    speech. An example of Poetrie, The firmament bewailed his
                                    funerall, the sunne mourned and would not be seene, and the
                                    clouds shed great plentie of sorowfull teares. This kind of
                                    fained description, is framed only by attributing life, sense,
                                    reason, and affection to things which are voyd of them all. </p>
                            </div>

                            <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="6"> <head>From things without life to things having life.</head>

                                <p>From this place <term>Metaphors</term> of this sort are taken as
                                    to say, that men of famous renowne do shine, which is onely
                                    proper to the planets, as the Sunne, Moone and starres: in like
                                    maner we say, a stonie heart, a greene heard, a leaden wit, raw
                                    youth. Also a bitter people, a crooked nation, a sharpe judge, a
                                    glorious prince, the blossome of tneder age, the mist of
                                    memorie. In these examples by shine is signified excellent fame
                                    and renowne, by stoneie heart crueltie, by leaden wit a mind of
                                    small capacitie, &amp; c. This place is also very copious, and
                                    serveth much to perspecuitie. </p>
                            </div>

                            <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="7"> <head>From things senslesse to things senslesse.</head>

                                <p>By this place vices are layd to bud, desires to burne, beautie to
                                    wither, anger to boile, &amp; sometime to flame. In like forme
                                    we say, that envie is the canker of fame, that idlenesse is the
                                    rust of a common wealth, that <cit>
                                        <quote>evill words do corrupt good maners</quote>
                                        <bibl>1.Cor.15</bibl>
                                    </cit>. Also by this place are these and such like translations,
                                    a golden sentence, a filed phrase, flowing speech, ye waves of
                                    worldly troubles, the stormes of adversitie, the carkasses of
                                    mangled and destoryed cities. These significations are evident
                                    inough, and therefore I omit their interpretations.</p>
                            </div>

                            <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="8"> <head>From the offices and actions of men.</head>

                                <p>From the offices and actions of men are very usuall translations,
                                    and apt for description. 1. From the Magistrate. Example of holy
                                    Scripture, <cit>
                                        <quote>Judge not and you shall not be udged, condemne not,
                                            and ye shall not be condemned.</quote>
                                        <bibl>Luke.6.37.</bibl>
                                    </cit> Here judging and condemning be
                                    <term>Metaphoricall</term>, the authoritie to judge and condemne
                                    pertaineth properly to Judges who are lawfully deputed by the
                                    Princes of kingdomes to that office. </p>
                                <p><cit>
                                        <quote>Whose names are written in the booke of life,</quote>
                                        <bibl>Ephes.4.</bibl>
                                    </cit> here the wordes written and booke, are
                                        <term>Metaphors</term> taken from the Registers of Judges,
                                    or Scribes, or Secretaries of Princes, who are wont to register
                                    and inroll the pardons of life. </p>
                                <p> 2 From martiall actions and practises. Examples of holy
                                    scripture, <cit>
                                        <quote>I have fought a good fight.</quote>
                                        <bibl>2.Tim.4.</bibl>
                                    </cit> Another. <cit>
                                        <quote>Put on the armour of God, that you may resist in the
                                            evill time</quote>
                                        <bibl>Ephes.6.</bibl>
                                    </cit>: also, we wrastle not against fleshe and blood, &amp; c. </p>

                                <p>Arme not thy selfe to make warre against God, undermine not the
                                    simple and silly man, wound not the conscience of thy weake
                                    brother, clime not too fast to the scate of honor, tread not the
                                    poore under thy foote, triumph not before the victorie. </p>
                                <p>3 From the Phisition and Chirurgian, <cit>
                                        <quote>They heale the hurt of my people very
                                            slenderly.</quote>
                                        <bibl>Jere.8.</bibl>
                                    </cit> Another. <cit>
                                        <quote>A faithfull friend is a medicine of life.</quote>
                                        <bibl>Eccles.6.</bibl>
                                    </cit> By this place men say, that an injurie may be salved,
                                    that is, may be recompensed, that an ill member of a common
                                    wealth ought to be cut off, that is, ought to be executed
                                    according to his deserts. </p>
                                <p>4 From the husbandman. Examples of Scripture, <cit>
                                        <quote>They that plow iniquitie shall reape the
                                            fame.</quote>
                                        <bibl>Job.4.</bibl>
                                    </cit>
                                </p>
                                <p><cit>
                                        <quote>I have planted, Apollo hath watred.</quote>
                                        <bibl>1.Cor.3.</bibl>
                                    </cit>
                                </p>
                                <p><cit>
                                        <quote>Thou art he whom I must thresh.</quote>
                                        <bibl>2.Reg.14.</bibl>
                                    </cit>
                                </p>
                                <p>Sathan hath desired to sift you. </p>
                                <p><cit>
                                        <quote>He shall gather the wheate into his barne, &amp;
                                            c.</quote>
                                        <bibl>Mat.3.</bibl>
                                    </cit>
                                </p>
                                <p>5 From Artificers many translations are taken, as these and such
                                    like, to build, to pull downe, to set up, to waygh in ballance,
                                    to bray in a morter, to plane, to square, to mingle, to toyne,
                                    to digge, to frame, &amp; c. </p>
                            </div>

                            <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="9"> <head>From certain Substantives very much used in
                                    translation.</head>

                                <p>From certain Substantives, very apt and pleasant
                                        <term>Metaphors</term> are taken, as these following, and
                                    such like, <cit>
                                        <quote>Thy word is a lanterne to my feete, and light unto my
                                            pathes.</quote>
                                        <bibl>Psal.119.</bibl>
                                    </cit>
                                </p>
                                <p><cit>
                                        <quote>The night is past, &amp; the day is come.</quote>
                                        <bibl>Rom.13.</bibl>
                                    </cit> Another, <cit>
                                        <quote>The day dawne and the day starre ariseth in your
                                            hearts.</quote>
                                        <bibl>2.Pet.1.</bibl>
                                    </cit>
                                </p>
                                <p>They have stumbled against the stumbling stone. They are fallen
                                    into the same pit they made for others. </p>
                                <p>The way of sinners, and the chaire of scorners. <note place="marg" anchored="false">Psal.1.</note>
                                </p>
                                <p>Also we say by this place, that impunitie is a gate to all
                                    mischiefe, that hypocrisie is covered under the cloke of
                                    religion, that the hope of an hypocrite is a spiders web, that
                                    one evil condition is the staine of life. These also are common
                                        <term>Metaphors</term>, a spectacle of vertue, a haven of
                                    peace of rest, a buckler of defence, a fountaine of life, a
                                    rocke of refuge, a treasure of goodnesse, a shadow of
                                    protection. This place is a verie plentifull streame of
                                    translations, and as it is most plentifull, so is it not least
                                    pleasant. </p>
                            </div>

                            <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="10"> <head>From the four Elements.</head>

                                <p>First to begin with translations taken from the nature and
                                    propertie of fire we say a man of an inflamed mind, the flaming
                                    desire of malice doth seldome die till it be quenched with
                                    blood. Kindle not wrath, lest thou beest not able to quench it:
                                    an evill name is the smoke of sinne. </p>
                                <p>2 From the aire. His tyrannie never ceassed thundring out most
                                    dreadfull threatnings, &amp; with his venimous breath he blasted
                                    the green and flourishing properitie of his common wealth. </p>

                                <p>By this place we say, The raging tempests of sedition, the
                                    whirlewinds of trouble, the infection of ill examples. </p>
                                <p>3 From water, by this place it is, that one calleth wedlocke a
                                    sweete shower mingled with sharpe haile. An example of the holy
                                    Scripture. <cit>
                                        <quote>Wash me O Lord and I shall be whiter than
                                            snow.</quote>
                                        <bibl>Psal.51.</bibl>
                                    </cit> Also the Apostle saith, Quench not the spirit: we say in
                                    a proverb, Strive not against the streame. Likewise in this
                                    petition, <cit>
                                        <quote>Let the deaw of thy mercy O Lord refresh the heate of
                                            my miserie</quote>
                                        <bibl>Psal.18.</bibl>
                                    </cit>: <cit>
                                        <quote>We shall take me out of many waters, that is, out of
                                            many dangers</quote>
                                        <bibl>Psal.23.</bibl>
                                    </cit>: and in another place he sayth, And leade me foorth by
                                    the waters of comfort. </p>
                                <p>By this place we say, the waves of worldly troubles, that men
                                    ebbe or flow, thereby signifying either their amendement or
                                    decay, whether it be in the state of health or wealth. </p>
                                <p>4 From the earth are borrowed these &amp; such like translations,
                                    a large field of matter, a mountain of wealth, a wildernesse of
                                    doubts, a denne of thieves, a path of pleasure, a way of error,
                                    a vale of miserie. </p>
                            </div>

                            <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="11"> <head>From men to God.</head>

                                <p>So infinite and incomprehensible is the nature of Almightie God,
                                    and mans capacitie of so small a compasse, that no one attribute
                                    of God can be conceived by mans weake understanding without the
                                    helpe of earthly images and naturall propertie well knowne to
                                    man, and therefore forasmuch as mans eye cannot behold invisible
                                    vertues, nor his understanding able to apprehend the
                                    incomprehensible wisedome: Almightie God of his goodnesse hath
                                    described him selfe by the most excellent and evident letters
                                    and caracters imprinted most lively in his creatures, not only
                                    by such as are somewhat secret, but also and most chiefly by
                                    such as are evident and manifest to mans understanding and
                                    knowledge. Hence it is that he is called a King, a Lord, and
                                    Lord of hosts, a Judge, a father, an husbandman, a planter of a
                                    vineyard, a shepherd, a nurse, a guide, a rocke, a buckler in
                                    the day of battel, an Egle: these and such like are the letters
                                    of comfort, by which we may easily reade and plainely understand
                                    the goodnesse of our God towards us, for by earthly kings, and
                                    Lords of armies is described to us his majestie and his power,
                                    by Judges his equitie and love of justice, by fathers his love
                                    and tender compassion, by shepherds his dayly providence and
                                    careful custodie of his people, by nurses his most loving regard
                                    and manifold benefites, by guides, his governement and safe
                                    condition, by rockes his sure defence against all violence and
                                    oppression. But in respect of his enemies, he is called a giant
                                    to wound, a judge to condemne, and a fire to consume. This part
                                    of translation is called of the Grecians Anthtopopathia, that
                                    is, an attributing to God humane affections. </p>
                            </div>

                            <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="12"> <head>From God to men.</head>

                                <p>By this place we give the titles of highnesse an dmajestie to
                                    PRinces, which are proper to God, yet meete for them in respect
                                    of their high dignities &amp; princely thrones, wherin Almightie
                                    God the giver of majesty hath place thee. An example of the
                                    sacred Scripture, <cit>
                                        <quote>I said ye are Gods</quote>
                                        <bibl>Psal.82.</bibl>
                                    </cit>: by calling thee Gods he signifieth from whome they have
                                    their authoritie, whose place they supply, whose person they
                                    present, and whose example they ought to follow, both in
                                    executing of justice, and in shewing of mercy. Thus in one word
                                    they are put in mind what they are, or what they ought to be,
                                    and being as they should be, that they ought so to continue.
                                </p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <!-- End of efficient cause -->

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="3"> <head>The use of <term>Metaphors</term>.</head>

                            <p>All <term>Metaphors</term> have their maniforld trutes, and the same
                                both profitable and pleasant, which is a thing well known to men of
                                learning and wisedome. First, they give pleasant light to darke
                                things, tereby removing unprofitable and odious obscurite. <note place="marg" anchored="false">They give light.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>Secondly, by the aptnesse of thier proportion, and nearenesse of
                                affinitie, they worke in the hearer many effects, they obtaine <note place="marg" anchored="false">2. They move
                                affections.</note>allowance of his judgement, they move his
                                affections, and minister a pleasure to his wit.<note place="marg" anchored="false">3. They are pleasant.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>Thirdly, they are forcible to perswade. Fourthly to commend <note place="marg" anchored="false">4. They are forcible to
                                    perswade.</note> or dispraise. </p>
                            <p>Fifthly, they leave such a firme impression in the momory, as is not
                                lightly forgotten.<note place="marg" anchored="false">They are well
                                    remembred.</note>
                            </p>
                        </div>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="4"> <head>The comparison of <term>Metaphors</term>.</head>

                            <p>Metaphors in respect of their perspecuitie, &amp; light which they
                                give, may well be compared to the starres of the skie, which <note place="marg" anchored="false">Compared to the stars.</note> are
                                both the comfort of the night, &amp; the beautie of the firmament.
                                    <note place="marg" anchored="false">2. To colours.</note> 2. In
                                respect of their aptnesse to make descriptions, they are not onely
                                as pleasant colours of all kinds, but also as readie pensils pliable
                                    <note place="marg" anchored="false">3. To pensils. </note>to lure
                                out and shadow any maner of proportion in narture. 3. In respect of
                                thier firme impression in the mind &amp; remembrance <note place="marg" anchored="false">4. To seales, To stamps in
                                    mettall.</note>of the hearer, they are as seales upon soft ware,
                                or as deep stamps in long lasting metal. </p>
                        </div>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="5"> <head>The Caution.</head>

                            <p>In the choise and use of translation heed ought to be taken, that
                                    <note place="marg" anchored="false">1. Unlikenesse</note> these
                                faults be not found in <term>Metaphors</term>. First, that there be
                                not an unlikenesse in stead of a likenesse, as if one should say,
                                the bull barketh, <note place="marg" anchored="false">2. Far fetcht or
                                    strange.</note>which is very unlike, Secondly, that the
                                similitude be not farre fetcht, as from strange things unknowne to
                                the hearer, as if one should take <term>Metaphors</term> from the
                                parts of a ship, and apply them among husbandmen which never came at
                                the sea, he shall obscure the thing that he would fainest make
                                evident. Thirdly, <note place="marg" anchored="false">3. Unchast
                                    signification.</note> that there be no uncleane or unchast
                                signification contained in the <term>Metaphore</term>, which may
                                offend against modest and reverend minds. <note place="marg" anchored="false">4, Excesse, or defect in the
                                similitude.</note>Fourthly, that the similitude be not greater then
                                the matter requireth, or contrariwise lesse.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>

                    <div type="textpart" subtype="subpart" n="2"> <head><term>Onomatopeia</term>.</head>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="1">

                            <p><term>Onomatopeia</term>, this figure of the Latines is diversly
                                named, as <term>Nominatio</term>, <term>Nominis fictia</term>,
                                    <term>Procreatio</term>. It is a forme of speech whereby the
                                Orator or speaker maketh and faineth a name to some thing, imitating
                                the sound or voyce of that it signifieth, or else whereby he
                                affecteth a word derived from the name of a person, or from the
                                originall of ye thing which it doth expresse. And this form of
                                fayning, &amp; framing names is used diverse wayes. First, by
                                imitation of sounds, as to <note place="marg" anchored="false">1. By
                                    imitation of sound.</note> say, a hurliburly, signifying a
                                tumult or uprore: likewise, rushing, lumbring, ratling, blustring,
                                creking, and may such like. <note place="marg" anchored="false">2. By
                                    imitation of voyces.</note> Secondly, by imitation of voyces, as
                                the roaring of Lyons, the bellowing of buls, the blating of sheepe,
                                the grunting of swine, the croking of frogs, the chattering of Pies,
                                the chirping of sparrows, the howling of dogs, the neighing of
                                horses, ye hissing of serpents. Thirdly, by the derivation from the
                                original, as the citie Troy was so called by derivation from king
                                Troc, &amp; before that it was <note place="marg" anchored="false">3.
                                    By derivation from the originall.</note> called Teucria, from
                                Teucrus and first of all Dardania from Dardanus, so Ninivie of
                                Ninus, so Luds-towne of Lud, and now London. Fourthly, by
                                composition, as when we put two words together <note place="marg" anchored="false">4. By composition of two words.</note> and make
                                of them but one, as to say, Oratorlike, scholerlike: also to call a
                                churle thickskin, a niggard a pinchpeny, a flattere a pickthanke, a
                                glutton a bellygod. Fifthly, by reviving antiquity. <note place="marg" anchored="false">5. Imitating antiquitie.</note>
                                Touching this part I will refer the Reader to Chaucer &amp; Gower,
                                and to the new Shepherds Calendar, a most singular imitation of
                                ancient speech. The sixt maner of speaking or writing by this figure
                                is, when we signifie the imitation of another mans property or
                                fashion: this forme of speaking is very usual in the Greeke tongue,
                                and somewaht it is used in the Latine, as when they say, Patrissare,
                                matrissare, Platonissare, that is to say, to imitate his father, to
                                imitate his mother, to imitate Plato, which forme our tongue can
                                hardly imitate, except we should say, he doth fatherize, Platonize,
                                temporize, which is not much in use. Yet the English tongue
                                endevoreth what it can so speake by this part, as where it saith, I
                                can not court it, I can not Italian it, that is, I can not performe
                                the dutie or manners of a courtier, I can not imitate the fashion of
                                an Italian. </p>
                        </div>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="2"> <head>The use of this Figure.</head>

                            <p>This figure serveth fitly to make description of an action, as much
                                as may be signified by noise or found. Also it pretendeth <note place="marg" anchored="false">1. To describe.</note> to the hearer
                                the nature of beasts, birds and other things, by the proper
                                imitation of their voyces. By derivation from the originall, it
                                recordeth a perpetuall memorie of the first founders <note place="marg" anchored="false">2. To record.</note>of great workes:
                                it serveth to brevitie by the apt composition, it is <note place="marg" anchored="false">3. To brevity.</note> the register
                                of ancient speech and antiquitie.<note place="marg" anchored="false">4. To retaine antiquitie.</note>
                            </p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="3"> <head>The Caution.</head>

                            <p>As the use of this figure is both profitable &amp; pleasant, being
                                artificially framed: so is it very unseemely and ridiculous,<note place="marg" anchored="false">1. Unlike, or unequall in
                                    proportion.</note> if Art be neglected, and therefore these
                                observations ought to be regarded. First, concerning the imitation
                                of sound, that it be somwhat like to the thing it signifieth, and
                                not unlike, as if one should call the sound of a Cannon, a ratling
                                or cracking, it were farre from the fimilitude, or if he should call
                                the roaring of a Lion, a blating or a grunting, it were absurd if
                                the voyce should be extended to the uttermost in the word of
                                imitation, for that were most ridiculous. Thirdly, as is said in the
                                    <term>Metaphore</term>, unchast and vile imitation ought to be
                                shunned, and alwayes a discreet regard to be observed. </p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <!-- end of Onomatopeia -->


                    <div type="textpart" subtype="subpart" n="3"> <head><term>Catachresis</term>.</head>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="1">

                            <p><term>Catachresis</term> in Latine is called <term>Abusio</term>, and
                                it is a forme of speech wherby the speaker or writer wanting a
                                proper word, borroweth the next or the likest to the thing that he
                                would signifie. An example: They build a horse by Pallas art divine:
                                here the Poet traduceth that to a beast, which is proper to the
                                    making<note place="marg" anchored="false">Deut.3.</note> of a
                                house. An example of Moses. <cit>
                                    <quote>The drincke the pure blood of the grapes,</quote>
                                    <bibl>Prov.30.</bibl>
                                </cit> here the prophet putteth this word blood for juyce. Salomen
                                by this figure nameth <cit>
                                    <quote>the two daughters of the horsleech.</quote>
                                    <bibl>Psal.127.</bibl>
                                </cit> Also it is sayd in the Psalme. <cit>
                                    <quote>Let my right hand forget her cunning</quote>
                                    <bibl>Psa.1.</bibl>
                                </cit>: likewise the Prophet sayth, <cit>
                                    <quote>The sword shall devoure</quote>
                                    <bibl>Ione.46.</bibl>
                                </cit>. </p>
                            <p>By the licence of this figure we give names to many things which
                                lacke names, as when we say, the water runne, which is improper, for
                                to run, is proper to those creatures which have feete, and not water
                                which hath none. By this forme we attribute hornes to a snaile, and
                                feete to a stoole, &amp; so likewise to many other things which do
                                lacke their proper names. </p>

                            <p><note place="marg" anchored="false">To make supply where a word
                                    wasteth</note>The use of this figure is chiefly to serve in time
                                of neede, as to yeeld a necessarie supply for the want of a proper
                                word. </p>
                        </div>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="2"> <head>The Caution.</head>

                            <p><note place="marg" anchored="false">1. Not to far fetcht.</note>This
                                observation is to be regarded, that we fetch not the <note place="marg" anchored="false">2. Not to be used too
                                oft.</note>translation too farre off, or that which is much unlike.
                                Secondly that we use it not oft. </p>
                        </div>
                    </div>

                    <div type="textpart" subtype="subpart" n="4"> <head><term>Synecdoche</term>.</head>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="1">

                            <p><term>Synecdoche</term> in Latine called <term>Intellectio</term>,
                                that is, an understanding, and it is a forme of speech by which the
                                Orator signifieth more or lesse by a word, which the proper
                                signification doth not expresse: and it is by putting the whole for
                                the part or the part for the whole. </p>
                            <p>By the whole is meant, the whole of a quantitie, the generall kind,
                                the plurall number, the matter of which things are made. </p>
                            <p>1. The whole put for a part. An example: An host so great as dranke
                                rivers drie, meaning a great part of rivers. An example of ye holy
                                Scriptures: <cit>
                                    <quote>All the world came to heare the wisdome of
                                        Salomon,</quote>
                                    <bibl>1.Reg.10.</bibl>
                                </cit> understanding a great part of the world, and not all the
                                world as it is expressed. </p>
                            <p>2. The generall kind for the speciall kind. An example of the holy
                                Scripture: Preach the Gospell to all cratures, signifying to all
                                men, and not to any other Creature. </p>
                            <p>3. The Plurall number put for the singular Cicero to Brutus: We
                                deceived the people, and seemed Orators, understanding but himselfe. </p>
                            <p>4. The matter for the things made of that matter: They eate the
                                finest wheate, and drinke the sweetest grapes, by wheate is
                                understood bread, and by grapes wine. </p>
                            <p>5. Things following put for things going before: Thou shalt eat thy
                                bread in the sweat of thy face. Here by sweat following labor, is
                                signified labor going before sweate. Hitherto the more is signified,
                                and the lesse is understood. </p>
                            <p>Now contrariwise the part is expressed and the whole is understood.
                                An example of Scripture: I am not worthy that thou shouldest enter
                                under my roofe. Here by the roofe is signified the whole house.
                                Another example: <cit>
                                    <quote>Blessed in the wormbe that bore thee and the pappes which
                                        gave thee lucke.</quote>
                                    <bibl>Luc.11.</bibl>
                                </cit> There wombe &amp; the pappes do signifie the mother, and in
                                the holy Scripture the soule is often put alone, and signifieth the
                                whole man. </p>

                            <p>2 The speciall kind put for the general: it is not my sword that
                                shall helpe me, by sword is understood all kind of weapons, and
                                maner of defence. Another: <cit>
                                    <quote>Man that not live by bread only,</quote>
                                    <bibl>Mat.4.</bibl>
                                </cit> by bread is signfified all kind of food an nourishment. </p>
                            <p>3 The singular number for the plural: A man borne of a woman hath but
                                a short time to live, meaning all men. The Romane was victor in
                                battle, understanding the Romane host. </p>
                            <p>4 By things going before, things following are signified: He put the
                                people to the sword and the citie to the fire. Here by these words
                                sword and fire is signified the generall slaughter of the people,
                                and utter destruction of the citie, which presently folowed. Another
                                example of the holy Scripture: Say to the sonnes of Amon the sword
                                is drawne, here by the drawne sword is signfified the slaughter
                                ensuing. </p>
                            <p><note place="marg" anchored="false">1. Wisedome required in the
                                    hearer.</note>The Orator useth this figure chiefly when he is
                                well perswaded concerning the wisedome of his hearers, that they are
                                of sufficient capacitie and understanding to collect his meaning,
                                whereupon he maketh the bolder to remove his speech from the vulgar
                                    <note place="marg" anchored="false">2. A grace of
                                speech.</note>maner of speaking to a figurative forme, whereby he
                                giveth it a <note place="marg" anchored="false">3. A further
                                    consideration of the sense.</note>grace which otherwise it
                                should want, forcing the understanding of his hearer to a deeper
                                consideration of the sense and meaning. </p>
                        </div>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="2"> <head>The Caution.</head>

                            <p>These observations concerning this figure ought to be thought upon.
                                    <note place="marg" anchored="false">1. Apt choice of the
                                    partes.</note> first that when a part is put for the whole,
                                there be a discreete choise of that part: the roofe is put many
                                times for the house, but not the window, nor the rafters. </p>
                            <p><note place="marg" anchored="false">2. Choice of the speciall
                                    kind.</note>2. Secondly, that there be likewise a choyse of the
                                speciall kinds when they signifie the generall. </p>
                            <p><note place="marg" anchored="false">3. Not to be used in pleas nor in
                                    cuideces.</note>3 Also it is to be remembred that this figure
                                ought not to be used in judiciall pleading, for there a part may not
                                stand for the whole, nore the whole for a part, without some wrong
                                to the one partie or to the other. </p>
                            <p><note place="marg" anchored="false">4. Unfit among ignorant
                                    persons.</note>4 Lastly the use of this figure is very unfit
                                among ignorant hearers which for lacke of knowledge may mistake it,
                                and likewise <note place="marg" anchored="false">5. Captious cavillers
                                    may abuse it.</note>among cavilling and captious persons, which
                                of wilfull perversenesse may canily pervert the true meaning, either
                                by malice or mockerie. </p>
                        </div>
                    </div>

                    <div type="textpart" subtype="subpart" n="5"> <head><term>Metonimia</term>.</head>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="1">

                            <p><term>Metonimia</term>, called of the Latines
                                    <term>Transnominatio</term>, and of some <term>Hypallage</term>,
                                it is a forme of speech, wherby the Orator putteth one thing for
                                another, which by nature are nigh knit together. This change of name
                                is used foure wayes. 1. The cause for the effect. 2. The effect for
                                the cause. 3. The subject for he Adjunct. 4. The Adjunct for the
                                subject. </p>
                            <p>Under the name of the cause are contained the efficient, the
                                inventer, the commander, the instrument. </p>
                            <p>1 The efficient: <cit>
                                    <quote>The sword without, pestilence and famine within.</quote>
                                    <bibl>Ezec.7.</bibl>
                                </cit> By pestilence and famine is signified death the effect of
                                those causes. Another: <cit>
                                    <quote>I have called for a drought upon the earth.</quote>
                                    <bibl>Agge.1.</bibl>
                                </cit> By drought is understood hunger and famine caused by drought. </p>
                            <p>2. The inventer for the thing invented: as Mars for warre, Ceres for
                                fruit, Bacchus for wine, Vulcane for fire, Mercurie for eloquence,
                                ye author for his work thus, He learned his argumented of Aristotle,
                                &amp; his eloquence of Tullie, he esseemed much of Livius, and tooke
                                great delight in Plato; signifying by these Authors their <note place="marg" anchored="false">Luc.16.</note> workes. An example of
                                the holy Scripture: <cit>
                                    <quote>They have Moses and the Prophets</quote>
                                    <bibl>Luc.16.</bibl>
                                </cit>: that is, their bookes and volumes. </p>
                            <p>3 The commander or governour for those which are under his
                                governement: Hannibal was slaine by Scipio. Here Hannibal is put for
                                his army which he led against the Romans, and Scipio for the Romans
                                who obtained the victorie. </p>
                            <p>4 The instruments for their effects. Examples: <cit>
                                    <quote>The scepter shall not depart from Juda.</quote>
                                    <bibl>Gen.49.</bibl>
                                </cit> Another: The unlikely have worne the crowne. Here scepter and
                                crowne being instruments of royal dignitie do signifie a kingdom. <cit>
                                    <quote>He beareth not ye sword for nought.</quote>
                                    <bibl>Rom.13.</bibl>
                                </cit> Also: There shall no sword go through your land. In the
                                former example is understood by sword, the authoritie of a
                                Magistrate, in the later warre and conquest. </p>
                            <p>An example of Job: <cit>
                                    <quote>Let me be weighed in an even ballance.</quote>
                                    <bibl>Job.31.</bibl>
                                </cit> Here ballance, and instrument of equitie, is put for equity
                                it self. </p>
                            <p>In like maner we use to put the chaine for bondage, the key for
                                office, the rod for correction, and the crosse for persecution. </p>
                            <p>Secondly, the effect is put for the cause: by this we say, Death is
                                pale, feare sad, anger hastie, wine bold. Here is signified, that
                                death maketh pale, and feare maketh sad, and likewise of the rest.
                                An example of holy scripture: I am the resurrection, Christ meaneth
                                that he is the cause of the resurrection. Another: <cit>
                                    <quote>There are two nations in thy wombe.</quote>
                                    <bibl>Gen.25.</bibl>
                                </cit> Almightie God speaking this to Rebecca, signifieth by two
                                nations, the authors or fathers of two nations, that is, Esau the
                                father or author of the Idumeans, and Jacob the father or author of
                                the Israelites or Jewes. Another: <cit>
                                    <quote>Death is in the pot O man of God,</quote>
                                    <bibl>2.Reg.4.</bibl>
                                </cit> that is, a deadly thing, or a thing which is the cause of
                                death. </p>
                            <p>Another example of Job: Be not thou too extreme upon my sin. Here Job
                                by sinne signifieth him selfe, the efficient of his sinne. </p>
                            <p>By this place also, an instrument in respect of his regent may stand
                                as an effect, and signifie his agent. An example: <cit>
                                    <quote>As thy sword hath made many women childlesse, so shall
                                        thy mother be deprived of thee.</quote>
                                    <bibl>1.Sam.15.</bibl>
                                </cit> Here Samuel putteth the sword for Agag the regent or agent of
                                the sword. </p>
                            <p>Thirdly, the subject put for the Adjunct, the subject is that which
                                containeth, the Adjunct is that which is contained, and this
                                containing is sayd of diverse things diversly. </p>
                            <p>1 The possessor for the thing possessed. An example: <cit>
                                    <quote>Juda shall be inhabited for evermore.</quote>
                                    <bibl>Amos.1.</bibl>
                                </cit> Here Juda the sonne of Jacob is put for the land of Jewrie
                                which was promised to his posteritie, and by them possessed.
                                Another: I pray thee depart not from thy servant. Here Abraham
                                understandeth his tent under the naming of him selfe. By this place
                                cities, lands, houses and ships are often called by the names of
                                their owners. </p>
                            <p>2 Time put for the things done in time. An example: I have considered
                                the dayes of old, and the yeares that are past. By dayes and yeares,
                                the Prophet signifieth the peace and prosperity which sometime he
                                enjoyed. By this place it is said, that the dayes thought is the
                                nights dreame, that the mornings view correcteth the evenings worke.
                                In these two examples the day and the night, the morning and evening
                                do signifie the actions and accidents in them. Hence it is, that
                                times being put for the accidents in them, are either commended or
                                dispraised, as when we say, O blessed time, O happy age, or as the
                                Poet saith, My happie dayes be past, my joyfull yeares be gone. In
                                dispraise thus, O wicked world, O malicious age. </p>
                            <p>3 Place put for the things it containeth. An example: <cit>
                                    <quote>I call heaven and earth to record.</quote>
                                    <bibl>Deu.30.</bibl>
                                </cit> Here Moses by heaven and earth <note place="marg" anchored="false">1. The world.</note> understandeth the creatures
                                of heaven and earth, which he caleth to witnesse with him. </p>
                            <p>Another, Italie can not be overcome by warre, nor Greece by <note place="marg" anchored="false">2. Countreys.</note> learning,
                                meaning the people in those countreys. </p>
                            <p>They invade the citie opprest with sleepe. By the city is meant<note place="marg" anchored="false">3. Cities.</note> the Troyans being
                                in their dead sleepe and midnight. </p>
                            <p>An example of the holy Scripture, O Jerulalem, Jerusalem, thou which
                                killest the Prophets. By Jerusalem Christ signifieth the Rulers and
                                the people of that citie. </p>
                            <p>Another: <cit>
                                    <quote>He made him ruler of his house,</quote>
                                    <bibl>Gen.39.4.</bibl>
                                </cit> that is, of all his servants treasures, and goods within his
                                house. </p>
                            <p>4 The container for the thing contained: Is not the cup of<note place="marg" anchored="false">4. Houses.</note> blessing, which we
                                blesse the communion of the blood of Christ? In this example ye
                                Apostle putteth the cup for the contents of the cup. Another: <cit>
                                    <quote>There shall be one fold, and one shepherd,</quote>
                                    <bibl>Joh.70.</bibl>
                                </cit> that is, one company or flocke. </p>
                            <p>Sometime the <term>Metonimia</term> of place signifieth the actions
                                in lace. An example: <cit>
                                    <quote>For thy temples sake which is at Jerusalem, kings shall
                                        bring presents to thee.</quote>
                                    <bibl>Psal.68</bibl>
                                </cit> Here by the Temple is understood the holy exercises and
                                divine worship used in the Temple. </p>
                            <p>In the same sense men use to say, The hall is done, meaning the
                                actions in the Courts of judgement. </p>
                            <p>4 The Adjunct for the subject. An example: Righteousnesse hath looked
                                downe from heaven, meaning God in whom righteousnesse resteth.
                                Another: <cit>
                                    <quote>There is no truth, no mercie, no knowledge of God in this
                                        land.</quote>
                                    <bibl>Ose.4.1.</bibl>
                                </cit> By these Adjuncts the prophet signifieth that there are none,
                                or at least very fewe, in whome these vertues may be found. </p>
                            <p>Another: Noah lived after the flood three hundred and fifteen yeares.
                                Here the flood being an Adjunk, signifieth time the subject. </p>
                        </div>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="2"> <head>The use of this figure.</head>

                            <p>The use of this figure is very great and very pleasant, it <note place="marg" anchored="false">1.Varietie.</note>yieldeth great
                                varietie of speech, and serveth aptly to brevity, it <note place="marg" anchored="false">2.Veritie.</note>is of large and
                                ample capactitie to containe matters of great signification, <note place="marg" anchored="false">3.Ample capacitie.</note>and of many
                                figures there are none more pleasant or <note place="marg" anchored="false">4.Delectatio.</note>
                                <note place="marg" anchored="false">5.Signficiation.</note>more
                                significant then this. </p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="3"> <head>The Caution.</head>

                            <p>As there are many particular places of this figure: so there may be
                                many faults committed, &amp; therefore especial regard ought to be
                                had that they may be avoyded. <note place="marg" anchored="false">1.Not in use.</note>The most generall fault of all, is, when
                                the <term>Metonimie</term> is not taken from the common use, and
                                knowne custome of the word. As for example, if you should put
                                Neptune for the skill of riding, who is reported to be the inventer
                                of that art, you should make the <term>Metonimie</term> faultie,
                                    <note place="marg" anchored="false">2.Obscurity.</note> your
                                speech obscure, if not absurd. Therfore every inventer <note place="marg" anchored="false">3.Everie inventor, or cause, may not
                                    be put for their effects, &amp; c.</note> may not be put for the
                                thing invented, nor every cause for the effect, nor every subject
                                for the Adjunct, but such as are in knowne use, and may aptly be put
                                for the things which they signifie. </p>
                        </div>
                    </div>

                    <div type="textpart" subtype="subpart" n="6"> <head><term>Antonomasia</term>.</head>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="1">

                            <p><term>Antonomasia</term>, of the Latines called
                                    <term>Nominatio</term> and <term>Nominis permutatio</term>, that
                                is, a naming, or the changing of a name, it is a forme of speech by
                                which the Orator for a proper name putteth another, as some name of
                                dignity, office, profession, science or trade. </p>
                            <p><note place="marg" anchored="false">1.Dignitie.</note>1 By this figure
                                when the Orator speaketh to a king or a Prince, he saith, your
                                Grace, your Highnesse, or your Majestie: to a Noble man, your
                                Lordship, your Honor. </p>
                            <p>2 Also in sted of a name or title, he useth a decent and due Epithite
                                thus, Reverend Father, honorable Judge. In this forme speaketh the
                                Apostle Paule, where he saith, Dearely beloved, and Salomon likewise
                                bringeth in <cit>
                                    <quote>Christ calling his Church his sister, his love and his
                                        dove</quote>
                                    <bibl>Cant.</bibl>
                                </cit>, and the Church in like maner calling Christ her beloved. </p>
                            <p>3 The author by the name of his profession or science, as when we
                                say, the Philosopher for Aristotle: the Greeke Poet for Homer: the
                                Romane Orator for Cicero: the Psalmograph for David. </p>
                            <p>4 A man by the name of his countrey, as, the Persian, the Polonian,
                                the Germane, the Brittane. </p>
                            <p>5 Also when we give to one man the name of another for the affinities
                                sake of their maners or conditions. In praise thus, as when we call
                                a grave man a Cato, a just dealer an Aristides, a wise man a
                                Salomon. In dispraise, to call a glorious boaster a Thraso, an
                                envious detracter a Zoilus, a captious reprehender a Momus, a tyrant
                                a Nero, a voluptuous liver an Epicure. </p>
                        </div>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="2"> <head>The use of this figure</head>

                            <p>The use of this figure is both necessary &amp; profitable, for the by
                                forme the orator when he speaketh to high dignities, he boweth <note place="marg" anchored="false">1.Gravitie.</note>(as it were) the
                                knee of his speech, and lifteth up the eye of his phrase to the
                                bright beames of earthly glory, therby declaring his due reverence,
                                and their high dignitie. It helpeth much in praising <note place="marg" anchored="false">2.Amplification.</note> or
                                dispraising, by the equall comparison, it serveth readily for copie
                                and varietie.<note place="marg" anchored="false">3.Varietie.</note>
                            </p>
                        </div>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="3"> <head>The Caution.</head>

                            <p>The faultes that may be committed in this figure are these, To give a
                                lesse name then the dignitie requireth, as speaking to a king to
                                say, Your worship, or in sted of a name of reverence <note place="marg" anchored="false">1.Names debasing.</note> to use
                                another that is base or ridiculous, as speaking to a grave father,
                                to call him gray beard: or to use amorous termes, as <note place="marg" anchored="false">2.Ridiculous.</note>sweete heart,
                                and finally to use any name which is unfit for the <note place="marg" anchored="false">3.Amorous.</note> person to whom it
                                is attributed or undecent and unchast, either <note place="marg" anchored="false">4.Unchast.</note>in open apparance, or in
                                shadowed signification. </p>
                        </div>
                    </div>

                    <div type="textpart" subtype="subpart" n="7"> <head><term>Metalepsis</term>.</head>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="1">
                            <p><term>Metalepsis</term>, called of the Latines
                                    <term>Transumptio</term>, it is a forme of speech by which the
                                Orator in one word expressed, signifieth another word or thing
                                removed from it by certaine degrees. </p>
                            <p>Virgil by eares of corne signifieth sommers, &amp; by sommers yeares.
                                An example of the holy scripture: <cit>
                                    <quote>The tongues of the sucking children do cleave to the
                                        roofe of their mouth for very thirst.</quote>
                                    <bibl>Iere.lam.44</bibl>
                                </cit> Here by the extreme thirst of the sucking babes, the Prophet
                                signifieth the barraine and drie breasts of the mothers, by the drie
                                breasts the extreame hunger and famine, and by the famine the wofull
                                affliction and great miserie of the people.<note place="marg" anchored="false">1.This figure is a kind of
                                    <term>Metonimye</term>.</note> This figure is a kind of
                                    <term>Metonimie</term>, signifying by the effect a cause far off
                                by an effect nigh at hand: yet it is a forme of speech selcome used
                                of Orators and not oft of Poets, yet is it not voyd <note place="marg" anchored="false">2.Seldome used of Orators.</note>of
                                profit &amp; utility, for it teacheth the understanding to dive down
                                to the bottom of the sense, and instructeth the eye of the wit,
                                    to<note place="marg" anchored="false">3.The use &amp; utilitie of
                                    this figure.</note> discerne a meaning farre off. For which
                                property it may well be compare to an high prospect, which
                                presenteth to the viewe of the beholder an object far distant by
                                leading the eye from one marke to another by a lineall direction,
                                till it discerneth the thing that is looked for. </p>
                        </div>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="2"> <head>The Caution.</head>

                            <p><note place="marg" anchored="false">1.Too farre removed.</note> The
                                faultes which may be committed in this figure are these, when the
                                word expressed and the thing signified stand too far <note place="marg" anchored="false">2.Not to be used in matters
                                    requiring perspicutie.</note>asunder, that is so many degrees,
                                as the meaning can not be understood. Secondly, when it is used in a
                                cause which requireth perspicuitie. </p>
                        </div>
                    </div>

                    <div type="textpart" subtype="subpart" n="8"> <head><term>Antiphrasis</term>.</head>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="1">

                            <p><term>Antiphrasis</term> is a forme of speech which by a word exprest
                                doth signifie the contrary: as when the speaker sayth, wisely, or
                                wittily, understanding the contrary. Also to say You are alwayes my
                                friend, meaning, mine enemie. You are a man of great judgement,
                                signfying unapt and unable to judge. </p>
                        </div>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="2"> <head>The use of this figure.</head>

                            <p>The especiall use of this figure is to reprehend vice, and mock
                                folly: for by expressing a vertue, and signifying a vice, it <note place="marg" anchored="false">1.Sharpe rebuke.</note>striketh the
                                mind of the offender with the sharpe edge of contrarie comparison,
                                whereby he is compelled to see the great difference between what he
                                is, and what he ought to be, betweene what he hath done, and what he
                                ought to have done, and so by looking in the cleare glasse he may be
                                ashamed of his foule face, I meane his souls face. </p>
                        </div>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="3"> <head>The Caution.</head>

                            <p>This figure ought not be used without some urgent cause, <note place="marg" anchored="false">1.Not to be used without great
                                    cause.</note> neither is it seemely to be used of all person in
                                respect of the breach of duty: it were unmeete for the sonne to say,
                                wisely spoken <note place="marg" anchored="false">2.Not of all
                                    persons.</note>father for it were as much, as o call his father
                                foole: and likewise for a servant in his anger to use this figure
                                against his mayster, it were contrary to good maners: and therefore
                                these two things ought to be observed, that it be not used without
                                great cause, nor of any without some authoritie, or at the least
                                matched <note place="marg" anchored="false">3.Not included with
                                    authoritie.</note>in equalitie. </p>
                        </div>
                    </div>


                </div>
                <!-- end of Tropes of Words -->

                <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="5"> <head><term>Tropes</term> of Sentences.</head>

                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item n="1"><term>Allegoria</term></item>
                        <item n="2"><term>AEnigma</term></item>
                        <item n="3"><term>Paroemia</term></item>
                        <item n="4"><term>Hyperbole</term></item>
                        <item n="5"><term>Asteismus</term></item>
                        <item n="6"><term>Ironia</term></item>
                        <item n="7"><term>Charientismus</term></item>
                        <item n="8"><term>Sarcasmus</term></item>
                        <item n="9"><term>Mycterisinus</term></item>
                        <item n="10"><term>Diasiriuus</term></item>
                    </list>

                    <div type="textpart" subtype="subpart" n="1"> <head><term>Allegoria</term>.</head>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="1">

                            <p><term>Allegoria</term>, called of Quintilian, <term>Inversio</term>,
                                is a <term>Trope</term> of a sentence, or forme of speech which
                                expresseth one thing in words, and another in sense. In a
                                    <term>Metaphore</term> there is a translation of one word onely,
                                in an <term>Allegorie</term> of many, and for that cause an
                                    <term>Allegorie</term> is called a continued
                                    <term>Metaphore</term>. </p>
                            <p>An example: Rubbe not the scarre, lest you open againe the wound that
                                is healed, and so cause it to bleed afresh. The signification hereof
                                is, Renue not by rehearsall the sorrow which time hath made forgot. </p>
                            <p>Another: Shall we suffer the monstrous Crocodile to come out of Nilus
                                and to breake into our fold, to overcome our shepherd, to rent off
                                our skins with his griping pawes, to crash our carkasses with his
                                veimous teeth, to fill his insatiable panch with our flesh, and to
                                wallow at his pleasure in our wooll? </p>
                            <p>Another like unto this: Shall we sit aloofe amazed among boughes and
                                suffer the serpent to climbe our tree, to thrust us out of our
                                nests, to sucke our blood, to devour our birds, and to sleepe among
                                our feathers? By these two <term>Allegories,</term> as well by the
                                one as by the other, one enemies are described, who either by open
                                force or secret conspiracie, are prepared and fully bent to make
                                conquest of our countrey, to murder and destroy us people, to
                                possesse our dwellings, and enjoy our wealth. </p>
                            <p>Examples of Poetical <term>Allegories</term>: O ship shal new flouds
                                carie thee again into the sea? What doest thou nowe? strive manfully
                                to keepe the port alway. </p>
                            <p>Another: Thou Licinie mayst live full well, if wisely evermore. Thou
                                doest not thrust into the deepe, nor presse too nigh the shore: for
                                feare of stormes </p>
                            <p>In the former verse Horace by Ship understandeth Sextus Popeius
                                making incursions, and troubling the sea with navall war, whom he
                                exhorteth to make peace with Augustus. By flouds he signifieth
                                civill battell, and by Port peace and concord. In the later he much
                                commendeth mediocritie. Horace was much delighted in this kind of
                                speech, as may appeare by many of his verses which he wrote
                                Allegorically. </p>
                            <p>Examples of the holy Scriptures: <cit>
                                    <quote>Whose fan is in his hand, and he shall purge his floore,
                                        and gather his wheate into his barn, but will burne the
                                        chaffe with unquenchable fire.</quote>
                                    <bibl>Mat.3.</bibl>
                                </cit>
                            </p>
                            <p>Another: <cit>
                                    <quote>A brused reede shal he not breake, and smoking flare
                                        shall he not quench, till he bring forth judgement unto
                                        venorie.</quote>
                                    <bibl>Esa.4.3.</bibl>
                                </cit>
                            </p>
                            <p>Another: <cit>
                                    <quote>Give ye not that which is holy to dogs, neither cast ye
                                        your pearles before swine, lest they tread them under their
                                        feete, and turning againe all to rent you.</quote>
                                    <bibl>Mat.7.</bibl>
                                </cit>
                            </p>
                            <p>Sometime an <term>Allegorie</term> is mixt with some words retaining
                                their proper and usuall signification, whereof this may be an
                                example: Why doest thou covet the frute, and not consider the height
                                of the tree whereon it groweth? thou doest not forethinke of the
                                difficultie in climbing, nor danger in reaching, wherby it cometh to
                                passe that while thou endevorest to climbe to the top, thou fallest
                                with the bough which thou doest embrace. This <term>Allegorie</term>
                                describeth although somewhat obscurely, yet verie aptly, the danger,
                                vanitie, and common reward of ambition. The words which retaine
                                their proper sense are these, covet, consider, and forethinke, which
                                words do make it a mixt <term>Allegorie</term>. </p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="2"> <head>The use of this figure</head>

                            <p>The use of an <term>Allegorie</term> serveth most aptly to ingrave
                                the lively images of things, and to present them under deepe
                                shadowes <note place="marg" anchored="false">1.Shadowed
                                    description.</note>to the comtemplation of the mind, wherein wit
                                and indigement take pleasure, and the remembrance receiveth a long
                                lasting <note place="marg" anchored="false">2.Compared to a
                                    constellation.</note>impressin, and there as a
                                    <term>Metaphore</term> may be compared to a starre in respect of
                                beautie, brightnesse and direction: so may an <term>Allegorie</term>
                                be fitly likened to a signe compounded of many stars, which of the
                                Grecians is called Astron, and of the Latines Sidus, which we may
                                call a constellation, that is, a company or conjunction of many
                                starres. </p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="3"> <head>The Caution.</head>

                            <p>In speaking by <term>Allegories</term> strange similitudes and
                                    unknowne<note place="marg" anchored="false">Similitudes.</note>
                                translations ought to be avoyded, lest the <term>Allegorie</term>
                                which should<note place="marg" anchored="false">1.Strange.</note> be
                                pleasant, become peevish and altogether unprofitable: also <note place="marg" anchored="false">2.Unlike.</note> unlikenesse of the
                                comparisons do make the <term>Allegorie</term> absurd. </p>
                        </div>
                    </div>

                    <div type="textpart" subtype="subpart" n="2"> <head><term>AEnigma</term></head>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="1">

                            <p><term>AEnigma</term> a kind of <term>Allegorie</term>, differeing
                                onely in obscuritie,<note place="marg" anchored="false">1.A kinde of
                                        <term>Allegorie</term>.</note> for <term>AEnigma</term> is a
                                sentence or forme of speech, which for the darknesse, the sense may
                                hardly be gathered. </p>
                            <p>Examples: I consume my mother that bare me I eat up my nurse that fed
                                me, then I die leaving them all blind that saw me. Meant of the
                                fleame of a candle, which when it hath consumed both ware and weeke,
                                goeth out, leaving them in the darke which saw by it. </p>
                            <p>Another: As long as I live I eate, but when I drinke I die, I
                                understood of the fire, which continueth so long as it hath matter
                                to burne upon, except it be quenched with fire, which may be tearmed
                                the death of that nature. </p>
                            <p><note place="marg" anchored="false">1.A tree the mother.</note>{Ten
                                thousand children beautifull, of this my body bred, {Both sonnes and
                                daughters finely deckt, I live, &amp; they are dead: <note place="marg" anchored="false">2.Fruite the sonnes.</note>{My
                                sonnes were put to extreme death by such as lov'd thee well, <note place="marg" anchored="false">3.Leaves the daughters.</note>{My
                                daughters died in extreme age, but where I cannot tell. </p>
                            <p>Another. </p>
                            <p><note place="marg" anchored="false">1.A book the
                                anatomie.</note>{Anatomie of wonder great I speake, and yet am dead,
                                    <note place="marg" anchored="false">2.Wisedome the
                                ivyee.</note>{Men sucke sweet juyce, from thse blacke veines, which
                                mother wisdome bred. <note place="marg" anchored="false">3.Black veins
                                    the letters &amp; lines.</note>
                            </p>

                            <p>This figure although it be full of obscuritie, and darknesse yet it
                                is found in the sacred Scriptures both in speech and in visions, the
                                dreames of Pharaos chiefe Butler, and chief Baker, and also Pharaos
                                owne dreames were <term>AEnigmatical</term>, whose signification
                                Joseph expounded. </p>
                            <p>Also the vision of Nabuchodonozor was <term>AEnigmatical</term>,
                                &amp; most aptly proportioned in the similitudes, for under the
                                forme of a goodly tree, both him selfe and all the parts of his
                                prosperitie are most excellently described. By the place where it
                                was planted, were described his seate and kingdome: by the height,
                                his dignitie: by the ample aspect, his great glory, and dread of
                                nations toward him: by the strength of that tree, his great power:
                                by the beautifull leaves, his gorgeous apparell and glorious pompe:
                                by the frute, his wonderfull rents, tributes, and revenues: by the
                                meate of that tree, the wealth and prosperitie of his people: by the
                                shadow, the safe protection of his subjects: by the birds among the
                                branches, his prudent counsellers, and mightie princes: and by that,
                                that it is said, that all flesh did eate of it, is understood the
                                great plentie of all necessaries, hitherto is described the
                                wonderfull felicitie and glorie of this mightie Monarch. </p>

                            <p>And now in like manner, the overthrow and confusion of all this is
                                proclaimed by the Angel, saying as followeth, Hew down the tree,
                                breake off his brances, and scatter his frute abrode, that the
                                beasts may get them away from udner his, &amp; the birds from his
                                brancees, nevertheless leave the stumpe in the earth, &amp; c. The
                                meaning whereof Daniel by divine grace expounded. </p>
                        </div>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="2"> <head>The use of this figure.</head>

                            <p>This figure is more convenient to Poets then to Orators, and<note place="marg" anchored="false">1.Most meet for Poets.</note> more
                                agreeable to high and heavenly visions, that to the forme of
                                familiar and proper speech. For being a figure of deepe<note place="marg" anchored="false">2.Used in heavenly visions.</note>
                                obscuritie, is is opposed to perspecuitie, the principall vertue of
                                an Orator.<note place="marg" anchored="false">3.Opposed to
                                    perspicuitie.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>Sometime notwithstanding darknesse of speech causeth delectation, as
                                that which is wittily invented, and aptly applyed, and<note place="marg" anchored="false">4.Being wittie it delighteth.</note>
                                apt capacities, who are best able to find out the sense of a
                                similitude, and to uncover the darked vaile of
                                    <term>AEnigmatical</term> speech. For <note place="marg" anchored="false">5.Compared to a mine.</note> in deede this figure
                                is like a deepe mine, the obtaining of whose mettall requireth deepe
                                digging, or to a darke night, whose stars<note place="marg" anchored="false">6.To hidde starres.</note> he hid with thicke
                                cloudes. </p>
                        </div>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="3"> <head>The Caution.</head>

                            <p>In this figure regard ought to be had, that the similitudes be
                                    not<note place="marg" anchored="false">1.Unfit.</note> unfit,
                                strange, or unchast. If they be unfit, or unlike, they make<note place="marg" anchored="false">2.Strange.</note> it absurd, if
                                strange, they make it obscure and unpossible to be<note place="marg" anchored="false">3.Unchast.</note> interpreted, if unchast or
                                uncleane, they make it odious, by leading<note place="marg" anchored="false">1.Absurd.</note> of the minde to undecent things,
                                of which sort there be many of <note place="marg" anchored="false">2.Obscure.</note> our English riddles.<note place="marg" anchored="false">3.Odious.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>Lastly, that this figure be not used to seduce by obscure prophecie,
                                    <note place="marg" anchored="false">4.Not to seduce.</note> as of
                                it hath bene to many a mans destruction, nor amongst<note place="marg" anchored="false">5.Used among ignorant person a
                                    vanitie.</note> simple and silly persons, which are unapt and
                                unable to conceive the meaning of darke speech, and therefore a
                                vanitie. </p>
                        </div>
                    </div>


                    <div type="textpart" subtype="subpart" n="3"> <head><term>Paroemia</term></head>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="1">

                            <p><term>Paroemia</term>, called of us a <term>Proverbe</term>, is a
                                sentence or forme of speech much used, and commonly knowen, and also
                                excellent for the similitude and signification: to which two things
                                are necessarily required, the one, that it be renowned, and much
                                spoken off, as a sentence in everie mans mouth. The other, that it
                                be witty, and well proportioned, whereby it may be discerned by some
                                speciall marke and note from common speech, and be commended by
                                antiquitie and learning. </p>
                            <p>Examples. </p>
                            <p>The tumbling stone doth seldome gather mosse: teaching that riches
                                and wealth are not gathered by wandering. </p>
                            <p>He that maketh his fire with hay, hath much smoke and litle heate:
                                meaning that many words and litle matter, make men wearie but never
                                the iser. </p>
                            <p>All are not theeves that dogges barke at: declaring that ill tongues
                                do as well slander good men, as speake truth of the evil. </p>
                            <p>One swallow maketh no sommer, that is, one uncertaine conjecture
                                proveth no veritie. </p>
                            <p>While the grasse groweth the steed starveth: signifying that present
                                neede requireth present helpe. </p>
                            <p>The sweetest rose hath his thorne, meaning the best man is not
                                without his fault. </p>
                            <p>It is good to strike with the hammer while the iron is hote: a
                                    <term>proverbe</term> commending the benefit and goodnesse of
                                oportunitie. </p>
                            <p>Many drops do pierce the marble stone: a singular
                                    <term>proverbe</term> declaring the vertue of constancie and
                                continuance. </p>
                        </div>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="2"> <head>The use of this figure.</head>

                            <p>Amongst all the excellent formes of speech there are none other more
                                briefe, more significant, more evident or more excellent, then apt
                                    <term>Proverbs</term>: for what figure of speech is more fit to
                                    <note place="marg" anchored="false">1.The praise or commendation
                                    of <term>Proverbs</term>.</note> teach, more forcible to
                                perswade, more wise to forewarne, more sharpe to reprove, more
                                strong to confirme, or more piercing to imprint? Briefly, they are
                                most profitable, and most pleasant, &amp; may well be called, The
                                Summaries of maners, or The Images of humane life: for in them there
                                is contained a generall doctrine of direction, and particular rules
                                for all duties in all persons. Finally, for thier perspecuitie they
                                are like the most bright <note place="marg" anchored="false">2.Compared to the brightest starres.</note> and glorious
                                starres of the firmament, which as they are more excellent then
                                others in brightnesse and glorie, so are they more loelied upon,
                                more admired, and more beloved, and as they excell others in the
                                dignitie of light, so are they more distantly removed and more
                                thinly dispersed. In like maner ought <term>Proverbes</term> to be
                                sparingly sprinkled, both in private speech, and in publicke<note place="marg" anchored="false">To be sparingly used.</note>
                                orations, and then not without some fit occasion to use them, for
                                    <note place="marg" anchored="false">Too often used looseth their
                                    grace.</note>
                                <term>proverbs</term> being fitly applyed and duly placed, do extend
                                their power and shew their dignitie: otherwise they loose their
                                grace, and the oration his strength. </p>
                        </div>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="3"> <head>The Caution</head>

                            <p>There are diverse vices which ought to be avoyded &amp; banished out
                                of <term>Proverbs</term>, strangenesse, unlikenesse, uncomelinesse,
                                barrennesse, and untruth. Strange <term>Proverbes</term> are those
                                which <note place="marg" anchored="false">1.Strange.</note>are either
                                framed by similitudes of strange things little known or taken from
                                strange tongues disagreeing to ours, when the <term>Proverbes</term>
                                be translated. </p>
                            <p>Unlike <term>Proverbs</term> be those which are made of unfit
                                    similitudes.<note place="marg" anchored="false">2.Unlikke.</note>
                                Uncomely <term>Proverbs</term> are such as consist of wanton,
                                unchast, and <note place="marg" anchored="false">3.Uncomely.</note>
                                vile similitudes, which proceed for the most part from unchast minds
                                and polluted mouthes. </p>
                            <p>Barren <term>Proverbs</term> are those which containe no pith or
                                    virtue,<note place="marg" anchored="false">4.Barren.</note>
                                whereby they should teach and delight. </p>
                            <p>Untrue and fasle <term>Proverbes</term> are such, as many instances
                                    may<note place="marg" anchored="false">5.Untrue.</note> reprove.
                            </p>
                        </div>
                    </div>

                    <div type="textpart" subtype="subpart" n="4"> <head><term>Hyperbole</term>.</head>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="1">

                            <p><term>Hyperbole</term> of Cicero called <term>Superlatio</term>, of
                                Quintilian <term>Superiectio</term>, and it is a sentence or saying
                                surimounting the truth onely for the cause of increasing or
                                diminishing, not with purpose to deceive by speaking untruly, but
                                with desire to amplifie the greatnesse or smalnesse of things by the
                                exceeding similitude. </p>
                            <p>This figure Cicero useth much in the praises of Pompey, He hath made
                                saith he (meaning Pompey) moe battels then others have read, and
                                conquered moe provinces then others have desired. Now in this
                                excesse of his praise, Cicero meant not so much as he spake, but by
                                making an incredible report, he doth signifie that the noble actes
                                of Pompey were so worthy, and his victories so many, that they were
                                almost incredible. </p>
                            <p>This figure is either simple or compared. Simple, as to call the
                                belly of a great glutton bottomlesse him that is most hastie in his
                                furie braineless, a notable coward hearlesse: who knoweth not that
                                the meaning of thse sayings is otherwise than the words do properly
                                expresse? For by this kinde of large speech the excesse of those
                                vices are aptly signfified. </p>
                            <p>Another example: Streames of teares gushed out of her eyes, and the
                                greatnesse of her griefe rent her heart in sunder. Here by these
                                incredible reports, her incredible lamentation and sorrow is
                                signified. </p>
                            <p>This forme of speech is found in the sacred Scriptures, and that in
                                many places. Examples: <cit>
                                    <quote>David saith, that his eye is consumed for very
                                        heavinesse, and that his bones are putrified for the sorrow
                                        of his sinne.</quote>
                                    <bibl>Psal.31.10.11.</bibl>
                                </cit>
                            </p>
                            <p>Job saith, that <cit>
                                    <quote>his feare was so great, that it did terrifie his <note place="marg" anchored="false">Job.4.14.</note> bones, and
                                        made them to tremble.</quote>
                                    <bibl>Job.4.14.</bibl>
                                </cit>
                            </p>
                            <p>And in another place, he saith ye <cit>
                                    <quote>his bones did cleane to the skin.</quote>
                                    <bibl>Job.19.20.</bibl>
                                </cit>
                            </p>
                            <p>Also Paule saith to the Galathians, <cit>
                                    <quote>If it had bene possible you would have plucked out your
                                        own eyes &amp; given them to me.</quote>
                                    <bibl>Gal.4.15.</bibl>
                                </cit>
                            </p>
                            <p><term>Hyperbole</term> is compared two maner of wayes. First by
                                equalitie of comparison, as, to call a beautifull virgine an Angell,
                                a good man a Saint, a shrew a devill, a drunkard a swine, an
                                executioner a wolfe. </p>
                            <p>Secondly by the comparative degree, &amp; that from many places. </p>

                            <p>1 First from like things, as sweeter then hony, whiter then snow,
                                lighter then smoke, heavier then lead. </p>
                            <p>2 Secondly from living creatures, as swifter then the swallow, slower
                                then the snaile, more loving then the turtle, more odious then the
                                toade. </p>
                            <p>3 Thirdly from fained and false gods, as, mightier then Mars, fairer
                                then Venus, wiser then Pallas, more eloquent then Mercurie. </p>
                            <p>4 Fourthly from persons fained in fables, as wearier then Sisiphus,
                                thirstier then Tantalus, more chast then Penelope, more foolish then
                                Grillus. </p>
                            <p>5 Fiftly from persons in Comedies, as, more glorious then Thraso,
                                more covetous then Mitio. </p>
                            <p>6 Sixtly from persons in histories, as, more envious then Zoilus,
                                more unkind then Timon, richer Craesus, poorer then Codrus, stronger
                                then Milo. </p>
                            <p>7 Seventhly from Nations, as more cruell then a Scithian, more false
                                then a Cretian, more wanton then a Miletian. </p>
                            <p>8 Eightly from dignities, offices, and conditions of life, as, more
                                stately then an Emperour, more vigilant then the watchman, more base
                                then a swineheard, more vaine then a vice, more hated then a
                                hangman. </p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="2"> <head>The use of this figure.</head>

                            <p>The use hereof serveth most fitly for amplification, and that<note place="marg" anchored="false">1.To amplify.</note> especially when
                                matter require either to be amplified in the greatest degree, or
                                diminished in the least: by this figure the <note place="marg" anchored="false">2.To diminish.</note>Orator either lifteth up
                                high or calleth downe low, either stretcheth things to the uttermost
                                length, or presseth them to the least quantitie: so high is the
                                reach, &amp; so wide is the compasse of this figure, <note place="marg" anchored="false">3. Of large capacitie</note> that it
                                mounteth to the highest things, compasseth the widest, and
                                comprehendeth the greatest. </p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="3">
 <head>The Caution.</head>

                            <p>Two things especially are here to be noted and avoyded, the one, that
                                this figure be not used to amplifie trifles, or <note place="marg" anchored="false">1.Amplifying of trifles.</note> diminish the
                                estimation of good things, by the one it becometh a vice of speech
                                called <term>Bomphiologia</term>, by the other it is turned into
                                    <note place="marg" anchored="false">2.Defacing of good
                                    things.</note><term>Tapinosis</term>: for these two are faults
                                of speech offending in contrary extremities. The other, that albeit
                                matters require (and that worthily) to be amplified, that yet there
                                be not too great an excesse in the <note place="marg" anchored="false">3.Excesse of comparison.</note> comparison: but that it may be
                                discreetly moderated, ut nequid nimis. </p>
                        </div>
                    </div>

                    <div type="textpart" subtype="subpart" n="5"> <head><term>Asteismus</term>.</head>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="1">

                            <p><term>Asteisimus</term>, in Latine <term>Urbanitas</term>, is a
                                wittie jesting in civill maner, and gracing of speech with some
                                merie conceipt: it is usually taken for any mirth or pleasant speech
                                which is voyd of rusticall simplicitie &amp; rudenesse, and the
                                merie &amp; pleasant sayings of this figure are called
                                    <term>facetiae</term> that is to say, the pleasures and delights
                                of speech: which are taken <note place="marg" anchored="false">1.<term>AEquivocation</term>.</note> from diverse places,
                                but chiefly from these, from <term>Equivocation</term>, as when a
                                word having two significations, is expressed in the one, and
                                understood in the other, either contrary, or at least much
                                differing, which as it is most wittie, so is it most pleasant.
                                Secondly the occasion of mirth may be taken from a
                                    <term>fallace</term> in sophistrie <note place="marg" anchored="false">2.<term>Secundum quid, ad dictum
                                        simpliciter</term>.</note> called <term>Secundum quid ad
                                    dictum simpliciter</term>, that is, when a saying is captiously
                                taken, and turned to another sense, contrary or much differing from
                                the meaning of the speaker, as in this example: To one demanding of
                                Diogenes what he would take for<note place="marg" anchored="false">Diogenes answer.</note> a knocke upon his pate, he made this
                                answer, that he would take an helmet. Now he that made the demand,
                                meant, what hire, and not what defence. To one that said, he knew
                                not if he should be put out of his house where to hid his head:
                                another made him answer, that he might hide it in his cap. </p>
                            <p>There are many and sundry other places from whence wittie mirth may
                                be fitty taken, as from pleasant imitation of mens speech and
                                fashions, from similitudes and comparisons, from pleasant reports of
                                merrie actions and accidents, and from anie moe which I shall not
                                here meede to rehearse. Now for to give to every particular place an
                                example, it would be too tedious, and peradventure to some
                                offensive. He that desireth further examples of this figure, let him
                                reade Facetias Brusonii, Poggii, Bebelii, and Apophthegmata Erasmi
                                Roterodami, Licosthenis, and other moe authors handling the like
                                argument. </p>
                        </div>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="2"> <head>The use of this figure.</head>

                            <p>The use hereof is pleasant and commendable, especially among good
                                wittes, and men of merrie and delightful natures, but yet more meete
                                for private companie, then publike orations, if it be discreetly
                                used with the due observation of circumstances, as place, time,
                                persons, causes, and occasions, it ministreth grace, and pleasure,
                                and mirth to the hearer, wherby the time is pleasantly passed, and
                                the dull and wearisome minds of men are much refreshed. </p>
                        </div>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="3"> <head>The Caution.</head>

                            <p>Heede in the use of this figure ought to be taken, that it offend not
                                against charitie, chastitie, nor pietie. It offendeth <note place="marg" anchored="false">1.Against charitie.</note>against
                                charitie, when the mirth toucheth some person to his griefe or
                                shame, whereby he is moved to take it in evill part. It <note place="marg" anchored="false">2.Against Chastitie.</note>
                                offendeth against chastity, when the testing consisteth of unchast
                                speech, or containeth uncchast significations, which albeit it may
                                move laughter, yet it offendeth modest and chast minds: it
                                committeth a great offence against pietie, when the occasion of
                                mirth &amp; laughter is taken from ye abuse of reverend matters, as
                                the holy <note place="marg" anchored="false">3.Against
                                pietie.</note>scriptures, the judgements of God, magistrates,
                                parents, &amp; such like, or when sport is made at the miseries and
                                calamities of men: by all which abuses Almightie God is provoked to
                                displeasure and wrath, which in justice is wont to revenge al
                                insolency &amp; impietie. </p>
                        </div>
                    </div>

                    <div type="textpart" subtype="subpart" n="6"> <head><term>Ironia</term></head>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="1">

                            <p><term>Ironia</term> called of the Latines <term>Dissimulatio</term>
                                and <term>Irriso</term>, and of some Illusio, it is a Trope in which
                                one contrarie is understood by another, not so well perceived by the
                                words, as either by the pronunciation, by the person, or by the
                                nature of the thing. <term>Antiphrasis</term> and this are of very
                                nigh affinitie, onely differing in this, that
                                    <term>Antiphrasis</term> consisteth in the contrarie sense of a
                                word, and <term>Ironia</term>of a sentence. </p>
                            <p>An example from a Poet: Gnato speaketh thus to Thraso, what <note place="marg" anchored="false">Teren.Andr.</note>(quoth he) they
                                knew not you after I had shewed them your good conditicions, and
                                made mention of your vertues. Then answered Thraso. You did like an
                                honest man, I thanke you with all my heart. Here both the saying of
                                Gnato, and the answer of Thraso, hath a contrary signification. </p>
                            <p>This figure of some is devided to be godly, and wicked, that is,
                                according to the matter or end, not according to the forme, for the
                                forme remaineth the same. </p>
                            <p>Of a godly vertuous <term>Ironia</term>, they give these examples:
                                And the Lord God said, <cit>
                                    <quote>Behold, the man is become as one of us, to know good and
                                        evill</quote>
                                    <bibl>Gen.3.12.</bibl>
                                </cit>: by this derision the Lord God reprocheth Admans miserie,
                                whereinto he was fallen by ambition. </p>
                            <p>Another: <cit>
                                    <quote>Go and crie unto the gods which you have chosen, let them
                                        save you in the time of your tribulation.</quote>
                                    <bibl>Iudic.10.14</bibl>
                                </cit>
                            </p>
                            <p>Another: <cit>
                                    <quote>Sleepe on and take your rest.</quote>
                                    <bibl>Mat.26.45.</bibl>
                                </cit> This saying Christ speaketh in a contrary sense, meaning that
                                trouble was nigh at hand to waken them out of their securitie. </p>
                            <p>The <term>Ironia</term> of Elias is commonly knowne and most evident.
                                    <bibl>1.Reg.18.27.</bibl>
                            </p>
                            <p>Of a wicked <term>Ironia</term>there is an example of Michol saying
                                to David. <cit>
                                    <quote>O how glorious was the king of Israell this day.</quote>
                                    <bibl>2.Sam.6.20.</bibl>
                                </cit>
                            </p>
                        </div>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="2"> <head>The use of this figure.</head>

                            <p><note place="marg" anchored="false">1.To reprove and rebuke.</note>
                                This figure pertaineth chiefly to reprove by derision and illusion,
                                    <note place="marg" anchored="false">2.To jest.</note>and also to
                                jest and move mirth by opposing contraries. </p>
                        </div>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="3"> <head>The Caution.</head>

                            <p><note place="marg" anchored="false">1.Not to be used without urgent
                                    cause.</note>It ought to be foreseene, that this figure be not
                                used to illude without some urgent cause, or to jest without some
                                fit occasion, nor often used, lest he that useth it be either taken
                                for a common mocker, or else for such a one, as men can not tell how
                                to understand him, or when to beleeve him. Neither is it a meete
                                forme of speech for every sort of people to use, especially of the
                                inferior toward the superior, to whom by some reason he oweth dutie,
                                for it <note place="marg" anchored="false">2.Unseemely for an
                                    inferiour.</note> is against the rule of modestie and good
                                maners, either to deride his better, or to jest with im in this
                                forme and maner. </p>
                        </div>
                    </div>

                    <div type="textpart" subtype="subpart" n="7"> <head><term>Charientismus</term>.</head>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="1">
                            <p><term>Charientismus</term> is a trope of speech which mitigateth hard
                                matters with pleasant words. </p>
                            <p>An example: A certaine man being apprehended, and brought before
                                Alexander the Great king of Macedonia, for rayling aginst him, and
                                being demanded of Alexander why he and his companie had so done,
                                made this answer, had not the fayled (sayth he) we had spoken much
                                worse. By which answer he signified, that those words proceeded
                                rather from wine then malice: by which free and pleasant confession,
                                he asswaged Alexanders great displeasure, and obtained forgivenesse. </p>
                            <p>Salomon commendeth that <cit>
                                    <quote>answer which may turne away displeasure, and pacifie
                                        wrath.</quote>
                                    <bibl>Prov.15.</bibl>
                                </cit>
                            </p>
                        </div>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="2">

                            <p>The benefit of this figure is great and necessaire, for it <note place="marg" anchored="false">1.Compared to a salve, &amp; to a
                                    medicin.</note> standeth as it were in sted of a salve to heale
                                the wounds of displeasure, or in place of a vertuous medicine to
                                stanch the bleeding vaines of unkindness, or to coole the boyling
                                inflammation of revenge, for which respects it may well be compared
                                to the wind called Favonius, which by his warme and nourishing
                                breath, <note place="marg" anchored="false">2.Compared to the West
                                    Wind.</note> appeaseth the displeasure of all creatures,
                                conceived against ye same Element, when it puffed out his cold and
                                bitter blastes from the contrary coast called Subsolanus. </p>
                        </div>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="3"> <head>The Caution.</head>

                            <p>Two great faults may be committed in this figure, the one is<note place="marg" anchored="false">1.A base submission.</note> a base
                                and vile submission, the other is open flatterie; the one is a
                                shame, the other a sinne.<note place="marg" anchored="false">2.Open
                                    flatterie.</note>
                            </p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div type="textpart" subtype="subpart" n="8"> <head><term>Sarcasmus</term>.</head>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="1">

                            <p>Sarcasmus is a bitter kind of derision, most commonly used of an
                                enemie. An example: Demothenes taketh upon him (quoth Demades) to
                                correct me, what? Sus Mineruam? That same Minerva (quoth
                                Demosthenes) was the last yeare taken in adulterie. He objecteth
                                adulterie to Demades forasmuch as the Poets make Minerva a virgine. </p>
                            <p>Another: When M. Appius in his prooeme declared that he was earnestly
                                intreated of a friend, that he should use his didligence eloquence
                                and fedeltitie in the cause of his client. After all the plea ended,
                                Cicero comming to Appius, sayd thus unto him, Are you so hard a man
                                (saith he) that of so many things which your friend did request, you
                                would performe none? </p>
                            <p>An example of the holy Scripture: <cit>
                                    <quote>Sing us one of your songs of Sion.</quote>
                                    <bibl>Psal. 137.</bibl>
                                </cit> This saying was uttered in scornful and insulting manner
                                against the poore Israelites being captives in Babylon. </p>
                            <p>Another: <cit>
                                    <quote>Thou which doest destroy the Temple, and build it againe
                                        in three dayes, save thy self and come down from ye
                                        crosse.</quote>
                                    <bibl>Mar.15.</bibl>
                                </cit>
                            </p>
                            <p>Another: He saved other, him selfe he cannot save. </p>
                            <p>Let that Christ the king of Israell come downe now from the crosse,
                                that we may see and beleeve him. These examples of the Jewes against
                                Christ are here set down to teach the forme of this figure, and not
                                to confirme the abuse. </p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="2"> <head>The use of this figure.</head>

                            <p><note place="marg" anchored="false">1.To represse pride, follie, &amp;
                                    rudenesse.</note>The best &amp; most lawfull use of this
                                    <term>Trope</term> is to represse proud folly and wicked
                                insolencie, and sometime leud miserie: for indeed this figure is
                                like to most bitter corrections in Phisicke,<note place="marg" anchored="false">2.Compared to bitter corrections.</note> which
                                are seldome or never applyed, but to vehement and desperat diseases,
                                which although they be painfull and bitter, yet for the most part
                                they bring profit, as by removing the diseases, and restoring
                                health: even so the benefit of an enemies mocke to a wise man, is
                                the knowledge of his fault, and the amending of it. </p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="3"> <head>The Caution.</head>

                            <p><note place="marg" anchored="false">1.Not to be used without a needful
                                    cause.</note>Let it be first provided that this figure be not
                                used without some great cause which may well deserve it, as
                                arrogancie, insolent pride, wilfull folly, shamefull lecherie,
                                ridiculous avarice, or such like, for it is both folly and rudenesse
                                to use derision <note place="marg" anchored="false">2.Folly and
                                    rudenesse.</note> without cause: but to mocke silly people,
                                innocents, or men in misery, or the poore in distresse, argueth both
                                the pride of the mind,<note place="marg" anchored="false">3.Pride and
                                    crueltie.</note> and the crueltie of the heart: which evils and
                                wicked properties, being mae knowne by wicked practise, the scorner
                                and common mocker becommeth odious to all men. </p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div type="textpart" subtype="subpart" n="9"> <head><term>Mycterismus</term>.</head>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="1">

                            <p><term>Mycterismus</term> is a privie kind of mocke, or maner of
                                jesting, yet not so privie but that it may well be perceived. </p>
                            <p>An example: When a certaine man which was bald had spitefully rayled
                                against Diogenes, after a litle pawse Diogenes answered him thus: My
                                friend, farther I have done thee no harme, but this I must say to
                                thee, I do much commend the haires that are fallen from thy head,
                                for I suppose they were wise, in that they made hast to leave the
                                companie of so foolilsh a scull. </p>
                            <p>Another: To one that demanded of Demonax the philosopher, if
                                Philosophers did use to eate sweet cakes, Demonax made this answer,
                                Doest thou think (quoth he) that bees gather their hony for fooles
                                onely? </p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="2"> <head>The use of this figure</head>

                            <p>The use hereof differeth not much from the use of
                                    <term>Sarcasmus</term>,<note place="marg" anchored="false">1.The
                                    difference between this figure &amp;
                                    <term>Sarcasmus</term>.</note> but in this, that
                                    <term>Sarcasmus</term> is more manifest, and this more privie,
                                that more generall, and this more speciall, that more easie, and
                                this more hard. The chiefe use of this figure serveth to <note place="marg" anchored="false">2.To represse pride, folly, and
                                    vice.</note>represse pride, rebuke folly, and taunt vice: and
                                may be likened to a black frost, which is wont to nip a man by the
                                nose, before he<note place="marg" anchored="false">3.Compared to the
                                    frost.</note> can discerne it with his eye. </p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="3"> <head>The Caution.</head>

                            <p>This figure must not be too obscure and darke, for by that it may
                                loose the vertue and use, if it be not perceived, and<note place="marg" anchored="false">1.Not too obscure.</note> therefore
                                it is not to be used to simple and ignorant persons, which do <note place="marg" anchored="false">2.Not rusticall.</note>want the
                                capacitie &amp; subtlety of wit to perceive it. Neither must it be
                                rude or rusticall, which is the utter disgrace of it. </p>
                        </div>
                    </div>

                    <div type="textpart" subtype="subpart" n="10"> <head><term>Diasyrmus</term>.</head>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="1">

                            <p><term>Dyasyrmus</term> is a Trope by which the arguments of an
                                adversarie are either deraved or rejected. Cicero for Murena against
                                Cato, speaketh much in this manner, and also against Sulpitius
                                disputing in the Civill law. </p>
                            <p>This figure is for the most part made either by some base similitude,
                                or by some ridiculous example, to which the adversaries objection or
                                argument is compared, whereby it is either made ridiculous, or at
                                least much disgraced. </p>
                            <p>As for to shew examples of this figure I judge it needlesse and
                                superfluous, considering the dayly plentie of them almost everie
                                where, both private and publike: and therefore it may suffise to
                                shew the use, and forewarne the abuse of it. </p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="2"> <head>The use of this figure.</head>

                            <p><note place="marg" anchored="false">1.To make an evasion.</note>The
                                most lawfull and commendable use of this <term>Trope</term>, is
                                either to make an evasion out of the subtle snare of a captious
                                argument, or to reject such objections as are curious, foolish,
                                    or<note place="marg" anchored="false">2.To abate the pride of a
                                    proud adversarie.</note> obscure, or to abate the pride and
                                arrogancie of a proude and insolent disputer. </p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="textpart" subtype="subsubpart" n="3"> <head>The Caution.</head>

                            <p><note place="marg" anchored="false">1.Where it ought not to be
                                    used.</note>The especiall warning that is to be observed in this
                                figure is, that in all grave and weightie controversies it ought to
                                keepe silence, as in solemne disputations, &amp; judiciall
                                pleadings, except there be the greater cause to urge it. In grave
                                disputations it is unseemely, and in law pleadings injurious, in
                                both it may outface the truth, or at least hinder it. And therefore
                                it were to be wished that the abuse of this figure might be banished
                                from the barre of pleading, and presence of the judgement seate,
                                where the truth ought alwayes to be supported and not suppressed,
                                for the by the <note place="marg" anchored="false">2.The effects of
                                    the abuse.</note>abuse of this figure, good causes may be
                                scorned, honest persons disgraced, and true testimonies depraved.
                            </p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
  
        
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
