<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd"[
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Dictionaries//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
	<title>The Processe of Irish Affaires</title>
	<title>An Electronic Edition</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
	&Holinshed.publicationStmt;
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
	&Ellis.sourceDesc;
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl>
	<state n="chunk" unit="chronicle"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>

    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
	<language id="en">English</language>
	<language id="la">Latin</language>
	<language id="greek">Greek</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
	<date>3/25/03</date>
	<respStmt>
	  <name>cew</name><resp>ed</resp>
	</respStmt>
	<item>The Process broken out</item>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
      <text> <!-- Processe of Irish Affaires -->
	<front>
	  <pb n="233"/>
	  <titlePage>
	    <docTitle>
	      <titlePart>The Processe Of Irish Affaires</titlePart>
	      <titlePart>(Beginning Where Giraldus Did End) Vntill This Present Age, Being A Witnesse Of Sundrie Things As Yet Fresh In Memorie:</titlePart>
	      <titlePart>Which Processe From Henseforward Is Intituled</titlePart>
	      <titlePart>The Chronicles Of Ireland</titlePart>
</docTitle>
	  </titlePage>
	  <div type="preface">
<p>LEAUING at the conquest of Ireland penned by Giraldus
Cambrensis, we are now to proceed in that which followeth:
wherin our authour (as he himselfe writeth) vsed
such notes as were written by one Philip Flatsburie, out of
a certeine namelesse author, from this place vnto the yeare
1370: and we hauing none other helpe besides (except
onelie Henrie of Marleborow) do set downe that which we
find in our oft mentioned authour, and in the same Marleborow
in all the whole discourse that followeth, except in
some certeine particular places, where we shew from whense
we haue drawne that which we write as occasion serueth.
<!--<fw place="bot-left">"VOL. VI."</fw>--><!--<fw place="bot-center">"2 H"</fw>-->
</p>
	  </div>
	</front>
	<body>
	  <head>The Chronicles of Ireland, &amp;c.</head>
	  <pb n="234"/>	<!-- blank verso page -->
	      <head>The Chronicles of Ireland, &amp;c.</head>

<div n="Edward1" type="chronicle">
<p>HUGH de Lacie (of whom such memorable mention is made hertofore) the
rather to m&eacute;et with such hurlie burlies as were like to put the state of the Irish
countrie in danger, if the same were not the sooner brought to quiet, erected and
built a number of castels and forts in places conuenientlie seated, well and sufficientlie
garnished with men, munitions, and vittels, as one at Derwath, where diuerse
<note place="marg">A castell built at Derwath.</note>
of the Irish praied to be set on worke for wages. Lacie came sundrie times
thither to further the woorke, full glad to s&eacute;e them fall in vre with anie such exercise,
wherein might they once begin to haue a delight, and tast the sw&eacute;etnesse of a
true mans life, he thought it no small token of reformation: for which cause he
visited them the oftner, and merilie would command his gentlemen to giue the laborers
example to take their tooles in hand, and to woorke a season, whilest the poore
soules looking on might rest them. But this pastime grew to a tragicall end. For
on a time, as each man was busilie occupied, some lading, some heauing, some
plastering, some grauing, the generall also himselfe digging with a pickaxe: a desperat
villaine among them, whose toole the noble man vsed, espieng both his hands
occupied, and his bodie inclining downwards, still as he stroke watched when he so
<note place="marg"><date>1186</date></note>

<note place="marg">Lacie is traitorouslie slaine.</note>
stooped, and with an axe cleft his head in sunder, little esteeming the torments that
for this traitorous act insued. This Lacie was reputed to be the conqueror of Meth,
for that he was the first that brought it to anie due order of obedience vnto the
English power. His bodie the two archbishops, Iohn of Dublin, and Matthew
of Cashill buried in the monasterie of Bectie, and his head in saint Thomas abbeie
at Dublin.</p>
<p>By occasion of this murther committed on the person of Hugh Lacie, Iohn
Curcie, and Hugh Lacie the yoonger, with their assistants, did streight execution
vpon the rebels; and preuenting euerie mischiefe yer it fell, staied the realme from
vprores. Thus they knitting themselues togither in friendship, continued in wealth
<note place="marg">Curcie and Hugh Lacie the voonger keepe the realme in quiet.</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1199.</date></note>

<note place="marg">King Iohn slaieth his nephue Arthur.</note>
and honor vntill the first yeare of king Iohus reigne, who succ&eacute;eding his brother
king Richard, tooke his nephue Arthur, son to his brother Geffreie earle of Britaine,
and dispatched him (some said) with his owne hands, because he knew what claime
he made to the crowne, as descended of the elder brother. And therefore not
onelie the French king, but also certeine lords of England and Ireland fauored
his title: and when they vnderstood that he was made awaie, they tooke it in maruelous
euill part. And Curcie either of zeale to the truth, or parcialitie, abhorring
<note place="marg">Curcie vttereth displeasant words against King Iohn.</note>
such barbarous crueltie, whereof all mens eares were full, spake bloudie words against
king Iohn, which his lurking aduersaries (that laie readie to vndermine him) caught
<!--<fw place="bot-center">"2 H 2"</fw>--><!--<fw place="bot-right">"by"</fw>-->


<pb n="236"/>

<!--<fw place="top-left">"236"</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>-->


by the end, and vsed the same as a meane to lift him out of credit: which they
did not onelie bring to passe, but also procured a commission to attach his bodie,
and to send him ouer into England. Earle Curcie mistrusting his part, and belike
<note place="marg">He is accused.</note>
getting some inkeling of their drift, kept himselfe aloofe, till Hugh Lacie lord
iustice was faine to leuie an armie and to inuade Vlster, from whense he was oftentimes
put backe: wherevpon he proclaimed Curcie traitor, and hired sundrie gentlemen
<note place="marg">He is proclamed traitor.</note>
with promise of great recompense, to bring him in either quicke or dead.
They fought once at Downe, in which battell there died no small number on both
parts; but Curcie got the vpper hand, and so was the lord iustice foiled at Curcies
hands: but yet so long he continued in practising to haue him, that at length Curcies
owne capteins were inueihed to betraie their owne maister: insomuch that vpon
Good fridaie, whilest the earle out of his armour visited barefooted certeine religious
houses for deuotion sake, they laid for him, tooke him as a rebell, &amp; shipped
him ouer into England the next waie, where he was adiudged to perpetuall prison.
<note place="marg">He is taken.</note>
One Seintleger addeth in his collections (as Campion saith) that Lacie paied the
traitors their monie, and foorthwith therevpon hanged them.</p>
<p>This Curcie translated the church and prebendaries of the trinitie in Downe, to
<note place="marg">Translation of prebendaries to monks.</note>
an abbeie of blacke moonks brought thither from Chester, and caused the same to
be consecrated vnto saint Patrike: for which alteration, taking the name from God
to a creature; he d&eacute;emed himselfe woorthilie punished. Not long after (as saie the
Irish) certeine French knights came to king Iohns court, and one among them required
the combat for triall of the right to the duchie of Normandie. It was not
<note place="marg">A chalenge for a combat made by certeine French knights.</note>
thought expedient to ieopard the title vpon one mans lucke, yet the chalenge they
determined to answer. Some friend put them in mind of the earle imprisoned, a
warrior of notable courage, and in pitch of bodie like a giant. King Iohn demanded
Curcie, whether he could be content to fight in his quarrell? "Not for
<note place="marg">Cureies answer to king Iohn.</note>
thee" said the erle, "whose person I est&eacute;eme vnworthie th'aduenture of my blond,
but for the crowne &amp; dignitie of the realme, in which manie a good man liueth
<note place="marg">He taketh vpon him to defend the chalenge.</note>
against thy will, I shall be contented to hazard my life."</p>
<p>These words were not construed in the worst part, as proc&eacute;eding from an offended
mind of him that was therein est&eacute;emed more plaine than wise. Therefore being
cherished and much made of, he was fed so woonderfullie (now he came to so large
allowance in diet after hard keeping) that the French chalenger tooke him for a monster:
and fearing to deale with him, priuilie stole awaie into Spaine. It is further
reported, that the French king, being desirous to s&eacute;e Curcie, requested king Iohn
that he might come before them, and shew of what strength he was by striking a
blow at an helmet. Herevpon foorth he was brought, and presented before the
kings, where was an helmet set vpon a blocke. Curcie taking a sword in his hand,
and with a sterne &amp; frowning countenance cast vpon the kings, gaue such a stroke
to the helmet, that cleaning it in sunder, the sword sticked so fast in the log, that
no man there was able to plucke it foorth, except Curcie himselfe. When he therefore
had plucked foorth the sword, the kings asked him what he meant to looke vpon
them with such a grim &amp; froward countenance before he gaue the blow to the helmet?
He answered, that if he had missed in his stroke, he would haue killed all
the whole companie, as well the kings as others. Then was he released of bonds,
and crossing the seas towards Ireland whither he was bound, was fift&eacute;ene times beaten
backe againe to the English shore, &amp; going into France to change the coast died
<note place="marg">Curcie departeth this life.</note>

<note place="marg">The description of Curcie.</note>
there. This Curcie was white of colour, mightie of lims, with large bones and
strong of sinews, tall &amp; broad in proportion of bodie, so as his strength was
thought to exc&eacute;ed, of boldnesse incomparable, and a warrior euen from his youth;
the formost in the front of euerie battell where he came, and euer readie to hazard
himselfe in place of most danger, so forward in fight, that oftentimes forgetting the
<!--<fw place="bot-right">"office"</fw>-->


<pb n="237"/>

<!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-right">"237"</fw>-->


office of a capteine, he tooke in hand the part of a souldior, pressing foorth with
the formost, so that with his ouer rash violence, and desire of victorie, he might
s&eacute;eme to put all in danger. But although he was thus hastie and hot in the field
against his enimies, yet was he in conuersation modest and sober, and verie religious,
hauing churchmen in great reuerence, ascribing all to the goodnesse of God,
when he had atchiued anie praise-woorthie enterprise, y&eacute;elding thankes to his diuine
maiestie accordinglie. But as seldome times anie one man is found perfect in
all things, so these vertues were spotted with some vices; namelie, too much nigardnesse
in sparing, and inconstaneie. He maried the daughter of Godred king of
Man, and after manie conflicts and battels had against the Irish, he conquered (as
before ve haue heard) the countrie of Vlster, and building diuerse strong castels
therin, he established the same vnder his quiet rule and gouernment, till he and
Lacie fell out, as before is expressed.</p>
<p>After Curcies decease, because he left no heires, the earledome of Vlster was giuen
vnto Hugh Lacie in recompense of his good seruice. There was one of the Curcies
remaining in Ireland that was lord of Rathermie and Kilbarrocke, whome (as an
espiall of all their practises and informer thereof to the king) Walter and Hugh the
sons of Hugh Lacie slue, by reason whereof great trouble and disquietnesse insued:
those Lacies bearing themselues (now after the decease of their father) for gouernors
out of checke. To set the realme in quiet, king Iohn was faine to passe thither
<note place="marg">King Iohn went into Ireland.</note>
himselfe in person with a maine armie, banished the Lacies, subdued the residue of
the countrie yet not conquered, tooke pledges, punished malefactors, established
<note place="marg">S&eacute;e more hereof in Enland.</note>
the execution of English lawes, coined monie of like value currant sterling in both
realmes. The two Lacies repenting their misdemeanors, fled into France disguised
<note place="marg">They fled into France.</note>
in poore apparell, and serued there in an aboeie as gardeners, till the abbat by their
countenance and behauior began to gesse their estates, and opposed them so farre
that they disclosed what they were; bes&eacute;eching the abbat to keepe their counsels,
who commending their repentant humblenes, aduised them yet to make sute for
their princes fauor, if it might be had, promising to doo what he could in the matter,
and so tooke vpon him to be a suter for them vnto the king that was his godcept
and well acquainted with him. He trauelled so earnestlie herein, that at length
he obteined their pardons: but yet they were fined, Walter at foure thousand, and
<note place="marg">They are pardoned, and put to their fines.</note>
Hugh at fiue and twentie hundred markes: and herevpon Walter was restored vnto
the lordship of Meth, and Hugh to the earledome of Vlster.</p>
<p>King Iohn appointed his lieutenants in Ireland, and returning home, subdued
the Welshmen, and soone after with Pandulfus the legat of pope Innocentius the
third, who came to release him of the censure, wherin he stood excommunicat, to
whom as to the popes legat he made a personall surrender of both realines in waie
of submission; and after he was once absolued, he receiued them againe. Some
adde, that he gaue awaie his kingdoms to the see of Rome for him and his successors,
recognising to hold the same of the popes in f&eacute;e, paieng yearelie therefore
one thousand markes, as seauen hundred for England, and three hundred for Ireland.
<note place="marg">An hundred marks of gold.</note>

<note place="marg"><emph>Blondus.</emph></note>
Blondus saith, "Centum pro vtroque auri marchias." Sir Thomas More
(as Campion saith) a man both in calling &amp; office likelie to sound the matter to
the depth, writeth preciselie, that neither such writing the pope can shew, neither
were it effectuall if he could. How farre foorth, and with what limitation a prince
may or may not addict his realme feodarie to another, Iohn Maior a Scotish chronicler,
and a Sorbonist not vnlearned partlie scanneth, who thinketh three hundred
markes for Ireland no verie hard peniworth. The instrument (as Campion thinketh)
which our English writers rehearse, might happilie be motioned and drawen, and
<note place="marg"><emph>Iohn Bale in bis apologie against vows.</emph></note>
yet not confirmed with anie seale, nor ratified: but though the copie of this writing
remaine in record, yet certeine it is, king Iohns successors neuer paid it. After Iohn
<!--<fw place="bot-right">"Comin"</fw>-->


<pb n="238"/>

<!--<fw place="top-left">"238"</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>-->


Comin archbishop of Dublin, and founder of saint Patriks church succ&eacute;eded Henrie
Londores in the s&eacute;e, who builded the kings castell there, being lord ch&eacute;efe iustice
of Ireland, him they nicknamed (as the Irish doo commonlie giue additions in
respect of some fact or qualitie) Scorchuillein, that is, Burnebill, because he required
to peruse the writings of his tenants, colorablie pretending to learne the
kind of ech mans seuerall tenure, and burned the same before their faces, causing
them either to renew their takings, or to hold at will.</p>
<p>In the yeare one thousand two hundred and sixt&eacute;ene king Iohn departed this
life. In his daies diuerse monasteries were builded in Ireland, as (besides those
that before are mentioned) in the fourth yeare of his reigne the abbeie of
Dowish was founded; in the sixt the abbeie of Wetherham in the countie of Limerike,
by Theobald le Butler lord of Cacrackie, and in the twelfe yeare Richard
Oute builded the monasterie of Grenard. In the daies of Henrie the third that
<note place="marg">Henrie the third.</note>

<note place="marg">Warres betwixt Lacie and Marshall.</note>
succ&eacute;eded his father king Iohn great warres were raised in Ireland betwixt Hugh
Lacie &amp; William Marshall, so that the countrie of Meth was gr&eacute;euouslie afflicted.
In the yeare of our Lord 1228, after the death of Londores archbishop of Dublin,
<note place="marg"><date>1228</date></note>
that was lord ch&eacute;efe iustice, king Henrie the third vnderstanding the good seruice
doone by the Giraldines euer since their first comming into Ireland, although by
<note place="marg">The Giraldines.</note>
wrong reports the same had beene to their preiudice for a time sinisterlie misconstrued,
so as the gentlemen had still b&eacute;ene kept backe, and not rewarded according
to their deserts. The king now informed of the truth made Morice Fitzgerald the
<note place="marg">Morice Fitzgirald.</note>

<note place="marg">Lucas archbishop.</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1230</date></note>
sonne of Morice aforesaid lord ch&eacute;efe iustice of Ireland. Lucas succeeded Londres
in the archbishops s&eacute;e, and was consecrated. In the yeare one thousand two
hundred and thirtie, Richard Marshall was taken prisoner in battell at Kildare.
Some write that he was wounded there, and within few daies after died of the
<note place="marg"><date>1234</date></note>
hurt at Kilkennie, and was buried there in the queere of the church of the friers
preachers, n&eacute;ere to the place where his brother William was interred, who departed
this life in the yeare one thousand two hundred thirtie and one.</p>
<p>In the yeare one thousand two hundred fortie and one, Walter Lacie lord of Meth
<note place="marg"><date>1241</date></note>
departed this life in England: he left two daughters behind him that were his heires,
Margaret married to the lord Verdon, and Matild the wife of Geffrie Genuill.
<note place="marg">The lord Verdon.</note>

<note place="marg">Geffreie Genuill.</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1252</date></note>

<note place="marg"><date>1253</date></note>
King Henrie in the six &amp; thirtith yeare of his reigne, gaue to Edward his eldest
sonne, Gascoigne, Ireland, and the countie of Chester. In the yeare following,
Hugh Lacie earle of Vlster departed this life, and was buried at Cragfergus, in the
church of the friers minors, leaning a daughter behind him, that was his heire,
whome Walter de Burgh or Bourke married, and in right of hir was created earle
of Vlster, as after shall appeare. Morice Fitzgirald lord iustice of Ireland, being
requested by this prince to come and assist him with a power of men against the
Welsh rebels, left a sufficient garrison of men in the castell of Scligath, which he
<note place="marg">The castell of Scligath.</note>
had latelie builded, and then came oner with Phelin Ochonher, and a lustie band of
souldiers: &amp; meeting the prince at Chepstow, behaued themselues so valiantlie,
that returning with victorie, they greatlie increased the fauor of the king and
prince towards them; and vpon their returne into Ireland, they ioined with Cormacke
Mac Dermot Mac Rorie, and made a notable iournie against Odonill the
Irish enimie, that when Lacie was once dead, inuaded &amp; sore annoied the kings
subicets of Vlster. Odonill being vanquished, the lord iustice forced pledges and
<note place="marg">Odonill.</note>
tribute of Oneale to keepe the kings peace, and diuerse other exploits praise-worthic
did he, during the time of his gouernment, as Flatsburie hath gathered in his
notes for the lord Girald Fitzgirald earle of Kildare, in the yeare one thousand fiue
hundred and seuent&eacute;ene. After Morice Fitzgirald succeeded in office of lord iustice,
Iohn Fitzgeffrie knight, and after him Alaine de la Zouch, whome the earle of
<note place="marg">Iohn Fitzgeffrie lord iustice.</note>

<note place="marg">Alaine de la Zouch lord iustice.</note>
Surrie Fitzwarren slue. And after de la Zouch, in the yeare one thousand two hun-
<!--<fw place="bot-right">"dred"</fw>-->


<pb n="239"/>

<!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-right">"239"</fw>-->


dred fiftie and eight, being the two and fortith of Henrie the third his reigne, was
Stephan de long Esp&eacute;e sent to supplie that roome, who slue Oneale with thr&eacute;e hundred
<note place="marg">Stephan de long Esp&eacute;e.</note>

<note place="marg">William Dene lord iustice.</note>

<note place="marg">Gr&eacute;ene castell destroied.</note>

<note place="marg">Mac Carcie.</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1261.</date></note>
fiftie &amp; two of his men in the str&eacute;ets of Downe, and shortlie after departed
this life; then William Dene was made lord iustice, and Gr&eacute;ene castell was destroied.
Also Mac Careie plaid the diuell in Desmond.</p>
<p>In the yeare one thousand two hundred sixtie and one, sir William Dene lord
instice of Ireland deceased, and sir Richard Rochell (or Capell as some copies haue)
<note place="marg">Sir Richard Capell lord iustice.</note>
was sent to be lord iustice after him, who greatlie enuied the familie of the Giraldins;
during his gouernement the lord Iohn Fitzthomas and the lord Morice his
<note place="marg">Lord Iohn Fitzthomas slaine.</note>
son were slaine. In the yeare one thousand two hundred sixtie and foure, Walter
de Burgh was made earle of Vlster, and Morice Fitzmorice tooke the lord iustice
<note place="marg">The lord iustice taken.</note>
of Ireland togither with Theobald Butler, Miles Cogan, and diuerse other great
lords at Tristildermot, on saint Nicholas daie. And so was Ireland full of warres,
betwixt the Burghs and Giraldins. In the yeare one thousand two hundred sixtie
<note place="marg"><date>1266</date></note>

<note place="marg"><date>1267</date></note>
and six, there chanced an earthquake in Ireland. In the yeere following, king
Henrie tooke vp the variance that was in Ireland betwixt the parties, and discharging
Dene, appointed Dauid Barrie lord iustice in his place, who tamed the insolent
<note place="marg">Dauid Barrie lord iustice.</note>
dealings of Morice Fitzmorice, cousine germane to Fitzgirald.</p>
<p>In the yeare one thousand two hundred sixtie and eight, Conhur Obren was
<note place="marg"><date>1263</date></note>
slaine by Dermot Mac Monerd, and Morice Fitzgirald earle of Desmond was
drowned in the sea, betwixt Wales &amp; Ireland. And Robert Vffort was sent ouer
<note place="marg">Robert Vffort.</note>
to remaine lord iustice of Ireland, and Barrie was discharged, who continued till
the yeare one thousand two hundred sixtie and nine, and then was Richard de Excester
<note place="marg">Richard de Excester.</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1270</date></note>

<note place="marg"><date>1271</date></note>
made lord iustice. And in the yeare following, was the lord Iames Audleie
made lord iustice. Richard Verdon, and Iohn Verdon were slaine, and Fulke archbishop
of Dublin deceased. Also the castels of Aldlecke, Roscoman, &amp; Scheligagh,
were destroied. The same yeare was a great dearth and mortulitie in Ireland. In
the yeare one thousand two hundred seuentie &amp; two, the lord Iames Audleie was
<note place="marg">The lord Audleie.</note>

<note place="marg">Randon.</note>

<note place="marg">The decease of king Henrie the third.</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1272</date></note>

<note place="marg">Walter Genuill.</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1275</date></note>
slaine by a fall from his horsse in Thomond, and then was Morice Fitzmorice made
lord iustice of Ireland, and the castell of Randon was destroied. In the yeare one
thousand two hundred seauentie and two, king Henrie the third departed this life,
and the lord Walter Genuill latelie returned home from his iournie into the holie
land, was sent into Ireland, and made lord iustice there. In the yeare one thousand
two hundred seuentie and fiue, the castell of Roscoman was eftsoones repared and
fortified.</p>
<p>In the yeare one thousand two hundred seuentie and six, there was an ouerthrow
<note place="marg"><date>1276</date></note>

<note place="marg">An ouerthrow at Glenburie.</note>
giuen at Glenburie, where William Fitzroger, prior of the knights hospitalers, &amp;
manie other with him, were taken prisoners, and a great number of other were
slaine. The same yeare, Iohn de Verdon departed this world, and Thomas de Clare
maried the daughter of Morice Fitzmorice. In the yeare following, Robert Vffort
was appointed to supplie the roome of Genuill, being called home, and so was
this Vffort the second time ordeined lord iustice of Ireland. He hauing occasion
to passe into England, made his substitute Fulborne bishop of Waterford till his
returne, and then resumed the gouernement into his owne hands againe. In the
yeare one thousand two hundred seauentie and seauen, Thomas de Clare slue Obrenroth
<note place="marg"><date>1277</date></note>
king of Tholethmond: and yet after this the Irish closed him vp in Slewbani,
togither with Maurice Fitzmaurice, so that they gaue hostages to escape, and the
eastell of Roscoman was woone. In the yere next insuing, was Iohn de Derlington
<note place="marg"><date>1278</date></note>
consecrated archbishop of Dublin. There was also a councell holden at
Grenoke, and Mac Dermot slue Cathgur Oconthir king of Connagh. In the
yeare one thousand two hundred seuentie and nine, Robert Vffort vpon occasion of
<!--<fw place="bot-right">"busines"</fw>-->


<pb n="240"/>

<!--<fw place="top-left">"240"</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>-->


busines came ouer into England, and left frier Fulborne bishop of Waterford to supplie
his roome, and Rafe Piphard and Ohaulan chased Oneale in a battell.</p>
<p>In the yeare one thousand two hundred and foure score, Robert Vffort came
<note place="marg"><date>1280</date></note>
the third time to occupie the roome of lord chiefe iustice in Ireland, resuming that
roome into his hands againe. In the yeare following, the bishop of Waterford was
<note place="marg"><date>1281</date></note>
established by the king of England lord iustice of Ireland. Adam Cusacke the
yoonger slue William Barret, and manie other in Connagh. And in the next yeare,
to wit, one thousand two hundred foure score and two, Penqueit slue Murertagh,
&amp; his brother Art Mac Murgh at Athlon. Also the lord Iames de Birmingham, and
Piers de Tute departed this life. Also the archbishop Derlington deceassed. And
about the same time, the citie of Dublin was defaced by fire, and the st&eacute;eple of
Christs church vtterlie destroied. The citizens before they went about to repare
their owne priuat buildings, agreed togither to make a collection for reparing the
<note place="marg">Christ church repared.</note>
ruines of that ancient building first begun by the Danes, and continued by Citrius
prince of Dublin at the instance of Donat sometime bishop of that citie, and dedicated
<note place="marg">Donat bishop of Dublin.</note>
to the blessed trinitie.</p>
<p>At lengh Strangbow earle of Peubroke, Fitzstephans, &amp; Laurence, that for his
vertue was called saint Laurence archbishop of Dublin, and his foure successors,
Iohn of Euesham, Henrie Scortchhill, and Lucas, and last of all Iohn de saint
Paule finished it. This notable building, since the time that it was thus defaced by
fire, hath b&eacute;ne beautified in diuerse sorts by many zealous citizens. Strangbowes
<note place="marg">Strangbows too ne restored by Henrie Sidneie.</note>
toome defaced, by the fall of the roofe of the church, sir Henrie Sidneie, when he
was lord deputie, restore; &amp; likewise did cost vpon the earle of Kildares chappell
for an ornament to the quier, ouer the which he left also a monument of capteine
Randolfe, late coronell of the English bands of footmen in Vlster that died there
<note place="marg">Capteine Randolfe.</note>
valiantlie, fighting in his princes seruice, as after shall appeare. In the yeare one
thousand two hundred foure score and three, Furmund chancellor of Ireland, and
Richard Tute departed this life, and frier Stepiran Fulborne was made lord iustice
of Ireland.</p>
<p>In the yeare 1285, the lord Theobald Butler fled from Dubline, and died shortlie
<note place="marg"><date>1285</date></note>
after, and the lord Theobald Verdon lost his men and horsses as he went towards
Offalie, &amp; the next day Gerald Fitzmaurice was taken, and Iohn Samford was consecrated
<note place="marg">Iohn Samford consecrated archbishop of Dublin.</note>

<note place="marg">An ouerthrow at Rathod.</note>

<note place="marg">Norwagh and Ardscol burnt</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1286</date></note>
archbishop of Dublin. Moreouer at Rathod, the lord Gerfreie Genuill
fled, and sir Gerard Doget, and Rafe Petit were slaine, with a great number of
others. The Norwagh and Ardscoil with other townes and villages were burnt by
Philip Stanton the sixteenth daie of Nouember, in the yeare 1286. Also Calwagh
was taken at Kildare. In the yeare 1287, dinerse nobles in Ireland deceased, as
Richard Decerer, Gerald Fitzmaurice. Thomas de Clare, Richard Taffic, &amp; Nicholas
Teling knights. The yeare next insuing, deceased frier Fulborne lord iustice of
<note place="marg"><date>1288</date></note>

<note place="marg">Samford archbishop of Dublin lord iustice.</note>
Ireland, and Iohn Samford archbishop of Dublin was aduanced to the roome of
lord iustice. Also Richard Burgh earle of Vlster besreged Theobald Verdon in
the castell of Athlon, and came with a great power vnto frim, by the working of
Walter Lacie.</p>
<p>In the yeare 1290, was the chase or discomfiture of Offalie, &amp; diuerse Englishmen
<note place="marg"><date>1290</date></note>
slaine. Also Mac Coghlan slue Omolaghelin king of Meth, and William
Burgh was discomfited at Deluin by Mac Coghlan. The same yeare 1290, William
Vescie was made lord iustice of Ireland, and entered into that office on S. Martins
<note place="marg">William Vescie lord iustice.</note>
daie. Vnto this iustice, Edward Balioil king of Scotland did homage for an earledome
which he held in Ireland, in like maner as he did to king Edward for the
crowne of Scotland. In the yeare 1292, a fifteenth was granted to the king, of all
<note place="marg"><date>1292</date></note>
the temporall goods in Ireland, whilest Vescie was as yet lord iustice. This Vescie
<!--<fw place="bot-right">"was"</fw>-->


<pb n="241"/>

<!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-right">"241"</fw>-->


was a sterne man and full of courage, he called Iohn earle of Kildare before him,
charging him with foule riots and misdemeanors, for that he ranged abroad, and
sought reuenge vpon priuat displeasures out of all order, and not for anie aduancement
of the publike wealth or seruice of his souereigne.</p>
<p>The earle as impatient to heare himselfe touched as the iustice to suffer euill
<note place="marg">The earle of Kildare.</note>
dooing, answered thus. "By your honor and mine (my lord) and by king Edwards
hand (for that was accompted no small oth in those daies among the Irish) you
would if you durst appeach me in plaine termes of treason or felonie: for where I
haue the title, and you the fl&eacute;ece of Kildare. I wote well how great an eiesore I
am in your sight, so that if I might be handsomlie trussed vp for a fellon, then
might my master your sonne become a gentleman." "A gentleman" quoth the
iustice, "thou proud earle? I tell th&eacute;e, the Vescies were gentlemen before Kildare
was an earledome: and before that Welsh bankrupt thy cousine fethered his nest
in Leinster. But seeing thou darest me, I will suerlie breake thy heart." And
therwith he called the earle a notorious th&eacute;efe and a murtherer. Then followed
facing and bracing among the souldiers, with high words, and terrible swearing on
both sides, vntill either part appeased his owne.</p>
<p>The lord iustice shortlie after, leaning his deputie William Haie, tooke the sea,
and hasted ouer to the king. The earle immediatlie followed, and as heinouslie
as the lord iustice accused him of felonie, Kildare no lesse appealed him of treason.
For triall heereof, the earle asked the combat, and Vescie refused not: but yet when
the lists were prouided, Vescie was slipt awaie into France, and so disherited of
all his lands in the countie of Kildare, which were bestowed vpon the earle and his
heires for euer. The earle waxing loftie of mind in such prosperous successe,
squared with diuerse nobles, English and Irish of that land. The same yeare died
<note place="marg"><date>1294</date></note>

<note place="marg">The death of the archbishop Samford.</note>

<note place="marg">The earle of Vlster taken prisoner.</note>
Iohn Samford archbishop of Dublin, and Iohn Fitzthomas earle of Kildare, and
Iohn de la Mare tooke prisoners, Richard Burgh earle of Vlster, and William Burgh
within the countrie of Meth, and the castell of Kildare was taken, and all the
countrie wasted by the English on the one side, and the Irish on the other, and
Calwagh burnt all the rolles and talies concerning the records &amp; accompts of that
countie. Great dearth and death reigned in Ireland this yeare, and the two y&eacute;eres
<note place="marg">Great dearth and death.</note>
next insuing. The earle of Kildare deteined the earle of Vlster prisoner, vntill by
authoritie of a parlement holden at Kilkennie, he was deliuered out of the castell
of Leie, for his two sonnes, and for the inuasion which the earle of Kildare had
made into Meth, and other his vnrulie and misordred parts, was disseized of the
castell of Sligagh, and of all his lands in Connagh.</p>
<p>William Dodingsels, being this yeare made lord iustice of Ireland, after Vescie
<note place="marg">William Dodingsels lord iustice.</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1295</date></note>

<note place="marg">Thomas Fitzmaurice lord iustice.</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1296</date></note>

<note place="marg"><date>1298</date></note>

<note place="marg"><emph>Rec. Turris.</emph></note>
died, in the y&eacute;ere next following, that is 1295, and the thr&eacute;e and twentith of king
Edward the first. After him succ&eacute;eded in that roome the lord Thomas Fitzmaurice.
In the yeare 1296, frier William de Bothum was consecrated archbishop of Dublin.
In the yeare 1298, and six and twentith of Edward the first, the lord Thomas Fitzmaurice
departed this life, and an agr&eacute;ement was made betwixt the earle of Vlster
and the lord Iohn Fitzthomas earle of Kildare, by Iohn Wogan that was ordeined
lord iustice of Ireland. In the y&eacute;ere 1299 William archbishop of Dublin departed
<note place="marg"><date>1299</date></note>
this life, and Richard de Fringis was consecrated archbishop in his place. The king
went vnto Iohn Wogan lord iustice, commanding him to giue summons vnto the
nobles of Ireland, to prepare themselues with horsse and armor to come in their
best arraie for the warre, to serue him against the Scots: and withall wrote vnto
the same nobles, as to Richard de Burgh earle of Vlster, Geffreie de Genuill, Iohn
Fitzthomas, Thomas Fitzmaurice, Theobald lord Butler, Theobald lord Verdon,
Piers lord Birmingham of Thetemoie, Eustace lord Powre, Hugh lord Purcell, Iohn
de Cogan, Iohn de Barrie, William de Barrie, Walter de Lastice, Richard de
<!--<fw place="bot-left">"VOL. VI."</fw>--><!--<fw place="bot-center">"2 I"</fw>--><!--<fw place="bot-right">"Excester,"</fw>-->

<pb n="242"/>

<!--<fw place="top-left">"242"</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>-->


Excester, Iohn Pipurd, Walter Lenfant, Iohn of Oxford, Adam de Stanton, Sunon
de Pheibe, William Cadell, Iohn de Vale, Maurice de Carre, George de la Roch,
Maurice de Rochford, and Maurice Fitzthomas de Kerto, commanding them to be
with him at Withwelaun the first of March. Such a precept I remember I haue
read, registred in a close roll among the records of the tower. But where Marlburrow
saith, that the said Iohn Wogan lord iustice of Ireland, and the lord
Iohn Fitzthomas, with manie others, came to king Edward into Scotland, in the
nine and twentith yeare of king Edwards reigne, Campion noteth it to be in the
yere 1299, which fell in the seuen &amp; twentith of the reigne of king Edward:
&amp; if my remembrance faile me not, the close roll aforementioned beareth date of
the foure and twentith yeare of king Edwards reigne. All which notes may be
true, for it is verie like, that in those warres against the Scots, the king sent diuerse
times to the Irish lords to come to serue him, as it behooued them to doo by
their tenures: and not onelie he sent into Ireland to haue the seruices of men, but
also for prouision of vittels, as in close rolles I remember I haue also s&eacute;ene recorded
of the seauen and twentith and thirtith yeare of the said king Edward the first his
reigne. For this we find in a certeine abstract of the Irish chronicles, which should
s&eacute;eme to be collected out of Flatsburie, whom Campion so much followed, that in
<note place="marg"><emph>Cbr. Pembrig.</emph></note>

<note place="marg"><date>1301</date></note>

<note place="marg">Irishmen inuade Scotland</note>
the yeare 1301, the lord Iohn Wogan lord iustice, Iohn Fitzthomas, Peter Birmingham,
&amp; diuerse others went into Scotland in aid of king Edward, in which
yeare also a great part of the citie of Dublin, with the church of saint Werburgh
was burnt in the night of the feast daie of saint Colme. Also the lord Genuill
married the daughter of Iohn de Montfort, and the lord Iohn Mortimer married
the daughter and heire of Peter Genuill, also the lord Theobald de Verdon married
the daughter of the lord Roger Mortimer. The same yeare in the winter season,
the Irish of Leinster raised warre against the townes of Wicklow and Rathdon,
dooing much hurt by burning in the countrie all about: but they were chastised
for their wickednesse, loosing the most part of their prouision and cattell. And
in the Lent season the more part of them had b&eacute;ene vtterlie destroied, if discord
and variance had not risen among the Englishmen, to the impeachment of their
purposed enterprises.</p>
<p>In haruest there were thr&eacute;e hundred th&eacute;eues slaine by the Phelanes. Also Walter
le Power wasted a great part of Mounster, burning manie farmes and places in that
<note place="marg">Walter Power.</note>
countrie. In the yeare 1302, pope Boniface demanded a tenth of all the spirituall
<note place="marg"><date>1302</date></note>
liuings in England and Ireland, for the space of thr&eacute;e yeares, to mainteine wars in
defense of the church of Rome, against the king of Arragon. In the yeare 1303,
<note place="marg"><date>1303</date></note>

<note place="marg">The earle of Vlster.</note>
the earle of Vlster, and Richard Burgh, and sir Eustace le Power, with a puissant
armie entered Scotland. The earle made thr&eacute;e and thirtie knights at Dublin, before
he-set forwards. The same yeere Girald, sonne and heire to the lord Iohn
Fitzthomas departed this life, and likewise the countesse of Vlster. William de
Wellisleie, and sir Robert de Persiuall were slaine the two and twentith of October.
In the yeare 1304, a great part of the citie of Dublin was burnt by casuall fire.
<note place="marg"><date>1304</date></note>
In the yeare next insuing, lordaine Comin with his complices slue Maritagh Oconhur
king of Offalie, and his brother Calwagh, with diuerse others within the court
of Piers de Birmingham at Carricke in Carbrie. Also sir Gilbert Sutton steward
of Wexford was slaine by the Irishmen, n&eacute;ere to the farme of Heimond de Grace,
which Heimond bare himselfe right valiantlie in that fight, and in the end through
his great manhood escaped.</p>
<p>In the yeare 1306 a great slaughter was made in Offalie n&eacute;ere to the castell of
<note place="marg"><date>1306</date></note>

<note place="marg">A discomfiture at Offalie.</note>
Geschill, the thirteenth daie of Aprill vpon Oconhur and his fr&eacute;ends by the Odempsies,
in the which place were slaine a great number of men. Also Obren king of
Thomond was slaine. Moreouer, Donald Oge Mac Arthie slue Donald Russe king
<!--<fw place="bot-right">"of"</fw>-->


<pb n="243"/>

<!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-right">"243"</fw>-->


of Desmond. And vpon the twelfe of Maie in the confins of Meth, a great ouerthrow
chanced to the side of the lord Piers Butler, and Balimore in Leinster was
<note place="marg">Balimore burnt.</note>
burnt by the Irish, where Henrie Celfe was slaine at that present time. Hereof
followed great wars betwixt the English and Irish in Leinster, so that a great
<note place="marg">Warres in Leinster.</note>
armie was called togither foorth of diuerse parts of Ireland, to restreine the malice
of the Irish in Leinster, in which iournie sir Thomas Mandeuill knight entred into
a conflict with the Irish n&eacute;ere to Glenfell, in the which he bare himselfe right manfullie,
till his horsse was slaine vnder him, and yet then to his great praise and high
commendation he saued both himselfe and manie of his companie. The lord chancellor
<note place="marg">The lord chancellor consecrated bishop of Imaleie.</note>
of Ireland, Thomas Caucocke, was consecrated bishop of Imaleie within the
Trinitie church at Dublin, and kept such a feast as the like had not lightlie beene
s&eacute;ene nor heard of before that time in Ireland, first to the rich &amp; after to the poore.
Richard Flerings archbishop of Dublin deceased on the euen of saint Luke the
<note place="marg">The archbishop of Dublin deceased.</note>
euangelist, to whom succ&eacute;eded Richard de Hauerings, who after he had continued
in that s&eacute;e about a fiue yeares, resigned it ouer by dispensasion obteined from Rome,
and then his nephue Iohn L&eacute;ech was admitted archbishop there.</p>
<p>In the yeare 1307 the first of Aprill, Murcod Ballagh was beheaded n&eacute;ere to
<note place="marg"><date>1307</date></note>
Merton by sir Dauid Caunton knight, and shortlie after was Adam Daune slaine.
Also, a great discomfiture and slaughter fell vpon the Englishmen in Connagh by
<note place="marg">A disc&omacr;fiture in Connagh.</note>
the Oscheles the first daie of Maie, and the robbers that dwelt in the parties of
Offalie raised the castell of Geischell, and in the vigill of the translation of Thomas
Becket, being the sixt of Iulie, they burnt the towne of Leie and besieged the
castell: but they were constreined to depart from thense shortlie after, by Iohn
Fitzthomas and Edmund Butler that came to remoue that siege. In the yeare 1308
<note place="marg"><date>1308</date></note>
king Edward the first departed this life the seuenth of Iulie.</p>
	  </div>
<div n="Edward2" type="chronicle">
<head>Edward the second.</head>
<p>RICHARD archbishop of Dublin, after that he had gouerned that s&eacute;e the space
of fiue yeares, by reason of a vision that he saw in his sl&eacute;epe, f&eacute;eling himselfe
troubled in conscience, with consideration of that dreame, resigned the next morrow
all his title to the archbishops dignitie (as before ye haue heard) and contented himselfe
with other ecclesiasticall benefices as seemed conuenient to his estate. This
<note place="marg"><date>1300</date></note>

<note place="marg">The order of the T&emacr;plers suppressed.</note>
yeare by vertue of letters directed from the pope to the king of England, he caused
all the Templers as well in England as Ireland to be apprehended and committed
to safe k&eacute;eping. The profession of these Templers began at Ierusalem, by certeine
gentlemen that remained in an hostell n&eacute;ere to the temple, who till the councell of
Trois in France were not increased aboue the number of nine, but from that time
foorth in little more than fiftie yeares, by the zealous contribution of all christian
realmes, they had houses erected euerie where, with liuings bountifullie assigned to
the same for their maintenance, in so much as they were augmented vnto the number
of thr&eacute;e hundred, that were knights of that order, beside inferiour brethren
innumerable: but now with wealth they so forgot themselues, that they nothing
lesse regarded, than the purpose of their foundation: and withall being accused
of horrible heresies (whether in all things iustlie or otherwise, the Lord knoweth)
they were in the councell at Lions in France condemned, and their liuings transposed
to the knights Hospitalers, otherwise called the knights of the Rhodes, and now
of Malta. The manner of their apprehension and committing was sudden, and so
generall in all places vpon one daie, that they had no time to shift for themselues.</p>
<p>For first, the king sent foorth a precept to euerie shiriffe within the realme of
<!--<fw place="bot-center">"2 I 2"</fw>--><!--<fw place="bot-right">"England,"</fw>-->


<pb n="244"/>

<!--<fw place="top-left">"244"</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>-->


England, commanding them within each of their roomes to cause a prescribed number
of knights, or rather such men of credit, on whose fidelities he might assure
himselfe to assemble at a certeine towne named in the same writ, the sundaie next
after the Epiphanie, &amp; that ech of the same shiriffes failed not to bethere the same
daie, to execute all that should be inioined them by anie other writ, then and there
to be deliuered. The shiriffe of Yorke was commanded to giue summons to foure
and twentie such knights, or other sufficient men to m&eacute;et him at Yorke. The
shiriffe of Norffolke and Suffolke, to summon twentie to meet him at Thetford.
The other shiriffs were appointed to call to them some ten, some twelue, or some
fourteene, to m&eacute;et them at such townes as in their writs were named. The date of
this writ was from Westminster the fift&eacute;enth of December, in the first yeare of this
king Edward the seconds reigne. The other writ was sent by a chapleine authorized
both to deliuer the same writ, and to take an oth of the shiriffe, that he should
not disclose the contents, till he had put the same in execution, which was to attach
by assistance of those aforementioned knights, or as manie of them as he thought
expedient to vse, all the Templers within the precinct of his roome, and to seize
all their lands, goods, and cattels into the kings hands, and to cause an inuentarie
of the same indented be made in presence of the warden of the place, whether
he were knight of the order or anie other, and in the presence of other honest
men neighbours thereabouts, keeping the one counterpane with himselfe, sealed with
his seale that made the seizure, and leauing the other in the hands of the said warden:
and further to s&eacute;e the same goods and cattels to be put in safe k&eacute;eping, and to
prouide that the quicke goods might be well kept and looked vnto, and the grounds
manured to the most profit, and to cause the bodies of the Templers attached, to be
so deteined in all safetie, as that they be not yet committed to irons nor to streict
prison, but to remaine in some conuenient place other than their owne houses, and
to be found of the goods so seized accordinglie as falleth for their estates, till he
haue otherwise in commandement from the king: and what is doone herein, to certifie
into the excheker the morrow after the purification. The date of this second
writ was from Biflet the twentith of December. There was likewise a writ directed
to Iohn Wogan lord iustice of Ireland, signifieng vnto him what should be doone
in England, touching the apprehension of the Templers, and seizure of their lands
and goods, commanding him to proc&eacute;ed in semblable manner against them in Ireland:
but the daie and place when the shiriffes should there assemble, was left to
the discretion of the said iustice and treasuror of the excheker there, but so as the
same might be doone before anie rumour of this thing could be brought ouer out
of England thither. Also a like commandement was sent vnto Iohn de Britaine
earle of Richmond, lord warden of Scotland, and to Eustace Cotesbach chamberleine
of Scotland, also to Walter de Pederton lord iustice of west Wales, to Hugh
Aldighleigh <emph>ali&agrave;s</emph> Auderleie lord iustice of north Wales, and to Robert Holland lord
iustice of Chester. Thus much for the Temples. But now to other dooings in
Ireland.</p>
<p>In the yeare 1308 the twelfe of Aprill deceased Peter de Birmingham a noble
<note place="marg"><date>1308</date></note>
warriour, and one that had b&eacute;ene no small scourge to the Irish. The eleuenth of
Maie the castell of Kennun was burnt, and diuers of them that had it in k&eacute;eeping
were slaine by William Macbalther, and other of the Irish, and likewise the towne
<note place="marg">This Macbalther was after hanged at Dublin.</note>

<note place="marg">The lord iustice discomfited.</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1308</date></note>
of Courcoulie was burnt by the same malefactors. And the sixt of Iune, Iohn lord
Wogan lord iustice was discomfited n&eacute;ere to Glindelorie, where Iohn de S. Hogelin,
Iohn Norton, Iohn Breton, and manie other were slaine. The sixt&eacute;enth of Iune,
Dunlouan, Tobir, and manic other townes were burnt by the Irish rebels. About
<note place="marg">Iohn Decer maior of Dublin.</note>
this season, Iohn Decer maior of Dublin builded the high pipe there, &amp; the bridge
<!--<fw place="bot-right">"ouer"</fw>-->


<pb n="245"/>

<!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-right">"245"</fw>-->


ouer the Liffie towards S. Vlstons, and a chappell of our ladie at the friers minors,
where he was buried, repared the church of the friers preachers, and euerie fridaie
tabled the friers at his owne costs.</p>
<p>Iohn Wogan hauing occasion to passe into England, William Burgh did supplie
<note place="marg">Burgh.</note>

<note place="marg">Piers Gaueston sent into Ireland.</note>
his roome, vnto whom king Edward recommended Piers de Gaueston, when (contrarie
to the kings mind) he was banished by the lords of England, and about the
natiuitie of our ladie he came ouer into Ireland, being sent thither by the king with
manie iewels: and beside the letters which he brought of recommendation from the
king, he had assigned to him the c&omacr;modities roiall of that realme, which bred some
trouble and bickerings there, betwixt Richard Burgh earle of Vlster, and the said
Gaueston, who notwithstanding bought the good willes of the souldiers with his
liberalitie, slue Dermot Odempsie, subdued Obren, edified soundrie castels, causeies,
and bridges, but the next yeare he was reuoked home by the king, as in the historie
of England it maie appeare.</p>
<p>In the vigill of Simon and Iude, the lord Roger Mortimer landed in Ireland with
<note place="marg">Lord Roger Mortimer.</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1309</date></note>
his wife, right heire to the seigniorie of Meth, as daughter to Piers Genuill, that
was sonne to the lord Geffreie Genuill, which Geffreie became a frier at Trim of
the order of the preachers: by reason whereof, the lord Mortimer and his wife entered
into possession of the lands of Meth. In the yeare 1309, on Candlemas day,
the lord Iohn Bonneuill was slaine n&eacute;ere to the towne of Ardscoll, by the lord
<note place="marg">Lord Iohn Bonneuill slaine.</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1310</date></note>
Arnold Powre and his complices, his bodie was buried at Athie in the church of
the friers preachers. In the yere following, at a parlement holden at Kildare, the
lord Arnold Powre was acquit of that slaughter, for that it was prooued it was doone
in his owne defense. In the yeare 1311, or (as some bookes haue) the yeare 1309,
<note place="marg"><date>1311</date></note>

<note place="marg">A parlement at Kilkennie.</note>

<note place="marg"><emph>Campion.</emph></note>
Wogan lord iustice summoned a parlement at Kilkennie, where diuerse wholesome
lawes were ordeined, but neuer executed. There fell the bishops in contention
about their iurisdictions, namelie the bishop of Dublin forbad the primat of Armagh
to raise his croisier within the prouince of Leinster.</p>
<p>Shortlie after, Rowland Ioice the primat stale by night (in his pontificals) from
Howth to the priorie of Grace Dieu, where the bishops seruants met him, &amp; with
force chased him out of the diocesse. This bishop was named Iohn a L&eacute;ekes, and
was consecrated not long before he kept this sturre. Richard earle of Vlster with
a great armie came to Bonrath in Thomond, where as sir Robert or rather sir Richard
de Clare discomfited his power, tooke sir William de Burgh prisoner, or (as some
<note place="marg">Sir Richard de Clare.</note>

<note place="marg">Iohn Lacie slaine.</note>
bookes haue) the earle himselfe. Iohn Lacie the sonne of Walter Lacie, and diuerse
others were slaine. The twelfe of Nouember this yere, Richard de Clare slue six
hundred Galloglasses, and Iohn Morgoghedan was slaine by Omolmoie. Also Donat
Obren was murthered by his owne men in Thomond.</p>
<p>The one and twentith of Februarie began a riot in Argile by Robert Verdon, for
<note place="marg"><date>1312</date></note>

<note place="marg">Robert Verdon raiseth a riotous tumult.</note>

<note place="marg">Iohn Wogan lord iustice.</note>
the appeasing wherof an armie was lead thither by Iohn Wogan lord chiefe iustice
in the beginning of Iulie, but the same was discomfited, and diuerse men of account
slaine, as sir Nicholas Auenell, Patrike de Roch, &amp; others. At length yet the said
sir Robert Verdon, and many of his complices came and submitted themselues to
prison within the castell of Dublin, abiding there the kings mercie. The lord
Edmund Butler was made deputie iustice vuder the lord Iobn Wogan, who in
the Lent next insuing besieged the Obrens in Glindelow, and compelled them to
yeeld themselues to the kings peace. Also in the yeare abouesaid 1312, Maurice
Fitzthomas maried the ladie Katharine, daughter to the earle of Vister at Gr&eacute;ene
castell, and Thomas Fitziohn maried an other of the said earles daughters in the
same place, but not on the same daie: for the first of those two mariages was celebrated
the morrow after saint Dommikes daie, and this second mariage was kept
<!--<fw place="bot-right">"the"</fw>-->


<pb n="246"/>

<!--<fw place="top-left">"246"</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>-->


the morrow after the feast of the assumption of our ladie. Also Robert de Bruse
ouerthrew the castell of Man, and tooke the lord Donegan Odowill on saint Barnabies
daie.</p>
<p>In the yeare 1313, Iohn a Leekes archbishop of Dublln departed this life: after
<note place="marg"><date>1313</date></note>

<note place="marg"><emph>Campion.</emph></note>
whose decease were elected in schisme and diuision of sides two successors, Walter
Thorneburie lord chancellor, and Alexander Bignor treasuror of Ireland. The
chancellor to strengthen his election, hastilie went to sea, and togither with an hundred
and fiftie and six persons perished by shipwracke. The other submitting his
cause to the processe of law, taried at home and sped. Moreouer, the lord Iohn
de Burgh, sonne and heire to the earle of Vlster, deceased at Galbie on the feast
<note place="marg">The earle of Vlsters sonne and heire deceaseth.</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1314</date></note>
daie of saint Marcell &amp; Marcelline. Also the lord Edmund Butler created thirtie
knights in the castle or Dublin on Michaels daie being sundaie. The knights
hospitalers or of saint Iohns (as they were called) were inuested in the lands of
the Templers in Ireland. The same yeare was the lord Theobald Verdon sent lord
iustice into Ireland.</p>
<p>In the ninth yeare of king Edwards reigne, Edward Bruse, brother to Robert
<note place="marg"><date>1315</date></note>

<note place="marg">Edward Bruse inuadeth Ireland.</note>
Bruse king of Scots, entered the north part of Ireland with six thousand men.
There were with him diuerse capteins of high renowme among the Scotish nation,
of whome the chiefe were these: the earles of Murrie and Mentith, the lord Iohn
<note place="marg">Capteins of name with Bruse.</note>
Steward, the lord Iohn Campbell, the lord Thomas Randolfe, Fergus de Andressan,
Iohn Wood, and Iohn Bisset. They landed n&eacute;ere to Cragfergus in Vlster the frue.
&amp; twentith of Maie, and ioining with the Irish, conquered the earledome of Vlster,
and gaue the English there diuerse great ouerthrowes, tooke the towne of Dundalke,
spoiled &amp; burnt it, with a great part of Vrgile: they burnt churches &amp; abbeies,
<note place="marg">Dundalke taken and burnt.</note>
with the people whom they found in the same, sparing neither man, woman
nor child. Then was the lord Edmund Butler chosen lord iustice, who made the
<note place="marg">Edmund Butler lord iustice.</note>
earle of Vlster and the Giraldines friends, and reconciled himselfe with sir Iohn
Mandeuill, thus seeking to preserue the residue of the realme which Edward Bruse
meant wholie to conquer, hauing caused himselfe to be crowned king of Ireland.
The lord iustice assembled a great power out of Mounster, and Leinster, and other
parts therabouts, and the earle of Vlster with another armie came vnto him n&eacute;ere
vnto Dundalke, where they consulted togither how to deale in defending the countrie
against the enimies: but hearing the Scots were withdrawne backe, the earle
of Vlster folowed them, and fighting with them at Coiners, h&eacute;e lost the field.</p>
<p>There were manie slaine on both parts, and William de Burgh the earls brother,
sir Iohn Mandeuill, and sir Alane Fitzalane were taken prisoners. Herewith the
Irish of Connagh and Meth began foorthwith to rebell against the Englishmen, and
burnt the castell of Athlon and Randon. And the Bruse comming forward burnt
Kenlis in Meth, and Granard, also Finnagh, and Newcastell, and kept his Christmas
at Loghsudie. From thense he went through the countrie vnto Rathimegan and
Kildare, and to the parties about Tristeldermot and Athie, then to Raban, Sketlier,
&amp; n&eacute;ere to Ardskoll in Leinster: where the lord iustice Butler, the lord Iohn Fitzthomas,
the lord Arnold Powre, and other the lords and gentlemen of Leinster and
Mounster came to incounter the Bruse: but through discord that rose among them,
they left the field vnto the enimies, sir William Pendergast knight, and Heimond
le Grace a right valiant esquier were slaine there. And on the Scotish side sir
Fergus Andressan and sir Walter Murrcie, with diuerse other that were buried in
the church of the friers preachers at Athie.</p>
<p>After this the Bruse in his returne towards Meth burnt the castell of Leie, and
so passed foorth till hee came to Kenlis in Meth. In which meane time Roger lord
Mortimer, trusting to win himselfe fame if he might ouerthrow the enimies, called
<!--<fw place="bot-right">"forth"</fw>-->


<pb n="247"/>

<!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-right">"247"</fw>-->


forth fift&eacute;ene thousand men, and vnderstanding that the Scots were come to Kenlis,
<note place="marg">The lord Mortimer discomfited by the Scots.</note>
made thitherwards, and there incountering with them, was put to the woorse, his
men (as was supposed) wilfullie shrinking from him, as those that bare him
hollow hearts. With the newes of this ouerthrow, vpstart the Irish of Mounster,
the Otoolies, Obrens, Omores, and with fire and sword wasted all from Arclow to
Leix. With them coped the lord iustice, and made of them a great slaughter,
fourescore of their heads were sent to the castell of Dublin.</p>
<p>In time of these troubles and warres in Ireland by the inuasion thus of the Scots,
certeine Irish lords, faithfull men and true subiects to the king of England, did
not onelie promise to continue in their loiall obeisance towards him, being their
souereigne prince; but also for more assurance deliuered hostages to be kept within
the castell of Dublin. The names of which lords that were so contented to assure
their allegiance were these, Iohn Fitzthomas lord of Offalie, Richard de Clare, Morice
Fitzthomas, Thomas Fitziohn le Power baron of Donoille, Arnold le Power, Morice
<note place="marg">Assurance giuen by the lords of Ireland for their loialtie.</note>
de Rochford, Dauid de la Roch, and Miles de la Roch. These and diuerse other
resisted with all their might and maine the iniurious attempts of the Scots, although
the Scots had drawne to their side the most part of the wild Irish, and no small
number also of the English Irish, as well lords, as others of meaner calling: so that
the countrie was miserablie afflicted, what by the Scots on the one part, and the Irish
rebels on the other, which rebels notwithstanding were ouerthrowne in diuerse
particular conflicts. But yet to the further scattering of the English forces in
Ireland, there rose foure princes of Connagh, but the Burghes and Birminghams
discomfited them, and slue eleuen thousand of them beside Athenrie. Amongst
<note place="marg">A great ouerthrow.</note>

<note place="marg">The king of Connagh slaine.</note>
other were slaine in this battell Fedelmicus, Oconhur king of Connagh, Okellie,
and diuerse other great lords and capteins of Connagh and Meth. The lord
Richard Birmingham had an esquier that belonged to him called Iohn Husseie, who
by the commandement of his maister went foorth to take view of the dead bodies,
and to bring him word whether Okellie his mortall fo were slaine among the residue.
Husseie comming into the field with one man to turne vp and surneie the dead
carcases, was streight espied by Okellie, that laie lurking in a brake bush thereby,
who hauing had good proofe of Husseie his valiancie before that time, longed sore
to traine him from his capteine, and presuming now vpon his good oportunitie,
discouered himselfe, not doubting, but either to win him with courteous persuasions,
or by force to worke his will of him, and so comming to him said: "Husseie, thou
s&eacute;est that I am at all points armed, &amp; haue mine esquire here likewise furnished
with armour &amp; weapon readie at mine elbow; thou art naked with thy page, a
yoongling, &amp; not to be accounted of: so that if I loued th&eacute;e not, and meant to
spare th&eacute;e for thine owne sake, I might now doo with th&eacute;e what I would, and slea
th&eacute;e for thy maisters sake. But come &amp; serue me vpon this request here made to
th&eacute;e, and I promise th&eacute;e by saint Patrikes staffe to make th&eacute;e a lord in Connagh,
of more possessions than thy maister hath in Ireland." When these words might
nothing weie him, his owne man (a great stout lubber) began to reproue him of
follie, for not consenting to so large an offer, which was assured with an oth,
wherevpon he durst gage his soule for performance.</p>
<p>Now had Husseie thr&eacute;e enimies, and first therefore turning to his knaue, he dispatched
him. Next he raught vnto Okellies esquier such a knocke vnder the pit of
the care, that downe he came to the ground and there he laie. Thirdlie, he laid so
about him, that yer anie helpe could be looked for, he had also siaine Okellie, and
<note place="marg">Okellie slaine.</note>
perceuing the esquire to be but astonied he recouered him, and holpe him vp
againe, and after he was somewhat come to himselfe, he forced him vpon a
trunchion, to beare his lords head into the high towne before him, who did so;
<!--<fw place="bot-right">"and"</fw>-->


<pb n="248"/>

<!--<fw place="top-left">"248"</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>-->


and Husseie presented it to Birmingham, who after the circumstances declared, he
dubbed Husseie knight, aduancing him to manie preferments. The successors of
that familie afterwards were barons of Galtrim. Sir Thomas Mandeuill and others
in this meane while made oftentimes enterprises against the Scots, and slue diuerse of
them in sundrie conflicts. But howsoeuer it chanced, we find recorded by Henrie
Marlburrow, that either the said sir Thomas Mandeuill (that thus valiantlie behaued
<note place="marg">Sir Thomas Mandeuill slaine.</note>
himselfe against the Scots) or some other bearing the same name, and his brother
also called Iohn Mandeuill were both slaine shortlie after at Downe, vpon their
comming foorth of England, by the Scots that were readie there to assaile them.</p>
<p>Thus may we see, that those lords and knights, which had giuen pledges for their
loialtie to the king of England, sought by all waies and meanes how to beat backe the
enimies: which they might haue doone with more ease, if the Irish had not assisted
the Scots, and presuming of their aid, rebelled in sundrie parts of the countrie;
who neuerthelesse were oftentimes well chastised for their disloiall dealings, as
partlie we haue touched; although we omit diuerse small ouerthrowes and other
particular matters, sith otherwise we should increase this booke further than our
first purposed intent would permit. Whilest the Scots were thus holden vp in
<note place="marg"><emph>Campion.</emph></note>

<note place="marg"><date>1316</date></note>

<note place="marg">The king of Scots in Ireland.</note>
Ireland, that they could not in all things worke their wils, Robert le Bruse king of
Scots came ouer himselfe, landed at Cragfergus to the aid of his brother, whose
souldiors most wickedlie entred into churches, spoiling and defacing the same of
all such toomes, monuments, plate, copes, &amp; other ornaments which they found,
and might laie hands vpon.</p>
<p>The castell of Cragfergus, after it had b&eacute;ene strictlie besieged a long time, was
<note place="marg">Cragfergus deliuered vp to the Scots.</note>

<note place="marg">Men eaten.</note>
surrendred to the Scots, by them that had kept it, till they for want of other vittels
were driuen to eate leather, and eight Scots (as some write) which they had taken
prisoners. The lord Thomas, sonne to the earle of Vlster departed this life. And
on the sundaie next after the natiuitie of our ladie, the lord Iohn Fitzthomas
<note place="marg">Iohn Fitzthomas the first earle of Kildare deceasseth.</note>
deceased at Laragh Brine n&eacute;ere to Mainoth, and was buried at Kildare, in the church
of the friers preachers. This Iohn Fitzthomas, a little before his death, was created
earle of Kildare; after whome succ&eacute;eded his sonne Thomas Fitziohn a right wise
and prudent personage. The fourt&eacute;enth of September, Conhor Mac Kele, &amp; flue
hundred Irishmen were slaine by the lord William de Burgh, and lord Richard
Birmingham in Connagh. Also on the mondaie after the feast of All saints, Iohn
<note place="marg">Scots ouerthrowne.</note>
Loggan and sir Hugh Bisset slue a great number of Scots, among the which were
one hundred with double armors, and two hundred with single armors: so that of
their men of armes there died thr&eacute;e hundred beside footemen.</p>
<p>The fift&eacute;enth of Nouember chanced a great tempest of wind and raine; which
<note place="marg">A great tempest.</note>
threw downe manie houses, with the st&eacute;eple of the Trinitie church in Dublin, and
did much other burt both by land and water. On the fift of December, sir Alane
Steward that had b&eacute;ene taken prisoner in Vlster by Iohn Loggan, and sir Iohn
Sandale, was brought to the castell of Dublin. After Canlemas, the Lacies
<note place="marg"><date>1317</date></note>
came to Dublin, &amp; procured an inquest to be impanelled to inquire of their
demeanor, for that they were accused to haue procured the Scots to come into
Ireland: but by that inquest they were discharged, and therewith tooke an oth to
keepe the kings peace, and to destroie the Scots to the vttermost of their power.
In the beginning of Lent, the Scots came in secret wise vnto Slane, with twentie
thousand armed men: and with them came the armie of Vlster, destroieng all the
countrie before them. Moreouer, on mondaie before the feast of S. Matthias the
apostle, the earle of Vlster lieng in the abbeie of S. Marie n&eacute;ere to Dublin, Robert
Notingham maior of that citie, with the communaltie of the same went thither,
<note place="marg">The earle of Vlster apprehended.</note>
tooke the earle, and put him in prison within the castell of Dublin, slue seuen of
his men, and spoiled the abbeie.
<!--<fw place="bot-right">"The"</fw>-->


<pb n="249"/>

<!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-right">"249"</fw>-->


The same w&eacute;eke, Edward Bruse marched towards Dublin, but herewith, turning
to the castell of Knoke, he entred the same, and tooke Hugh Tirrell the lord thereof,
<note place="marg">Hugh Tirrell taken by the Scots.</note>
togither with his wife, and ransomed them for a summe of monie. The citizens of
Dublin burnt all their suburbs for feare of a siege, and made the best purueiance
they could to defend their citie, if the Bruse had come to haue besieged them: but he
turning another waie, went vnto the towne of Naas, and was guided thither by the
Lacies, contrarie to their oth. From thense he passed vnto Tristeldermot, and so
to Baliganam, and to Callan, at length he came to Limerike, and there remained till
after Easter. They of Vlster sent to the lord iustice lamentable informations of
such crueltie as the enimies practised in those parts, bes&eacute;eching him to take some
order for their reliefe in that their so miserable estate. The lord iustice deliuered
to them the kings power with his standard, wherewith vnder pretense to expell the
<note place="marg">The kings standard deliuered to them of Vlster.</note>
Scots, they got vp in armor, and ranging through the countrie, did more vexe and
molest the subiects, than did the strangers. The Scots proc&eacute;eded and spoiled
Cashels, &amp; wheresoeuer they lighted vpon the Butlers lands, they burnt and spoiled
them vnmercifullie.</p>
<p>In this meane while had the lord iustice and Thomas Fitziohn earle of Kildare,
Richard de Clare, and Arnold le Powre baron of Donnoill leuied an armie of thirtie
thousand men, readie to go against the enimies, and to giue them battell, but no
good was doone. For about the same time the lord Roger Mortimer was sent into
<note place="marg">Roger Mortimer iustice of Ireland.</note>
Ireland as lord iustice, and landing at Yoghall, wrote his letters vnto the lord
Butler, &amp; to the other capteins, willing them not to fight till he came with such
power as he had brought ouer with him. Whereof the Bruse being warned, retired
first towards Kildare. But yet after this he came within foure miles of Trim, where
he laie in a wood, and lost manie of his men through famine, and so at length
about the beginning of Maie he returned into Vlster.</p>
<p>The lord Edmund Butler made great slaughter of the Irish n&eacute;ere to Tristledermot,
<note place="marg">Slaughter of Irishmen.</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1317</date></note>
and likewise at Balithan he had a good hand of Omorch, and slue manie
of his men. The lord Mortimer pacified the displeasure and variance betwixt
Richard earle of Vlster, and the nobles that had put the said earle vnder safe
<note place="marg">The earle of Vlster deliuered out of prison.</note>

<note place="marg">Scarsitie of vittels in Vlster.</note>
k&eacute;eping within the castell of Dublin, accusing him of certeine riots committed to
the preiudice and losse of the kings subiects, whereby the Scots increased in
strength and courage, whose spoiling of the countrie caused such horrible scarsitie in
Vlster, that the soldiors which the yeare before abused the kings authoritie, to
purueie themselues of ouer fine diet, surfetted with flesh and <emph>Aquavit&oelig;</emph> all the Lent
long, prolled and pilled insatiablie wheresoeuer they came without need, and without
regard of the poore people, whose onelie prouision they deuoured. These people
now liuing in slauerie vnder the Bruse, starued for hunger, hauing first experienced
manie lamentable shifts, euen to the eating of dead carcasses.</p>
<p>The earle of Vlster was deliuered by maineprise and vpon his oth, by the which
<note place="marg">The earle of Vlster deliuered.</note>
he vndertooke neuer to seeke reuenge of his apprehension otherwise than by order
of law, and so had daie giuen him vnto the feast of the natiuitie of saint Iohn
baptist: but he kept not his daie, whether for that he mistrusted to stand in triall
of his cause, or through some other reasonable let, I cannot tell. A great dearth
<note place="marg">Great dearth.</note>
this yeere afflicted the Irish people: for a measure of wheat called a chronecke was
sold at foure and twentie shillings, &amp; a chronecke of otes at sixteene shillings, and
all other vittels likewise were sold according to the same rate; for all the whole
countrie was sore wasted by the Scots and them of Vlster, insomuch that no small
number of people perished through famine.</p>
<p>About the feast of Pentecost the lord iustice Mortimer tooke his iornie towards
Drogheda, and sent to the Lacies, commanding them to come vnto him, but they
refused so to do. Whervpon he sent sir Hugh Crofts vnto them, to talke with them
<!--<fw place="bot-left">"VOL. VI."</fw>--><!--<fw place="bot-center">"2 K"</fw>--><!--<fw place="bot-right">"about"</fw>-->



<pb n="250"/>

<!--<fw place="top-left">"250"</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>-->


about some agr&eacute;ement of peace: but they slue the messenger, for whome great
<note place="marg">Sir Hugh Crofts slaine.</note>
lamentation was made, for that he was reputed &amp; knowne to be a right woorthie
knight. The lord iustiee sore offended herewith, gathereth an armie, &amp; goeth
against the Lacies, whome he chased out of Connagh, so that Hugh Lacie withdrew
to Vlster, &amp; there ioined himselfe with Edward Bruse. Wherevpon, on the thursdaie
next before the feast of saint Margaret, the said Hugh Lacie and also Walter
<note place="marg">The Lacies reuolt to the Scots.</note>
Lacie were proclamed traitors. This yeare passed verie troublesome vnto the whole
realme of Ireland, as well through slaughter betwixt the parties enimies one to
another, as by dearth and other misfortunes. Hugh Canon the kings iustice of his
bench was slaine by Andrew Birmingham betwixt the towne of Naas and castell
<note place="marg"><date>1318</date></note>
Marten. Also in the feast of the purification, the popes bulles were published,
whereby Alexander Bignor was consecrated archbishop of Dublin. About the
same time was great slaughter made of Irishmen, through a quarrell betwixt two
<note place="marg">Bignor consecrated archbishop of Dublin.</note>
great lords in Connagh: so that there died in fight to the number of foure thousand
men on both parties.</p>
<p>After Easter Walter Islep treasuror of Ireland was sent ouer into that realme,
<note place="marg">Walter Islep treasuror of Ireland.</note>
who brought letters to the lord Mortimer, commanding him to returne into
England vnto the king: which he did, and departing foorth of Ireland, remained
indebted to the citizens of Dublin for his prouision of vittels in the summe of a
thousand pounds, wherof he paid not one farthing, so that manie a bitter cursse
he carried with him to the sea, leauing William archbishop of Cashell lord
chancellor gouernor of the land in his place: and so by this meane was the said
archbishop both chancellor and iustice, and so continued till the feast of saint
Michaell. At what time Alexander Bignor archbishop of Dublin arriued at Yoghall,
being constituted lord iustice, and came to Dublin on saint Denise daie, being the
seauenth of October. But here is to be remembred, that a little before the departure
of the lord Mortimer foorth of Ireland, to wit, the fift of Maie, the lord
<note place="marg">The lord Richard de Clare slaine.</note>
Richard de Clare with foure knights, sir Henrie Capell, sir Thomas de Naas, sir
Iames Caunton, and sir Iohn Caunton; also Adam Apilgard and others (to the
number of foure score persons) were slaine by Obren and Mac Arthie. It was said
that the enimies in despite caused the lord Richards bodie to be cut in p&eacute;eces, so to
satisfie their malicious stomachs; but the same p&eacute;eces were yet afterwards buried in
the church of the friers minors at Limerike. Also before the lord Mortimers
returne into England, Iohn Lacie was had foorth of the castell of Dublin, and
carried to Trim, where he was arreigned and adiudged to be pressed to death, and
so he died in prison.</p>
<p>But now to returne vnto the dooings in time of Bignors gouernment. Immediatlie
<note place="marg">The lord Birmingham and other capteins against the Scots.</note>
vpon his arriuall, the lord Iohn Birmingham being generall of the field, and
hauing with him diuerse capteins of worthie fame, namelie sir Richard Tute, sir
Miles Verdon, sir Hugh Trippetton, sir Herbert Sutton, sir Iohn Cusacke, sir
Edmund Birmingham, sir William Birmingham, Walter Birmingham the primat of
Armagh, sir Walter de la Pulle, and Iohn Maupas led forth the kings power, to
the number of one thousand thr&eacute;e hundred foure and twentie able men against
Edward Bruse, who being accompanied with the lord Philip Mowbraie, the lord
Walter de Soules, the lord Alaine Steward, with his thr&eacute;e brethren, sir Walter, and
sir Hugh, sir Robert, and sir Aimerie Lacies, and others, was incamped not past
two miles from Dundalke with three thousand men, there abiding the Englishmen,
to fight with them if they came forward: which they did with all conuenient sp&eacute;ed,
being as desirous to giue battell as the Scots were to receiue it.</p>
<p>The primat of Armagh personallie accompanieng the English power, &amp; blessing
<note place="marg">The primat of Armagh.</note>
their enterprise, gaue them such comfortable exhortation, as he thought serued the
time yer they began to incounter. And herewith buckling togither, at length the

<!--<fw place="bot-right">"Scots"</fw>-->


<pb n="251"/>

<!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-right">"251"</fw>-->


Scots fullie and wholie were vanquished, and two thousand of them slaine, togither
<note place="marg">The battell of Armagh.</note>

<note place="marg">The Scots vanquished.</note>

<note place="marg">Edward Bruse slaine.</note>
with their capteine Edward Bruse. Maupas that pressed into the throng to
incounter with Bruse hand to hand, was found in the search dead aloft vpon the
slaine bodie of Bruse. The victorie thus obteined vpon saint Calixtus daie, made
an end of the Scotish kingdome in Ireland, &amp; lord Birmingham sending the head of
Bruse into England, or as Marlburrow hath, being the messenger himselfe, presented
it to king Edward, who in recompense gaue to him and his heires males the earledome
of Louth, and the baronie of Ardich and Athenrie to him and his heirs
<note place="marg">Birmingham made earle of Louth.</note>

<note place="marg">Sir Richard de Clare slaine.</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1319</date></note>
generall for euer. Shortlie after sir Richard de Clare with foure other knights of
name, and manie other men of warre were slaine in Thomond. The lord Roger
Mortimer came againe into Ireland to gouerne as lord iustice there now the second
time, and the townes of Athessell and Plebs were burned by the lord Fitzthomas
brother to the lord Maurice Fitzthomas. And about this season the bridge
of Kilcolin was builded by Maurice Iakis.</p>
<p>In the yeare following, to wit, one thousand thr&eacute;e hundred and twentie, which
<note place="marg"><date>1320</date></note>

<note place="marg">The earle of Kildare lord iustice.</note>

<note place="marg">An vniuersitie erected at Dublin.</note>
was the fouret&eacute;enth yeare of king Edwards reigne, Thomas Fitziohn earle of Kildare
was made lord iustice of Ireland. Here is to be remembred, that about this time
also Alexander Bignor archbishop of Dublin sent to pope Iohn the two and twentith,
for a priuilege to institute an vniuersitie within the citie of Dublin, and his sute tooke
effect: and the first thr&eacute;e doctors of diuinitie did the said archbishop himselfe creat,
William Harditie a frier preacher, Henrie Cogie a frier minor, and frier Edmund
Bernerden: and beside these one doctor of canon law, to wit, Richard archdeacon
of saint Patrikes that was chancellor of the same vniuersitie, who kept their terms
and commensements solemnlie: neither was this vniuersitie at anie time since disfranchised,
but onlie through change of times discontinued, and now since the
dissoluing of monasteries vtterlie decaied.</p>
<p>A motion was made (as Campion hath noted) in a parlement holden there, whilest
sir Henrie Sidneie was the qu&eacute;enes lieutenant, to haue it againe erected, by waie of
contributions to be laid togither: the said sir Henrie offering twentie pounds lands,
and an hundred pounds in monie. Other there were also, that according to their
abilities and deuotions followed with their offers. The name was deuised; A
worthie plantation of Plantagenet &amp; Bullogne. But while they disputed of a conuenient
place for it, and of other circumstances, they let fall the principall.</p>
<p>In the yeare one thousand three hundred twentie and one, there was a great
slaughter made of the Oconhurs at Balibagan, by the English of Leinster and Meth.
<note place="marg"><date>1321</date></note>
And Iohn Birmingham earle of Louth was lord iustice of Ireland. Vnto this man,
whilest he was lord iustice, the king wrote, commanding him to be with him at
<note place="marg"><emph>Rec. Turris.</emph></note>
Carleill in the octaues of the Trinitie, in the fift&eacute;enth yeare of his reigne, with thr&eacute;e
hundred men of armes, one thousand hobellars, and six thousand footmen, ech of
them armed with an aketon, a sallet, and gloues of maill, which number was to be
leuied in that land: besides thr&eacute;e hundred men of armes which the earle of Vlster
was appointed to serue within that iournie, which the king at that time intended to
make against the Scots. The date of the letter was the third of Aprill. In the
yeare one thousand thr&eacute;e hundred twentie and two, diuerse nobles in Ireland
<note place="marg"><date>1322</date></note>
departed this life, as the lord Richard Birmingham, the lord Edmund Butler, and
the lord Thomas Persiuall. Moreouer, the lord Andrew Birmingham, and sir
<note place="marg"><date>1323</date></note>

<note place="marg">Iohn Darcie lord iustice.</note>
Richard de la Lond were slaine by Onolan. In the eighteenth y&eacute;ere of king
Edward the second his reigne, the lord Iohn Darcie came into Ireland to be lord
iustice, and the kings lieutenant there. In these daies liued in the diocesse of
<note place="marg">The ladie Alice Kettle accused of sorcerie.</note>
Ossorie the ladie Alice Kettle, whome the bishop ascited to purge hir selfe of the
fame of inchantment and witchcraft imposed vnto hir, and to one Petronill and
Basill hir complices. She was charged to haue nightlie conference with a spirit

<!--<fw place="bot-center">"2 K 2"</fw>--><!--<fw place="bot-right">"called"</fw>-->


<pb n="252"/>

<!--<fw place="top-left">"252"</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>-->


called Robin Artisson, to whome she sacrificed in the high waie nine red cocks, and
nine peacocks eies. Also that she swept the streets of Kilkennie betw&eacute;ene compleine
and twilight, raking all the filth towards the doores of hir sonne William
Outlaw, murmuring &amp; muttering secretlie with hir selfe these words:

<quote rend="block"><lg>
<l>To the house of William my sonne,</l>
<l>Hie all the wealth of Kilkennie towne.</l>
</lg></quote></p>

<p>At the first conuiction they abiured &amp; did penance, but shortlie after they were
found in relapse, &amp; then was Pentronill burnt at Kilkennie, the other twaine might
not be heard of. She at the houre of hir death accused the said William as priuie to
their sorceries, whome the bishop held in durance nine w&eacute;eks, forbidding his keepers
to eat or to drinke with him, or to speake to him more than once in the daie.
But at length, thorough the sute and instance of Arnold le Powre then seneschall of
Kilkennie, he was deliuered, and after corrupted with bribes the seneschall to persecute
the bishop; so that he thrust him into prison for thr&eacute;e moneths. In rifling
the closet of the ladie, they found a water of sacramentall bread, hauing the diuels
name stamped thereon in st&eacute;ed of Iesus Christ, and a pipe of ointment, wherewith she
greased a staffe, vpon the which she ambled and gallopped thorough thicke and thin,
when and in what maner she listed. This businesse about these witches troubled all
the state of Ireland, the more; for that the ladie was supported by certeine of the
nobilitie, and lastlie conueied ouer into England, since which time it could neuer
be vnderstood what became of hir. In the yeare one thousand three hundred
twentie and six, &amp; last of king Edwards the seconds reigne, Richard Burgh earle of
Vlster departed this life.</p>
</div>

<div n="Edward3" type="chronicle">
<head>Edward the third.</head>
<p>VNNETH was the businesse about the witches at an end, when it was signified,
<note place="marg"><date>1326</date></note>
that a gentleman of the familie of the Otoolies in Leinster, named Adam Duffe,
<note place="marg"><date>1327</date></note>
possessed by some wicked spirit of error, denied obstinatelie the incarnation of our
sauior, the trinitie of persons in the vnitie of the Godhead, &amp; the resurrection of the
<note place="marg">Adam Duffe an heretike.</note>
flesh; as for the holie scripture, he said it was but a fable: the virgin Marie he
affirmed to be a woman of dissolute life, and the apostolike s&eacute;e erronious. For such
assertions he was burnt in Hogging greene beside Dublin. About the same time,
Fitzarke Macmorch, and sir Henrie Traherne were taken prisoners. In the yeare
following, the lord Thomas Fitziohn erle of Kildare, and the lord Arnold Powre &amp;
William earle of Vlster were sent ouer into Ireland, &amp; Roger Outlaw prior of saint
<note place="marg">The prior of Kilmainan lord iustice.</note>
Iohns of Ierusalem in Ireland, commonlie called the prior of Kilmainan, was
made lord iustice. This man by reason of variance that chanced to rise betwixt
the Giraldins, the Butlers, and Birminghams, on the one side; and the Powres &amp;
Burghs on the other, for terming the earle of Kildare a rimer, to pacifie the parties
called a parlement, wherein he himselfe was faine to make his purgation of a slander
imposed to him, as suspected of heresie.</p>
<p>The bishop of Ossorie had giuen an information against Arnold le Powre, conuented
<note place="marg">Arnold Powre accused of heresie.</note>
&amp; conuicted in his consistorie of certeine hereticall opinions, but bicause the
beginning of Powrs accusation concerned the iustices kinsman, and the bishop was
mistrusted to prosecute his owne wrong, and the person of the man rather than the
fault: a daie was limited for the iustifieng of the bill, the partie being apprehended
and respited therevnto. This dealing the bishop (who durst not stirre out of

<!--<fw place="bot-right">"Kilkennie"</fw>-->


<pb n="253"/>

<!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-right">"253"</fw>-->


Kilkennie to prosecute his accusation) was reputed parciall: and when by meanes
hereof the matter hanged in suspense, he infamed the said prior as an abbettor and
fauourer of Arnolds heresie. The prior submitted himselfe to the triall, and therevpon
were seuerall proclamations made in court, that it should be lawfull to anie man
to come into the court, and to inferre, accuse, and declare what euidence he could,
against the lord iustice: but none came. Then passed a decr&eacute;e by the councell,
commanding all bishops, abbats, priors, and the maiors of Dublin, Corke, Limerike,
Waterford, and Droghedagh, the shirifs, knights, &amp; seneschals of euerie shire, to
appeare at Dublin. From amongst all these, they appointed six inquisitors, which
examining the bishops and other persons aforesaid singularlie one by one, found
that with an vniuersall consent they deposed for the prior, affirming that (to their
iudgements) he was a zelous and a faithfull child of the catholike church. In the
meane time, Arnold le Powre the prisoner deceased in the castell, &amp; bicause he
stood vnpurged, long he laie vnburied.</p>
<p>In the yeare one thousand thr&eacute;e hundred twentie and nine, Iohn de Birmingham
<note place="marg"><date>1329</date></note>

<note place="marg">The earle of Louth slaine.</note>
earle of Louth, and his brother Peter, with many other of that surname, and
Richard Talbot of Malahide were slaine on Whitsun euen at Balibragan by men of
the countrie. Also the lord Thomas Butler, and diuerse other noblemen were
<note place="marg">The lord Butler slaine.</note>
slaine by Mac Gogoghdan &amp; other Irishmen n&eacute;ere to Molinger. For the Irish as
well in Leinster as in Meth made insurrections in that season, and so likewise did
they in Mounster vnder the leading of Obren, whom William earle of Vlster and
Iames earle of Ormond vanquished. So outragious were the Leinster Irish, that in
one church they burnt foure score innocent soules, asking no more but the life of
their priest then at masse, whome they notwithstanding sticked with their iauelins,
spurned the host, and wasted all with fire: neither forced they of the popes interdiction,
nor anie ecclesiasticall censures denounced against them (matters of no small
consideration among them namelie in those daies) but maliciouslie perseuered in the
course of their furious rage, till the citizens of Wexford somewhat tamed them,
and slue foure hundred of them in one skirmish, the rest flieng were all drenched in
the water of Slane. In the yeare one thousand thr&eacute;e hundred and thirtie, the earle
<note place="marg"><date>1330</date></note>

<note place="marg">The prior of Kilmainan lord iustice.</note>
of Vlster with a great armie made a iournie against Obren, and the prior of Kilmainan
lord iustice put Maurice Fitzthomas earle of Desmond in prison in the
marshalseie, out of the which he fr&eacute;elie escaped, and the lord Hugh Lacie returned
into Ireland, and obteined the kings peace and fauour.</p>
<p>In the yeare one thousand thr&eacute;e hundred thirtie and one, the earle of Vlster
<note place="marg"><date>1331</date></note>
passed ouer into England, and great slaughter was made vpon the Irish in Okenslie.
Also the castell of Arclo was taken by the Irishmen, and great slaughter made of
the English in the Cowlagh by Otothell and others. Also the lord Anthonie Lucie
<note place="marg">Anthonie Lucie lord iustice.</note>
was sent ouer lord iustice into Ireland, and great slaughter was made of the Irish at
Thurlis by the knights of the countrie, &amp; at Finnath in Meth, there were manie of
them slaine by the English; but yet was the castell of Fernis taken and burnt by
the Irish. On the feast daie of the assumption of our ladie, which falleth on the
fift&eacute;enth of August, Maurice Fitzthomas earle of Desmond was apprehended at
<note place="marg">The earle of Desmond apprehended,</note>
Limerike by the lord iustice, and sent vnto the castell of Dublin. Moreouer, the
lord iustice tooke sir William Birmingham at Clomell by a wile, whilest he was sicke
in his bed, &amp; sent him (togither with his sonne Walter Birmingham) vnto the castell
<note place="marg"><date>1332</date></note>

<note place="marg">William Birmingham executed.</note>
of Dublin, the thirtith of Aprill. In the yeare one thousand three hundred thirtie
and two the said sir William was hanged at Dublin, but Walter was deliuered by
reason he was within orders.</p>
<p>Campion following such notes as he hath s&eacute;ene, writeth that the death of this
<note place="marg"><emph>Campion.</emph></note>
William Birmingham chanced in time of the gouernement of William Outlaw prior

<!--<fw place="bot-right">"of"</fw>-->


<pb n="254"/>

<!--<fw place="top-left">"254"</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>-->


of Kilmainan, being lieutenant vnto Iohn lord Darcie, that was made lord iustice
(as the said Campion hath noted in the yeare one thousand thr&eacute;e hundred twentie
and nine. Although Marlburrow affirmeth that he came thither to beare that office,
in the yeare one thousand thr&eacute;e hundred thirtie and two, after the lord Lucie was
discharged, as hereafter shall be recited. But whensoeuer, or vnder whome soeuer
Birmingham was executed, he was accounted an od knight, and such a one as for
his valiancie, his match was not lightlie to be anie where found. The castell of
Clonmore was taken the same yeare by the Englishmen, and the castell of Bonrath
was destroid by the Irish of Thomond. Also Henrie de Mandeuill was taken and
sent prisoner to be safelie kept in Dublin. Likewise Walter Burgh with two of his
bretheren were taken in Connagh by the earle of Vlster, and sent to the castell of
Norburgh.</p>
<p>This yeare the lord Antonie Lucie was discharged of his roome by the king, and
so returned with his wife &amp; children into England, and the lord Iohn Darcie was
<note place="marg">The lord Darcie iustice.</note>
sent ouer lord iustice in Lucies place, and great slaughter was made vpon Bren Obren,
and Mac Arthie in Mounster, by the English of that countrie. This Iohn Darcie
(as should appeare by gifts bestowed vpon him by the king) was in singular fauour
with him. Amongst other things which he had of the kings gift, we find that he had
the manors of Louth, and Baliogarie, and other lands in Ireland which belonged to
the earle of Ew. And for that the said earle was a Frenchman, and tooke part with
<note place="marg">The earle of Ew.</note>
Philip de Valois the kings enimie, they were seized into the kings hand. The earle
of Desmond vpon suerties was set at libertie, and by the parlement holden at Dublin
in this yeare 1333, was sent ouer into England vnto the king; and William erle of
<note place="marg"><date>1333</date></note>

<note place="marg">A parlement.</note>
Vlster a yoong gentleman of twentie yeares of age, in going towards Knockfergus
the seauenth of Iune, was slaine neere to the foords in Vlster, by his owne people,
but his wife and daughter escaped into England: and the daughter was after maried
vnto the lord Lionell the kings sonne. She deceased afterwards at Dublin, and left
a daughter behind hir that was his heire, maried to Roger Mortimer earle of March,
and lord of Trim.</p>
<p>This murther was procured by Robert Fitzmartine Mandeuill, who was the first
that presumed to giue to the earle anie wound. To reuenge the death of this earle of
<note place="marg">The earle of Vlster slaine.</note>
Vlster (slaine as yee haue heard beside Knockfergus) the lord iustice Darcie with a
great power went into Vlster, to pursue those that through Mandeuils seditious
tumults had so traitorouslie murthered their lord. At his setting forward, the said
iustice Darcie appointed sir Thomas Burgh treasuror, to gouerne as lieutenant to him
<note place="marg">Sir Thomas Burgh.</note>
in his absence. When the lord iustice had punished the traitors in Vlster, he passed
ouer into Scotland, there to make warre against the Scots that were enimies
<note place="marg">The lord iustice inuadeth Scotland.</note>
at that present to the king of England, and on the feast daie of saint Margaret,
great slaughter was made of the Scots by the Irishmen: and so what by the king in
one part, and the lord iustice of Ireland in another, Scotland was in maner wholie
conquered, and Edward Balioll was established king of Scotland. The lord iustice
might haue possessed the Iles if they had b&eacute;ene worth the k&eacute;eping: into the which
Iles, except the said Darcie and the earle of Sussex late lieutenant of Ireland, no
gouernor at anie time yet aduentured. At Darcies comming backe into Ireland,
and exercising the office of lord iustice, he deliuered Walter Birmingham out of the
castell of Dublin.</p>
<p>In the yeare 1336, and tenth of Edward the thirds reigne, on S. Laurence daie,
<note place="marg"><date>1336</date></note>
the Irish of Connagh were discomfited and put to flight by the Englishmen of the
countrie there, with the losse of one Englishman, and ten thousand of the enimies.
<note place="marg"><date>1337</date></note>
The lord Iohn Charleton baron came into Ireland to be lord iustice, and with him
his brother Thomas bishop of Hereford lord chancellor, and John Rice lord treasuror,
<note place="marg">Sir Iohn Charleson iustice.</note>

<!--<fw place="bot-right">"and"</fw>-->


<pb n="255"/>

<!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-right">"255"</fw>-->


and two hundred Welshmen souldiors. The bishop was ordeined afterward lord
<note place="marg"><date>1338</date></note>

<note place="marg">The bishop of Hereford lord iustice.</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1340</date></note>

<note place="marg">Iohn Darcie lord iustice during life.</note>

<note place="marg">Calling in of liberties.</note>
iustice, in whose time all the Irish of Ireland were at defiance with the English, and
shortlie brought againe into quiet by the earles of Kildare and Desmond. The lord
Iohn Darcie by the kings letters patents was (during life) ordeined lord iustice of
Ireland, in the fourt&eacute;enth yeare of king Edward the thirds reigne, which king abused
by evill counsell and sinister informers, called in vnder his signet roiall, the franchises,
liberties and grants, whatsoeuer had b&eacute;ene deuised, made and ratified to the
realme of Ireland, and to euerie each person thereof. This reuoking of liberties was
displeasantlie taken. The English of birth and the English of blood falling at words,
were divided into factions about it, for which contention the Irish still waited, so as
the realme was euen vpon the point to giue ouer all, and to rebell. For redresse
whereof, the lord iustice called a parlement at Dublin, to the which the nobles
refused to come, and in quiet wise assembled themselues togither at Kilkennie,
where they with the commons agreed vpon certeine questions to be demanded of the
king by waie of supplication, signifieng in the same partlie their gr&eacute;efes. Which
questions were in effect as followeth.</p>
<p>1 How a realme of warre might be gouerned by one both vnskilfull and vnable
<note place="marg">Articles or questions.</note>
in all warlike seruice?</p>
<p>2 How an officer vnder the king, that entered verie poore, might in one yeare
grow to more excessiue wealth, than men of great patrimonie and liuelihood in
manie yeares?</p>
<p>3 How it chanced, that sith they were all called lords of their owne, that the
souereigne lord of them all was not a pennie the richer for them?</p>
<p>The cheefe of them that thus seemed to repine with the present gouernment, was
Thomas Fitzmaurice earle of Desmond, through whose maintenance and bearing
out of the matter, the countrie was in great trouble; so as it had not lightlie be&eacute;ne
s&eacute;ene, that such contrarietie in minds and disliking had appeared amongst those of
the English race, in that realme at anie time before. H&eacute;erewith Rafe Vffort was sent
<note place="marg"><date>1343</date></note>

<note place="marg">Rafe Vffort lord iustice.</note>
ouer lord iustice, who bringing his wife with him, the countesse of Vlster arriued
about the thirt&eacute;enth of Julie. This man was verie rigorous, and through persuasion
(as was said) of his wife, he was more extreame and couetous than otherwise he
<note place="marg">The countesse of Vlster.</note>
would haue b&eacute;ene, a matter not to be forgotten. For if this ladie had b&eacute;ene as
readie to mooue hir husband to haue shewed himselfe gentle and mild in his
gouernement, as she was bent to pricke him forward vnto sharpe dealings and rigorous
proc&eacute;edings, she had beene now aswell reported of, as she is infamed by their
pens that haue registred the dooings of those times. But to the purpose. This
Vffort lord iustice, in paine of forfeiture of all his lands, commanded the earle of
<note place="marg">The earle of Desmond.</note>
Desmond to make his personall appearance at a parlement, which he called to
be holden at Dublin, there to begin the seuenth of Iune. And bicause the earle
refused to come acording to the summons, he raised the kings standard, and with
an armie marched into Mounster, and there seized the earles possessions into
the kings hands, letting them foorth to farme for an annuall rent vnto other
persons.</p>
<p>And whilest he yet remained in Mounster, he deuised waies how to haue the earle
of Desmond apprehended: which being brought to passe, he afterward deliuered
him vpon mainprise of these suerties whose names insue. William de Burgh earle of
<note place="marg">Suerties for the earle of Desmond.</note>
Vlster, Iames Butler earle of Ormond, Richard Tute, Nicholas Verdon, Morice
Rochford, Eustace le Powre, Gerald de Rochford, Iohn Fitzrobert Powre, Robert
Barrie, Maurice Fitzgirald, Iohn Wellesleie, Walter le Fant, Richard Rokelleie,
Henrie Traherne, Roger Powre, Iohn Lenfant, Roger Powre, Matthew Fitzhenrie,
Richard Walleis, Edmund Burgh sonne to the earle of Vlster, knights: Dauid Barrie

<!--<fw place="bot-right">"William,"</fw>-->


<pb n="256"/>

<!--<fw place="top-left">"256"</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>-->


William Fitzgirald, Foulke de Fraxinus, Robert Fitzmaurice, Henrie Fitzberkleie,
Iohn Fitzgeorge de Roch, Thomas de Lees de Burgh. These (as y&eacute;e haue
heard) were bound for the earle. And bicause he made default, the lord iustice
verelie tooke the aduantage of the bond against the mainpernours, foure of them
onelie excepted, the two earles and two knights.</p>
<p>The lord iustice is charged with strict dealing by writers in this behalfe, for that
<note place="marg">Vffort euill spoken of.</note>
the same persons had assisted him in his warres against Desmond. But trulie if we
shall consider the matter with indifferencie, he did no more than law and reason required.
For if euerie suertie vpon forfeiture of his bond should be forborne, that
otherwise dooth his duetie, what care would men haue either to procure suerties or to
become suerties themselues? But such is the affection of writers, speciallie when
they haue conceiued anie misliking towards those of whome they take occasion
to speake, so as manie a worthie man hath b&eacute;ene defamed, and with slander greatlie
defaced in things wherein he rather hath deserued singular commendation. But
howsoeuer this matter was handled touching the earle of Desmond, vpon the death
<note place="marg">Ioie conceiued for the death of the lord iustice Vffort.</note>
of the lord iustice, which insued the next yeare, bonfiers were made, and great ioy
shewed through all the relme of Ireland. His ladie verelie (as should appeare) was
but a miserable woman, procuring him to extortion and briberie. Much he abridged
the prerogatiues of the church, and was so hated, that euen in the sight of the countrie
he was robbed without rescue by Mac Cartie, notwithstanding he gathered
power, and dispersed those rebels of Vlster. Robert Darcie was ordeined iustice by
<note place="marg"><date>1346</date></note>

<note place="marg">Robert Darcie lord iustice.</note>
the councell till the kings letters came to sir Iohn Fitzmaurice, who released Fitzthomas
earle of Kildare left in durance by Vffort at his death. Fitzmaurice continued
not long, but was discharged, and the lord Walter Birmingham elected to succeed in
<note place="marg">Iohn Fitzmorice iustice.</note>

<note place="marg">L. Birmingham iustice.</note>
that roome, who procured a safe conduct for Desmond to plead his cause before the
king, by whom he was liberallie intreated, and allowed towards his expenses there
twentie shillings a day at the princes charge. In consideration of which courtesie
shewed to his kinsman, the earle of Kildare, accompanied with diuerse lords, knights,
and chosen horssemen, serued the king at Calis, a towne thought impregnable, &amp;
returned after the winning thereof in great pompe and iollitie.</p>
<p>We find that Thomas Berkeleie, and Reinold lord Cobham, and sir Morice Berkleie
<note place="marg"><date>1347</date></note>

<note place="marg"><emph>Record. Tur.</emph></note>
became mainpernours for the said earle of Desmond, that he should come into
England, and abide such triall as the law would award. Iohn Archer prior of Kilmainan
<note place="marg"><date>1348</date></note>

<note place="marg">The prior of Kilmainan.</note>

<note place="marg">Baron Carew iustice.</note>

<note place="marg">Sir Thomas Rokesbie iustice.</note>

<note place="marg"><emph>Record. Tur.</emph></note>
was substituted lieutenant to the lord iustice. To whom succ&eacute;eded Baron
Carew, and after Carew followed sir Thomas Rokesbie knight, vnto whom was
assigned aboue his ordinarie retinue of twentie men of armes, a supplie of ten men
of armes, and twentie archers on horssebacke, so long as it should be thought n&eacute;edfull.
Great mortalitie chanced this yeare, as in other parts of the world, so especiallie
in places about the seacoasts of England and Ireland. In the yeare following
<note place="marg"><date>1349</date></note>
departed this life Alexander Bignor archbishop of Dublin. And the same yeare was
Iohn de saint Paule consecrated archbishop of that see. This yeare deceased Kemwrike
<note place="marg">Iohn de S. Paule archbishop of Dublin.</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1350</date></note>

<note place="marg">Kemwrike Shereman.</note>
Shereman sometime maior of Dublin, a great benefactor to euerie church
and religions house within twentie miles round about the citie. His legacies to the
poore and others, beside his liberalitie shewed in his life time, amounted to thr&eacute;e
thousand marks.</p>
<p>In this season dwelled in Vlster a welthie knight one sir Robert Sauage, who the
<note place="marg">Sir Robert Sauage.</note>
rather to preserue his owne, began to wall and fortifie his manor houses with castels
and piles against the Irish enemie, exhorting his heire Henrie Sauage to applie that
worke so beneficiall for himselfe &amp; his posteritie. "Father (quoth yoong Sauage) I
remember the prouerbe 'Better a castell of bones than of stones.' Where strength &amp;
courage of valiant men are prest to helpe vs, neuer will I (by the grace of God)

<!--<fw place="bot-right">"cumber"</fw>-->


<pb n="257"/>

<!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-right">"257"</fw>-->


cumber my selfe with dead walles. My fort shall be where soeuer yoong blouds be
stirring, &amp; where I find roome to fight." The father in a fume let lie the building,
and forsware to go anie further forward in it. But yet the want therof and such like
hath beene the decaie as well of the Sauages, as of all the English gentlemen in Vlster:
as the lacke also of walled townes is one of the principall occasions of the rude
wildnesse in other parts of Ireland.</p>
<p>This Sauage, having prepared an armie against the Irish, allowed to euerie
souldier before they should buckle with the enimie, a mightie draught of <emph>Aqua vit&oelig;,</emph>
wine, or old ale, and killed in prouision for their returne, b&eacute;efe, venison, and fowle,
great plentie: which dooings diuerse of his capteins misliked, bicause they considered
the successe of warre to be vncerteine, and therefore est&eacute;emed it better
policie to poison the cates, or to doo them awaie, than to k&eacute;epe the same; and happilie
to f&eacute;ed a sort of roges with such princelie food, if ought should happen to
themselues in this aduenture of so few against so manie. Herat smiled the gentleman
and said, "Tush ye are too full of enuie: this world is but an in, to the which
ye haue no speciall interest, but are onelie tenants at will of the Lord. If it please
him to command vs from it as it were from our lodging, and to set other good
fellowes in our roomes, what hurt shall it be for vs to leaue them some meat for their
suppers? Let them hardlie win it &amp; weare it. If they enter our dwellings, good
maner would no lesse but to welcome them with such fare as the countrie br&eacute;edeth,
and with all my heart much good may it doo them. Notwithstanding I presume so
far vpon your noble courages, that verelie my mind giueth me we shall returne at
night, &amp; banket our selues with our owne store. And so did, hauing slain 3000
Irishmen.</p>
<p>In the yeare 1355 deceased Maurice Fitzthomas earle of Desmond lord iustice of
<note place="marg"><date>1355</date></note>

<note place="marg">The earle of Desmond lord iustice deceased.</note>

<note place="marg">Thomas Rokesbie lord iustice his saieng.</note>
Ireland, who had that office of the kings grant for terme of life. After him succ&eacute;eded
in that roome Thomas de Rokesbie, a knight, sincere and vpright of conscience,
who being controlled for suffering himselfe to be serued in tr&eacute;ene cups, answered:
"Those homelie cups &amp; dishes paie trulie for that they conteine: I had rather
drinke out of tr&eacute;ene cups &amp; paie gold and siluer, than drinke out of gold &amp;
make woodden paiment. This yeare began great variance betwixt Richard Rafe primat
<note place="marg"><date>1357</date></note>

<note place="marg">Dissention betwixt the primat of Armagh, &amp; the foure orders of friers.</note>

<note place="marg">Thr&eacute;e lord iustices.</note>

<note place="marg"><emph>Record. Tur.</emph></note>
of Armagh, &amp; foure orders of begging friers, which ended at length by the
deaths of the said Richard Rafe, and Richard Kilminton, in the yeare 1360: Rafe
deceasing in the popes court, and Kilminton in England. Almerike de S. Amand,
Iohn or (as other haue) Iames Butler earle of Ormond, and Maurice Fitzthomas
earle of Kildare, were appointed lord iustices of Ireland by turnes. In Ormonds
time, and in the thr&eacute;e and twentith yeare of king Edward the thirds reigne, order
was taken that the Irish lords should remaine and dwell in their houses on the
marches, to defend the subiects from inuasions of enimies. And further, proclamation
went foorth, that no m&eacute;ere Irish borne should be made maior, bailiffe, porter,
officer, or minister in anie towne or place within the English dominions: nor that
anie archbishop, abbat, prior, or anie other being of the kings allegiance, vpon forfeiture
of all that he might forfeit, should aduance anie that was m&eacute;ere Irish borne to
the roome of a canon, or to haue anie other ecclesiasticall benefice that laie among
the English subiects.</p>
<p>To Maurice Thomas earle of Kildare, when he was ordeined lord iustice, the
<note place="marg">The earle of Kildare lord iustice.</note>
kings letters assigned in yearelie fee for his office 500 pounds, with condition, that
the said gouernour should find twentie great horsses to serue in the field, he himselfe
to be the twentith man in going against the enimie: which allowance and conditions
in those daies (so farre as I can gesse) should s&eacute;eme to be ordinarie to the office.
Lionell duke of Clarence sonne to king Edward the third, came ouer into Ireland to
<note place="marg">Lionell duke of Clarence.</note>

<!--<fw place="bot-left">"VOL. VI."</fw>--><!--<fw place="bot-center">"2 L"</fw>--><!--<fw place="bot-right">"be"</fw>-->


<pb n="258"/>

<!--<fw place="top-left">"258"</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>-->


be lord justice there, and was in right of his wife earle of Vlster. He published an
inhibition to all of the Irish birth not once to approch his armie, nor to be in anie
wise imploied in seruice of the wars. He vanquished Obren, but yet sudenlie (no
man vnderstanding how) an hundred of his souldiers were wanting as they laie in
garrison, the losse of whom was thought to be occasioned by that displeasant decree
afore rehearsed. Wherevpon he tooke better aduise, and receiued the Irish into like
fauour, as other lieutenants had them in before that present, shewing a tender loue
towards them all, and so euer after prospered in his affaires. He created diuerse
knights, as Preston, now knowne by the name of the familie of Gormanston, Holiewood,
Talbot, Cusac, de la Hide, Patrike, Robert and Iohn de Fraxinis: all these
being gentlemen of worthie fame in chiualrie. The excheker he remooued to Catherlagh,
&amp; bestowed in furnishing that towne fiue hundred pounds.</p>
<p>In the yeare 1362 Iohn de S. Paule archbishop of Dublin departed this life the
<note place="marg"><date>1362</date></note>
fift ides of September. And in the yeare following was Thomas Minot consecrated
archbishop of that place. Girald Fitzmaurice earle of Desmond was appointed lord
<note place="marg"><date>1367</date></note>

<note place="marg">The lord Windsor lieutenant.</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1369</date></note>

<note place="marg"><emph>Record. Turris.</emph></note>

<note place="marg">A parlement.</note>

<note place="marg">A subsidie.</note>
iustice, vntill the comming of the lord Windsor, the first lieutenant in Ireland, who
came ouer in the yeare 1369. This Windsore called a parlement at Kilkennie, in
the which was granted to the king a subsidie of three thousand pounds to be leuied of
the people, subjects to the king in that land. And in an other parlement holden by
him at Balidoill they granted two thousand pounds to be likewise leuied. Which
said sums were granted of the m&eacute;ere and fr&eacute;e good wils of the nobles and communaltie
of the land, towards the maintenance of the kings expenses in his warres.
Yet the king in the three and fortith yeare of his reigne, directing his letters vnto
the said lord Windsor, c&omacr;manded him to surcease from leuieng the foresaid monie,
although afterwards he commanded againe that the arrerages should be leuied and
paid to his lieutenant the said Windsor.</p>
<p>The third pestilence in Ireland made awaie a great number of people. In the
<note place="marg">Mortalitie of people.</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1370</date></note>

<note place="marg">Conhur.</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1372</date></note>

<note place="marg">Sir Richard Ashton lord iustice.</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1373</date></note>

<note place="marg">Slaughter.</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1375</date></note>
yeare 1370 the lord Gerald Fitzmorice earle of Desmond, and the lord Iohn Fitzrichard,
and the lord Iohn Fitziohn, and manie other noble men were slaine by
Obren, and Mac Conmard of Thomond in the moneth of Iulie. In the yeare 1372 sir
Richard Ashton was sent ouer to be lord iustice in Ireland. In the yeare following
great warre was raised betwixt the English of Meth, and Offeroll, in the which manie
vpon both sides were slaine. In Maie, the lord Iohn Husseie baron of Galtrim,
Iohn Fitzrichard shiriffe of Meth, and William Dalton were slaine in Kinaleigh.
In the yeare 1375 Thomas archbishop of Dublin departed this life, and the same
yeare was Robert de Wikeford consecrated archbishop there.</p>
</div>

<div n="Richard2" type="chronicle">
<head>Richard the second. </head>

<p>EDMUND Mortimer earle of March &amp; Vlster was made the kings lieutenant
<note place="marg"><date>1381</date></note>

<note place="marg">The earle of March the kings lieutenant.</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1383</date></note>

<note place="marg"><date>1385</date></note>
in Ireland. In the yeare 1383 a great mortalitie reigned in that countrie. This was
called the fourth pestilence. In the y&eacute;ere 1385 Dublin bridge fell. Beside Edmund
Mortimer earle of March, Campion affirmeth, that in this Richard the seconds daies,
there are iustices and lieutenants of Ireland speciallie recorded; Roger Mortimer
sonne to the said Edmund, Philip Courtneie the kings cousine, Iames earle of
Ormond, and Robert Vere earle of Oxford, marquesse of Dublin lord chamberleine,
who was also created duke of Ireland by parlement, and was credited with the whole
dominion of the realme by grant for tearme of life, without paieng anie thing therefore,
passing all writs, and placing all officers, as chancellor, treasuror, chiefe iustice,
admerall, his owne lieutenant, and other inferiour charges under his owne Teste. In

<!--<fw place="bot-right">"the"</fw>-->


<pb n="259"/>

<!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-right">"259"</fw>-->


the yeare 1390, Robert de Wikeford archbishop of Dublin departed this life, and the
<note place="marg"><date>1390</date></note>
same yeare was Robert Waldebie translated vnto the archbishop of Dublin an
Augustine frier.</p>
<p>In the yeare 1394, king Richard sore afflicted and troubled in mind with sorrow
<note place="marg"><date>1394</date></note>

<note place="marg">King Richard goeth ouer into Ireland.</note>
for the decease of his wife qu&eacute;ene Anne, that departed this life at Whitsuntide last
past, not able without teares to behold his palaces and chambers of estate, that represented
vnto him the solace past, &amp; doubled his sorrow, sought some occasion of
businesse: and now about Michaelmas passed ouer into Ireland, where diuerse lords
and princes of Vlster renewed their homages, &amp; placing Roger Mortimer erle of
March his lieutenant, returned about Shrouetide. In the yeare 1397, Richard de
<note place="marg">Roger Mortimer lord lieutenant.</note>

<note place="marg"><emph>Thom. Wals.</emph></note>

<note place="marg"><date>1397</date></note>
Northalis archbishop of Dublin departed this life, that was the same yeare from
another see remooued thither: he was a frier of the order of the Carmelites.</p>
<p>The same yeare Thomas de Craulie was chosen and consecrated archbishop of
Dublin. Also sir Thomas de Burgh, and sir Walter de Birmingham, slue six hundred
<note place="marg">Six hundred Irishmen slaine.</note>
Irishmen, with their capteine Macdowne. Moreouer, Edmund earle of March
lord deputie of Ireland, with the aid of the erle of Ormond, wasted the countrie of
an Irish lord called Obren, and at the winning of his chiefe house he made seuen
knights, to wit, sir Christopher Preston, sir Iohn Bedlow, sir Edmund Londores, sir
Iohn Londores, sir William Nugent, Walter de la Hide, and Robert Cadell. But
after this it chanced, that on the Ascension daie, certeine Irishmen slue fortie Englishmen:
and among them these were accounted as principall, John Fitzwilliams,
Thomas Talbot, and Thomas Cambrie. But shortlie after Roger Mortimer earle of
March and Vlster the kings lieutenant was slaine, with diuerse other, by Obren and
other Irishmen of Leinster at Kenlis. Then was Roger Greie elected lord iustice of
<note place="marg">Roger Greie lord iustice of Ireland.</note>
Ireland.</p>
<p>The same yeare on the feast daie of saint Marke the pope, the duke of Surreie
landed in Ireland, and with him came sir Thomas Craulie the archbishop of Dublin.
King Richard informed of the vnrulie parts and rebellious sturres of the Irishmen,
minded to appease the same, and speciallie to reuenge the death of the earle of
<note place="marg"><date>1398</date></note>

<note place="marg">King Richard passeth the second time ouer into Ireland.</note>
March: wherevpon with a nauie of two hundred sails he passed ouer into Ireland,
and landed at Waterford on a sundaie, being the morrow after saint Petronilla the
virgins day. The fridaie after his arriual at Ford in Kenlis within the towne of Kildare,
there were slaine two hundred Irishmen by Ienicho de Artois a Gascoigne,
and such Englishmen as he had with him: and the morrow after, the citizens of
Dublin brake into the countrie of Obren, slue thirtie &amp; thr&eacute;e of the enimies, and
tooke fourescore men with children.</p>
<p>The fourth kalends of Iulie, king Richard came to Dublin, and remained there
<note place="marg">The king commeth to Dublin.</note>
for a time; during the which diuerse lords and princes of the countrie came in and
submitted themselues vnto him, by whome they were courteouslie vsed, and trained
to honourable demeanor and ciuilitie, as much as the shortnes of time would permit,
<note place="marg">S&eacute;e more here of in England.</note>
as in the English historie you maie find set foorth more at large. Whilest king
Richard thus laie in Dublin to reduce Ireland into due subiection, he was aduertised
that Henrie duke of Lancaster, that latelie before had b&eacute;ene banished, was returned,
&amp; ment to bereaue him of the crowne. The sonne of which duke, togither
with the duke of Glocesters sonne, the king shut vp within the castell of Trim, and
then taking the seas, he returned and landed in Wales, where he found his defense so
weake, and vnsure, that finallie he came into his aduersaries hands, and was deposed
by authoritie of parlement, and then was the said duke of Lancaster admitted to
reigne in his place.

<!--<fw place="bot-center">"2 L 2"</fw>--><!--<fw place="bot-right">"Henrie "</fw>-->
</p>
</div>

<pb n="260"/>

<div n="Henry4" type="chronicle">
<head>
<!--<fw place="top-left">"260"</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>-->

Henrie the fourth. </head>

<p>AT Whitsuntide in the yeare 1400, which was the first yeare of the reigne of
<note place="marg"><date>1400</date></note>
Henrie the fourth, the conestable of Dublin castell, and diuerse other at Stanford
in Vlster, fought by sea with Scots, where manie Englishmen were slaine and
drowned. In the second yeare of king Henrie the fourth, sir Iohn Stanleie the
<note place="marg"><date>1401</date></note>

<note place="marg">Sir Iohn Stanleie lord lieutenant.</note>

<note place="marg">Sir Stephan Scroope.</note>
kings lieutenant in Ireland returned into England, leauing his vnder lieutenant there
sir William Stanleie. The same yeare on Bartholomew &eacute;euen, sir Stephan Scroope,
deputie vnto the lord Thomas of Lancaster the kings brother, and lord lieutenant of
Ireland, arriued there to supplie the roome of Alexander bishop of Meth, that
exercised the same office vnder the said lord Thomas of Lancaster, before the
comming of this sir Stephan Scroope; which sir Stephan for his violence and extortion
before time vsed in the same office vnder king Richard, was sore cried out vpon
by the voices of the poore people, insomuch that the ladie his wife hearing of such
exclamations, would in no wise continue with him there, except he would receiue a
solemne oth on the bible, that wittinglie he should wrong no christian creature
in that land, but dulie and trulie he should s&eacute;e paiment made for all expenses: and
hereof (she said) she had made a vow to Christ so determinatlie, that vnlesse it were
on his part firmelie promised, she could not without perill of soule go with him.
Hir husband assented and accomplished hir request effectuallie, recouered a good
opinion for his vpright deling, reformed his caters &amp; purueiors, inriched the countrie,
mainteined a plentifull house, remission of great offenses, remedies for persons
indangered to the prince, pardons of lands and liues he granted so charitablie and
so discr&eacute;etlie, that his name was neuer recited among them without manie blessings
and praiers, and so ch&eacute;erefullie they were readie to serue him against the Irish vpon
all necessarie occasions. The lord Thomas of Lancaster the kings sonne, and lord
lieutenant of Ireland, arriued the same yeare at Dublin, vpon saint Brices daie.</p>
<p>The maior of Dublin Iohn Drake, with a band of his citizens neere to Bre, slue
<note place="marg">The Irish ouershrowne by the maior of Dublin.</note>
foure thousand of the Irish outlawes (as Campion noteth out of the records of
Christs church) but Marlburrow speaketh onelie of 493, and these being all men of
warre. The verie same daie that this victorie was atchiued, to wit, the eleuenth
day of Iulie, the church of the friers prechers of Dublin was dedicated by the archbishop
of that citie. The same yeare in September, a parlement was holden at
Dublin, during the which in Vrgile sir Bartholomew Verdon knight, Iames White,
Stephan Gernon, and other their complices, slue the shiriffe of Louth Iohn Dowdall.
In the yere 1403, in Maie, sir Walter Betterleie steward of Vlster, a right valiant
<note place="marg"><date>1403</date></note>
knight was slaine, and to the number of thirtie other with him. The same yeare
about the feast of saint Martin, the lord Thomas of Lancaster the kings sonne
returned into England leauing the lord Stephan Scroope his deputie there: who also
<note place="marg">Stephan Scroope.</note>

<note place="marg">The earle of Ormond lord iustice.</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1404</date></note>

<note place="marg">The archbishop of Armagh deceased.</note>
in the beginning of Lent sailed ouer into England, and then the lords of the land
chose the earle of Ormond to be lord iustice.</p>
<p>In the fift yere of Henrie the fourth, Iohn Colton archbishop of Armagh the seuen
&amp; twentith of Aprill departed this life, vnto whom Nicholas Stoning succ&eacute;eded.
The same yeare on the daie of saint Vitale the martyr, the parlement of Dublin
began before the earle of Ormond then lord iustice of Ireland, where the statutes
of Kilkennie and Dublin were confirmed, and likewise the charter of Ireland. In
the sixt yeare of Henrie the fourth, in the moneth of Maie, thr&eacute;e Scotish barks
<note place="marg"><date>1405</date></note>
were taken, two at Green castell, and one at Alkeie, with capteine Macgolagh.
The same yeare the merchants of Brodagh entered Scotland, and tooke preies and
pledges. Also on the &eacute;euen of the feast day of the seuen brethren, Oghgard was

<!--<fw place="bot-right">"burnt"</fw>-->


<pb n="261"/>

<!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-right">"261"</fw>-->


burnt by the Irish. And in Iune sir Stephan Scroope that was come againe into
Ireland, returned eftsoones into England, leauing the earle of Ormond lord iustice
of Ireland. About the same time they of Dublin entered Scotland at saint Ninian,
<note place="marg">The citizens of Dublin inuade Scotland.</note>

<note place="marg">They inuade Wales.</note>
and valiantlie behaued themselues against the enimies, and after crossing the seas,
directed their course into Wales, and did much hurt to the Welshmen, bringing
from thense the shrine of saint Cubins, &amp; placed it in the church of the Trinitie
in Dublin. Iames Butler earle of Ormond died at Baligam, whilest he was lord
<note place="marg">The earle of Ormond deceased.</note>
iustice, vnto whom succeeded Gerald earle of Kildare.</p>
<p>In the seuenth yeare of king Henrie on Corpus Christi day, the citizens of Dublin
with the countrie people about them, manfullie vanquished the Irish enimies, and
slue diuerse of them, and tooke two ensignes or standards, bringing with them to
Dublin the heads of those whom they had slaine. The same yeare the prior of
Conall, in the plaine of Kildare, fought manfullie with the Irish, &amp; vanquished two
hundred that were well armed, slaieng part of them, and chasing the residue out of
the field, and the prior had not with him past the number of twentie Englishmen:
but God (as saith mine author) assisted those that put their trust in him. The same
<note place="marg"><emph>Hen. Marlb.</emph></note>
yeare after Michaelmas, Stephan Scroope deputie iustice to the lord Thomas of
Lancaster the kings sonne, and his lieutenant of Ireland, came againe ouer into Ireland.
And in the feast of saint Hilarie was a parlement holden at Dublin, which in
<note place="marg">A parlement at Dublin.</note>
Lent after was ended at Trim. And Meiler de Birmingham slue Cathole Oconhur
about the end of Februarie. In the yere 1407, a certeine false and heathenish
<note place="marg"><date>1407</date></note>
wretch an Irishman, named Mac Adam Mac Gilmore, that had caused fortie
churches to be destroied, as he that was neuer christened, and therefore called Corbi,
<note place="marg">Corbi what it signifieth.</note>
chanced to take prisoner one Patrike Sauage, and receiued for his ransome two
thousand markes, though afterwards he slue him, togither with his brother Richard.</p>
<p>The same yeare in the feast of the exaltation of the crosse, Stephan Scroope deputie
to the lord Thomas of Lancaster, with the earles of Ormond and Desmond,
and the prior of Kilmainan, and diuerse other capteins and men of warre of Meth,
set from Dublin, and inuaded the land of Mac Murch, where the Irish came into
the field and skirmished with them, so as in the former part of the daie they put the
English power to the woorse; but at length the Irish were vanquished and chased,
so that Onolan with his son and diuerse others were taken prisoners. But the
English capteins aduertised here, that the Burkens and Okeroll in the countie of
Kilkennie, had for the space of two daies togither doone much mischief, they rode
with all sp&eacute;ed vnto the towne of Callan, and there incountering with the aduersaries,
manfullie put them to flight, slue Okeroll, and eight hundred others. There went a
<note place="marg">Okeroll slaine.</note>
tale, and beleeued of manie, that the sunne stood still for a space that daie, till the
Englishmen had ridden six miles: so much was it thought that God fauoured the
English part in this enterprise, if we shall bel&eacute;eue it.</p>
<p>The same yeare the lord Stephan Scroope passed once againe ouer into England,
and Iames Butler earle of Ormond was elected by the countrie lord iustice of Ireland.
In the dais of this K. Henrie the fourth, the inhabitants of Corke being sore
afflicted with perpetuall oppressions of their Irish neighbors, complained themselues
in a generall writing directed to the lord Rutland and Corke, the kings deputie
there, and to the councell of the realme then assembled at Dublin: which letter
because it openeth a window to behold the state of those parties, and of the whole
realme of Ireland in those daies, we haue thought good to set downe here, as it hath
beene enterd by Campion, according to the copie deliuered to him by Francis
Agard esquire, one of the queenes maiesties priuie councell in Ireland.

<!--<fw place="bot-right">"A letter"</fw>-->
</p>

<pb n="262"/>

<p>
<!--<fw place="top-left">"262"</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>-->
<text>
		  <front>
		    <docTitle>
		      <titlePart>A letter from Corke out of an old record that beareth no date.</titlePart>
		    </docTitle>
		  </front>
<body>
		    <div type="letter">
<p>"IT may please your wisedomes to haue pittie on vs the kings poore subiects
within the countie of Corke, or else we are cast awaie for euer. For where there
are in this countie these lords by name, beside knights, esquiers, gentlemen, and
yeomen, to a great number that might dispend yearelie eight hundred pounds, sixe
hundred pounds, foure hundred pounds, two hundred pounds, one hundred pounds,
an hundred markes, twentie markes, twentie pounds, ten pounds, some more,
some lesse, to a great numbers, besides these lords. First the lord marques
Caro, his yearelie reuenues was beside Dorseie hauen and other cr&eacute;ekes, two
thousand two hundred pounds sterling. The lord Barneuale of B&eacute;erhauen, his yearelie
reuenue was beside Bodre hauen and other cr&eacute;ekes, one thousand six hundred pounds
sterling. The lord Wogan of the great castell, his yearelie reuenue beside his hauens
<note place="marg">I thinke rather Gr&eacute;ene castell.</note>
and cr&eacute;ekes, thirt&eacute;ene thousand pounds. The lord Balram of Enfort, his yearelie reuenue
beside hauens and creekes, one thousand thr&eacute;e hundred pounds sterling.
The lord Curcie of Kelbretton, his yearelie reuenue beside hauens and cr&eacute;ekes, one
thousand two hundred pounds sterling. The lord Mandeuile of Barenstellie, his
yearelie reuenue beside havenr and creekes, one thousand two hundred pounds
sterling. The lord Arundell of the Strand, his yearelie reuenue beside hauens
and cr&eacute;ekes, one thousand fine hundred pounds sterling. The lord Barod of
the gard, his yearelie reuenues beside hauens &amp; cr&eacute;ekes one thousand one hundred
pounds sterling. The lord Steineie of Baltmore, his yearelie reuenue beside
hauens and cr&eacute;ekes, eight hundred pounds sterling. The lord Roch of Poole
castell, his yearelie reuenues besides hauens and creekes, ten thousand pounds sterling.
The kings maiestie hath the lands of the late yoong Barrie by forfeiture, the
yearelie reuenue whereof, besides, two riuers and cr&eacute;ekes, and all other casualties, is
one thousand eight hundred pounds sterling.</p>
<p>"And that at the end of this parlement, your lordship, with the kings most noble
councell may come to Corke, &amp; call before you all these lords, and other Irishmen,
and bind them in paine of losse of life, lands and goods, that neuer one of them doo
make warre vpon an other, without licence or commandement of you my lord
deputie, and the kings councell; for the vtter destruction of these parts is that
onelie cause. And once all the Irishmen, and the kings enimies were driuen into
a great vallie called Clane onight, betwixt two great mounteines called Maccort,
or the leprous Iland: and there they liued long and manie yeares with their white
meat, till at the last these English lords fell at variance amongst themselues, and then
the weakest part tooke certeine Irishmen to take their part, and so vanquished their
enimies. And thus fell the English lords at warre among themselues, till the
Irishmen were stronger than they, and draue them awaie, and now haue the
countrie whole vnder them; but that the lord Roch, the lord Barrie, and the lord
Curcie onelie remaine with the least part of their ancestors possessions: and yoong
Barrie is there vpon the kings portion, paieng his grace neuer a pennie rent.
Wherefore we the kings poore subiects of the citie of Corke, Kinsale, and Yoghall,
desire your lordship to send hither too good iustices to s&eacute;e this matter ordred,
and some English capteins with twentie Englishmen that may be capteins ouer
vs all: and we will rise with them to redresse these enormities all at our owne
costs. And if you will not come nor send, we will send ouer to our liege lord
the king, and complaine on you all."</p>
		      <trailer>Thus far that letter.</trailer>
</div></body></text>
</p>

<p>And (as saith Campion) at this daie the citie of Corke is so incumbred with vnquiet
<note place="marg">The citie of Corke.</note>

<!--<fw place="bot-right">"neighbors"</fw>-->


<pb n="263"/>

<!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-right">"263"</fw>-->


neighbors of great power, that they are forced to gard their gates continuallie, &amp;
to k&eacute;epe them  shut at seruice times, at meales, and from sun setting to sun
rising, not suffering anie stranger to enter the towne with his weapon, but to
leaue the same at a lodge appointed. They dare vnneth at anie time walke abroad
far from the towne for their recreation, except at seasons; and then with strength
of men furnished with armor and weapon for their safegard. They match in wedlocke
among themselues, so that weln&eacute;ere the whole citie is alied and ioined togither in consanguinitie.
But now to returne vnto the dooings of the earle of Ormond that was
placed lord iustice in Scroops roome. We doo find that in the yeare 1408 he
<note place="marg"><date>1408</date></note>

<note place="marg">A parlement at Dublin.</note>
called a parlement at Dublin, in which the statutes of Kilkennie and Dublin
were eftsoones reuiued, and certeine ordinances established vnder the great seale
of England against purueiors. The same yeare, the morrow after Lammas daie,
<note place="marg">The lord Thomas of Lancaster commeth ouer into Ireland.</note>
the lord Thomas of Lancaster sonne to king Henrie the fourth, lord lieutenant of
Ireland, landed at Carlingford, and in the w&eacute;eke following he came vnto Dublin,
and put the earle of Kildare vnder arrest, comming to him with three of his
familie. He lost all his goods, being spoiled &amp; rifled by the lord lieutenant his
seruants, &amp; himselfe kept still in prison in the castell of Dublin, till he had paid 300
marks fine.</p>
<p>On the daie of saint Marcell the martyr deceased the lord Stephan Scroope at Tristeldermot.
<note place="marg">The lord Scroope deceaseth.</note>
The same yeare also was the lord Thomas of Lancaster at Kilmainan wounded
(I know not how) and vnneth escaped with life, and after caused summons to be
giuen by proclamation, that all such as ought by their tenures to serue the
king, should assemble at Rosse. And after the feast of saint Hilarie, he held a
parlement at Kilkennie for a tallage to be granted. And after the thirt&eacute;enth of
<note place="marg">The lord Thomas returneth into England.</note>
March, he returned into England, leauing the prior of Kilmainan for his deputie
in Ireland. This yeare also Hugh Macgilmore was slaine in Cragfergus within
the church of the friers minors, which church he had before destroied, and broken
downe the glasse windowes to haue the iron bars, thorough which his enimies the
Sauages entred vpon him. This yeare being the tenth of Henrie the fourth, in
<note place="marg"><date>1409</date></note>

<note place="marg">Iames de Artois.</note>

<note place="marg">The sword giuen to the citie of Dublin.</note>
Iune, Ianico de Artois with the Englishmen slue foure score of the Irish in Vlster.
This yeare king Henrie gaue the sword to the citie of Dublin, which citie was
first gouerned (as appeareth by their ancient scale called <emph>Signum pr&oelig;positur&oelig;</emph>) by
a prouost: and in the thirteenth of Henrie the third by a maior and two bailiffes,
<note place="marg">Bailiffes changed into shiriffes.</note>
which were changed into shiriffes, by charter granted by Edward the sixt,
1547.</p>
<p>This maioralitie, both for state and charge of office, and for bountifull hospitalitie,
exc&eacute;edeth anie citie in England, London excepted. In the yeare following, the
<note place="marg"><date>1410</date></note>
one and twentith daie of Maie, a parlement began at Dublin, which lasted thr&eacute;e
w&eacute;ekes, the prior of Kilmainan sitting as lord iustice. The same yeare, the two
and twentith of Iune, the same iustice tooke the castels of Mibraclide, Oferoll,
and de la Mare. Ireland this yeare was sore afflicted for want of corne. The lord
iustice entred into the land of Obren with 1500 Kernes, of which number eight hundred
<note place="marg">A iournie made by the lord iustice.</note>
reuolted to the Irish, so that if the power of Dublin had not beene there, it had
gon euil with the lord iustice: and yet he escaped not without losse, for Iohn Derpatrike
was slaine there. In the yeare 1411, mariages were celebrated among the
<note place="marg"><date>1411</date></note>

<note place="marg">Mariages.</note>
nobilitie in Ireland. William Preston maried the daughter of Edward Paris, and Iohn
Wogan matched with the eldest daughter of Christopher Preston; and Walter de
la Hide with the second daughter of the same Christopher. In the yeare 1412, about
<note place="marg"><date>1412</date></note>

<note place="marg">Oconthir.</note>
the feast of Tibertius and Valerianus, which falleth on the tenth of April, Oconthir
did much mischiefe in Meth, and tooke 160 Englishmen. The same yeare Odoles
a knight, and Thomas Fitzmorice fought togither, and either slue other. The foure
<note place="marg">The bishop of Meth deceaseth.</note>
and twentith of Maie, Robert Mounteine bishop of Meth departed this life, to

<!--<fw place="bot-right">"whome"</fw>-->


<pb n="264"/>

<!--<fw place="top-left">"264"</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>-->


whome succ&eacute;eded Edward de Audiscie sometime archdecon of Cornwall. This yeare
<note place="marg">The death of Henrie the fourth.</note>
on saint Cutberts daie king Henrie the fourth departed this life.</p>
</div>

<div n="Henry5" type="chronicle">
<head><emph>Henrie the fift.</emph></head>

<p>In the first yeare of this king, the fiue and twentith of September, landed in
<note place="marg"><date>1413.</date></note>

<note place="marg">Iohn Stanleie the kings lieutenant in Ireland.</note>
Ireland at Clawcarfe, Iohn Stanlie the kings lieutenant of that land. He departed
this life the 18 of Ianuarie next insuing at Athird, in Latine called <emph>Atrium Dei.</emph>
After his decease, Thomas Crauleie archbishop of Dublin was chosen lord iustice of
<note place="marg">Thomas Crauleie archbishop of Dublin.</note>
Ireland. Ianico de Artois led foorth a power against Maginors, a great lord of Ireland,
but n&eacute;ere to a place called Inor manie Englishmen were slaine. The morrow
after saint Matthias daie, a parlement began againe at Dublin, which continued
<note place="marg">A parlement</note>
for the space of fift&eacute;ene daies, in which meane time the Irish did much hurt by
inuasions made into the English pale, and burning vp all the houses afore them
that stood in their waie, as their vsuall custome was in times of other parlements:
wherevpon a tallage was demanded, but not granted. In the yeare 1414, the Englishmen
<note place="marg"><date>1414</date></note>
fought with the Irish neere to Kilka, and slue an hundred of the enimies, whilest
the archbishop being lord iustice in Tristeldermot, went in procession with his
cleargie; praieng for the good sp&eacute;ed of his men and other of the countrie
that were gone foorth to fight with the aduersaries. In the feast of saint Gordian
and Epirnachus, to wit the tenth of Maie, were the English of Meth discomfited
by Oconthir and his Irish, where they slue Thomas Maureuar baron of Serin; and
there were taken prisoners Christopher Fleming, John Dardis, and diuerse others,
<note place="marg">Englishmen slaine.</note>
beside manie that were slaine.</p>
<p>On saint Martins &eacute;euen sir Iohn Talbot of Holomshire, lord Furniuale landed at
<note place="marg">Iohn lord Talbot of Sherfield.</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1415</date></note>

<note place="marg">Robert Talbot deceaseth.</note>
Dalkeie, the kings lieutenant in Ireland, a man of great honor. In the yeere one
thousand foure hundred and fift&eacute;ene in Nouember, Robert Talbot, a right noble
man that walled the suburbs of Kilkennie, departed this life. Also Patrike Baret
bishop of Fernis deceased, and was buried among the canons at Kenlis. This
yeare on the feast daie of Geruasius and Prothasius which falleth on the ninet&eacute;enth
of Iune, the lord lieutenants wife the ladie Furniuall was brought to bed at Finglasse
of a sonne named Thomas. About the same time also Stephan Fleming archbishop
<note place="marg"><date>1416</date></note>

<note place="marg">The archbishop of Armagh deceaseth.</note>
of Armagh departed this life, after whome succ&eacute;eded Iohn Suanig. On the daie of
saint Laurence the lord Furniuals sonne Thomas Talbot that was borne at Finglasse in
Nouember last past, departed this life, and was buried in the qu&eacute;ere of the friers preachers
church in Dublin. About the same time the Irish fell vpon the Englishmen, and slue
manie of them, among other Thomas Balimore of Baliquelan was one. The parlement
which the last yeare had beene called and holden at Dublin, was this
<note place="marg">The parlement remooued to Trim.</note>
yeare remooued to Trim, &amp; there began the eleuenth of Maie, where it continued
for the space of eleuen daies, in the which was granted to the lord lieutenant a
subsidie in monie.</p>
<note place="marg">A subsidie.</note>
<p>In the yeare following, the archbishop of Dublin passed ouer into England, and
<note place="marg"><date>1417</date></note>

<note place="marg">The archbishop of Dublin deceased.</note>

<note place="marg">His praise.</note>
deceased at Faringdon, but his bodie was buried in the new college at Oxford.
This man is greatlie praised for his liberalitie, he was a good almesman, a great
clerke, a doctor of diuinitie, an excellent preacher, a great builder, beautifull, tall
of stature, and sanguine of complexion. He was foure score and ten yeares of age
when he died, and had gouerned the church of Dublin in good quiet for the
space of twentie yeeres. This yeare shortlie after Easter, the lord deputie spoiled
<note place="marg"><date>1418</date></note>
the tenants of Henrie Crus, and Henrie Bethat. Also at Olane on the
feast daie of saint Iohn and saint Paule, the erle of Kildare, sir Christopher

<!--<fw place="bot-right">"Preston,"</fw>-->


<pb n="265"/>

<!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-right">"265"</fw>-->


Preston, and sir Iohn Bedlow were arrested and committed to ward within the
castell of Trim, because they sought to commune with the prior of Kilmainan.</p>
<p>The nine and twentith of Iune Matthew Husseie baron of Galtrim deceased, &amp;
was buried at the friers preachers of Trim. In the yeare one thousand foure hundred
<note place="marg"><date>1419</date></note>

<note place="marg">A councell or parlement holden.</note>
&amp; ninet&eacute;ene a roiall councell was holden at Naas, where was granted to the lord
lieutenant a subsidie in monie. The same yeare vpon Cenethursdaie Othoell tooke
foure hundred kine that belonged vnto Balimore, so breaking the peace contrarie to
his oth. The fourth ides of Maie, Mac Murch ch&eacute;efe capteine of his nation, and
<note place="marg">Mac Murch taken prisenor.</note>
of all the Irish in Leinster was taken prisoner, and the same daie was sir Hugh
Cokeseie made knight. The last of Maie the lord lieutenant, and the archbishop
of Dublin with the maior rased the castell of Keninie. The morrow after the feast
daie of Processus and Martinianus, that is the twentith of Iune, the lord William
de Burgh and other Englishmen slue flue hundred Irishmen, &amp; tooke Okellie. On the
<note place="marg">Okellie taken.</note>
feast daie of Marie Magdalen the lord lieutenant Talbot returned into England, leauing
his deputie there the archbishop of Dublin. This yeare about saint Laurence
daie, diuerse went foorth of Ireland to serue the king in his warres of Normandie,
as Thomas Butler that was prior of Kilmainan, and manie others. Iohn Fitzhenrie
<note place="marg">The prior of Kilmainan went to serue the king in France.</note>
succ&eacute;eded the said Butler in gouernment of the priorie of Kilmainan. The
archbishop of Dublin that remained as lord deputie slue thirtie Irishmen n&eacute;ere
vnto Rodiston. Also the thirteenth of Februarie Iohn Fitzhenrie prior of Kilmainan
departed this life, and William Fitzthomas was chosen to succ&eacute;ed in his place, and
was confirmed the morrow after saint Valentines daie.</p>
<p>Iames Butler earle of Ormond appointed the kings lieutenant in Ireland, in place
<note place="marg"><date>1420</date></note>

<note place="marg">Iames Butler erle of Ormond lord lieutenant.</note>
of Iohn lord Talbot and Furniuall, landed at Waterford about the fourth ides of Aprill:
and shortlie after his comming ouer, he caused a combat to be fought betwixt two
of his cousins, of whom the one was slaine in that place, and the other carried awaie
sore wounded. On saint Georges daie, he held a councell in Dublin, &amp; summoned
<note place="marg">A parlement summoned.</note>
a parlement to begin there the seuenth of Iune. In the meane while he fetcht great
booties out of the countries of the Irish lords, Oralie, Mac Mahun, and Maginois.
But first yer we go further to shew what Marlburrow hath noted of the dooings,
whilest this earle of Ormond gouerned as the kings lieutenant in Ireland, we haue
thought good to set downe what Campion also writeth thereof, as thus.</p>
<p>In the red moore of Athie (the sunne almost lodged in the west, and miraculouslie
<note place="marg"><emph>Iames Young</emph> an author alleaged by <emph>Campion.</emph></note>

<note place="marg">The sunne staieth his course.</note>
standing still in his epicicle by the space of thr&eacute;e houres, till the feat was accomplished,
and no hole nor quakemire in all that bog annoieng either horsse or man
of his part) he vanquished Omore and his terrible armie with a few of his owne meinie,
and with the like number he ouercame Arthur Mac Morogh, at whose might
&amp; puisance all Leinster trembled. To the instruction of this mans worthinesse, the
compiler of certeine precepts touching the rule of a common-wealth exciteth his lord
the said earle in diuerse places of that worke incidentlie, eftsoons putting him in mind
that the Irish are false by kind, that it were expedient, and a worke of charitie to
execute vpon them wilfull and malicious transgressors the kings lawes somewhat
sharplie, that Odempsie being winked at a while, abused that small time of sufferance
to the iniurie of the earle of Kildare, intruding vniustlie vpon the castell of Leie, from
whense the said deputie had iustlie expelled him, and put the earle in possession
thereof, that notwithstanding their oths and pledges, they are yet no longer true than
they f&eacute;ele themselues the weaker. This deputie tamed the Brens, the Burghs, Mac
Banons, Oghaghucaght, Moris Mac Mahun, all the capteins of Thomond: &amp; all this
he did in thr&eacute;e months; the clergie twise euerie weeke in solemne procession praieng
for his good succes against those disordered persons, which now in euerie part of Ireland 
<!--<fw
place="bot-left">"VOL. VI."</fw>--><!--<fw place="bot-center">"2 M"</fw>--><!--<fw place="bot-right">"land"</fw>-->


<pb n="266"/>

<!--<fw place="top-left">"266"</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>-->


degenerated from the English ciuilitie, to their old trade of life vsed in that
countrie, repined at the English maner of gouernment. So far Campion.]</p>
<p>Diuerse parlements vpon prorogations were holden in time that this earle of
Ormond was gouernor. The first began at Dublin the seauenth of Iune in this
<note place="marg"><date>1420</date></note>

<note place="marg">The parlement began.</note>
yeare one thousand foure hundred and twentie, which continued about sixt&eacute;en
daies. At this parlement was granted to the lord lieutenant a subsidie of seauen
hundred marks. At the sixt&eacute;ene daies end this parlement was adiorned till the
mondaie after saint Andrews daie. In the same parlement the debts of the lord Iohn
Talbot, which were due to certeine persons for vittels and other things, taken vp
whilest he was lord lieutenant there, were reckoned vp; which lord Talbot verelie, for
that he saw not the creditors satisfied before his comming awaie, was partlie euill
spoken of in the countrie. The morrow after the feast of Simon and Iude, the
castell of Colmolin was taken by Thomas Fitzgirald. And on saint Katharins eeuen,
<note place="marg">The castell of Colmolin.</note>

<note place="marg">The earle of Ormonds son and heire borne.</note>
the sonne and heire of the earle of Ormond lord lieutenant was borne, for the which
there was great reioising. In the parlement begun againe at Dublin the mondaie
after saint Andrews daie, an other subsidie of thr&eacute;e hundred marks was granted
vnto the lord lieutenant. And after they had sat thirt&eacute;ene daies, it was eftsoons
adiorned vntill the mondaie after saint Ambrose daie. Then rumors were spred
abrode, that Thomas Fitz-Iohn earle of Desmond was departed this life at Paris
vpon saint Laurence daie, after whome succ&eacute;eded his vncle Iames Fitzgirald, whome
he had three seuerall times renounced, as one that was a waster of his patrimonie
both in England and Ireland, and not like to come to anie good proofe.</p>
<p>In the yeare one thousand foure hundred twentie and one, the parlement began
<note place="marg"><date>1421.</date></note>

<note place="marg">A parlement.</note>
againe vpon the last prorogation, the mondaie after saint Ambrose daie: in which
parlement it was ordeined that certeine persons should be sent to the king, to
sue that a reformation might be had in matters touching the state of the land.
The ch&eacute;efe of those that were thus sent, were the archbishop of Armagh, and sir
Christopher Preston knight. Moreouer Richard Ohedian bishop of Cashill was accused
<note place="marg">The bishop of Cashill accused.</note>
by Iohn Gese bishop of Lismore and Waterford, who laid thirtie articles vnto
his charge. Amongst other, one was for that he loued none of the English nation,
and that he bestowed not one benefice vpon anie Englishman, and counselled
other bishops that they should not bestow anie within their diocesse vpon anie Englishman.
Moreouer, another article was for counterfeting the kings seale. And
another, for that he went about to make himselfe king of Mounster, and had taken
a ring from the image of saint Patrike (which the earle of Desmond had offered) and
giuen it to his lemman. Manie other crimes were laid to him by the said bishop of
Lismore and Waterford, which he exhibited in writing. Also in the same parlement
there rose contention betwixt Adam Paine bishop of Clone, and another prelat,
whose church he would haue annexed vnto his see. At length, after the parlement
had continued for the space of eight&eacute;ene daies, it brake vp. Herewith came
news of the slaughter of the lord Thomas of Lancaster duke of Clarence, that had b&eacute;ene
<note place="marg">The duke of Clarence slaine in France.</note>
lord lieutenant of Ireland. And vpon the seuenth of Maie certeine of the erle of Ormonds
men were ouerthrowen by the Irish, n&eacute;ere to the abbeie of Leis, and seuen
and twentie Englishmen were slaine there: of whom the cheefe were two gentlemen,
the one named Purcell, &amp; the other Grant. Also ten were taken prisoners,
and two hundred escaped to the foresaid abbeie, so sauing themselues. About
the same time Mac Mahun an Irish lord did much hurt within the countrie of Vrgile,
<note place="marg">Mac Mahun.</note>
by burning &amp; wasting all afore him. Also vpon the morrow after Midsummer
daie, the earle of Ormond lord lieutenant entred into the countrie about Leis

<!--<fw place="bot-right">"vpon"</fw>-->


<pb n="267"/>

<!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-right">"267"</fw>-->


vpon Omordris, and for the space of foure daies togither did much hurt, in slaieng
and spoiling the people, till the Irish were glad to sue for peace.</p>
</div>

<div n="Henry6" type="chronicle">
<head><emph>Henrie the sixt.</emph></head>
<p>LIEUTENANTS to Henrie the sixt ouer the relme of Ireland were these, Edmund
earle of March, and Iames earle of Ormond his deputie; Iohn Sutton, lord
Dudleie, and sir Thomas Strange knight his deputie; sir Thomas Stanleie, and sir
<note place="marg">Here endeth <emph>Marlburrow.</emph> and all that followeth is taken out of <emph>Campion.</emph></note>
Christopher Plunket his deputie. This sir Thomas Stanleie on Michaelmasse daie, in
the twelfe yeare of king Henrie the sixt, with all the knights of Meth &amp; Irrell, fought
against the Irish, slue a great number, &amp; tooke Neill Odonell prisoner.]</p>
<p>Lion lord Wels, and the earle of Ormond his deputie. Iames earle of Ormond by
himselfe, Iohn earle of Shrewesburie, and the archbishop of Dublin lord iustice in
his absence. Richard Plantagenet duke of Yorke, father to king Edward the fourth
&amp; earle of Vlster, had the office of lieutenant by the kings letters patents during
the terme of tenne yeares, who appointed to rule vnder him as his deputies at sundrie
times the baron of Deluin, Richard Fitzeustace knight, Iames earle of Ormond,
<note place="marg"><emph>Campion</emph> out of the records of Christs church.</note>

<note place="marg">George duke of Clarence borne at Dublin.</note>

<note place="marg">Iacke Cade.</note>
and Thomas Fitzmorice earle of Kildare. To this Richard duke of Yorke and Vlster
then resident in Dublin, was borne within the castell there his second sonne
the lord George that was after duke of Clarence. His godfathers at the fontstone
were the earles of Ormond and Desmond. Whether the commotion of Iacke Cade
an Irishman borne, naming himselfe Mortimer, and so pretending cousinage to
diuerse noble houses in this land, proc&eacute;eded from some intelligence with the dukes
fr&eacute;ends here in Ireland, it is vncerteine: but surelie the duke was vehementlie suspected,
and immediatelie after began the troubles, which through him were raised.
Which broiles being couched for a time, the duke held himselfe in Ireland, being
latelie by parlement ordeined protector of the realme of England: he left his
agent in the court, his brother the earle of Salisburie, lord chancellor, to whom
he declared the truth of the troubles then toward in Ireland: which letter exemplified
by sir Henrie Sidneie lord deputie, a great searcher and preseruer of antiquities,
as it came to Campions hands, and by him set downe we haue thought good
likewise to present it here to your view.</p>

<p>
<text><body>
<div type="letter">
<head>To the right worshipfull, and withall mine heart entierelie beloued brother, the earle
of Salisburie.</head>

<note place="marg">The copie of a letter.</note>
<p>RIGHT worshipfull, &amp; with all my hart entierelie beloued brother, I recommend
me vnto you as heartilie as I can. And like it you to wit, sith I wrote last
vnto the king our souereigne lord his highnesse, the Irish enimie, that is to saie
Magoghigam, and with him thr&eacute;e or foure Irish capteins, associat with a great
fellowship of English rebels, notwithstanding that they were within the king our
souereigne lord his peace, of great malice, and against all truth haue maligned
against their legiance, and vengeablie haue brent a great towne of mine inheritance
in Meth, called Ramore, and other villages thereabouts, and murthered
and brent both men, women, and children, withouten mercie: the which enimies
be yet assembled in woods and forts, awaighting to doo the hurt and gr&eacute;euance
to the kings subiects, that they can thinke or imagine. For which cause I write at
this time vnto the kings highnesse, and beseech his good grace for to hasten my pai
ment for this land, according vnto his letters of warrant now late directed vnto the
treasuroe of England, to the intent I may wage men in sufficient number for to resist

<!--<fw place="bot-center">"2 M 2"</fw>--><!--<fw place="bot-right">"the"</fw>-->


<pb n="268"/>

<!--<fw place="top-left">"268"</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>-->


the malice of the same enimies, &amp; punish them in such wise, that other which
would doo the same for lacke of resistance, in time maie take example. For doubtlesse,
but if my paiment be had in all hast, for to haue men of warre in defense
and safegard of this land; my power can not stretch to k&eacute;epe it in the kings obeisance:
and verie necessitie will compell me to come into England to liue there
vpon my poore liuelihood. For I had leaner be dead than anie inconuenience
should fall thervnto by my default: for it shall neuer be chronicled nor remaine in
scripture (by the grace of God) that Ireland was lost by my negligence. And therefore
I bes&eacute;ech you right worshipfull brother, that you will hold to your hands instantlie,
that my paiment maie be had at this time in eschewing all inconucniences.
For I haue example in other places (more pitie it is) for to dread shame, and for
to acquit my troth vnto the kings highnesse, as my dutie is. And this I praie and
exhort you good brother, to shew vnto his good grace, and that you will be so
good, that this language maie be inacted at this present parlement for mine excuse
in time to come, and that you will be good to my seruant Roger Ro the bearer of
<note place="marg">Roger Ro.</note>
these, and to my other seruants, in such things as they shall pursue vnto the kings
highnes, and to giue full faith and credence vnto the report of the said Roger, touching
the said matters. Right worshipfull, and with all my heart entierlie beloned brother,
our blessed Lord God preserue and keepe you in all honour, prosperous estate, and
felicitie, &amp; grant you right good life and long.</p>
			<closer>
<dateline> Written at Dublin the fift&eacute;enth daie of June.</dateline>
<salute>Your faithfull true brother</salute>
<signed>RICHARD YORKE.</signed>
</closer>
</div>
</body></text>
</p>

<p>Of such power was Magoghigam in those daies, who as he wan and kept it by
<note place="marg">Magoghigham his power.</note>
the sword, so now his successors in that state liue but as meane capteins, y&eacute;elding
their winnings to the stronger. This is the miserie of lawlesse people, resembling
the rudenesse of the rude world, wherein euerie man was richer and poorer than
other, as he was in might and violence more or lesse inabled. Here began factions of
the nobilitie in Ireland, fauouring diuerse sides that stroue for the crowne of England.
For the duke of Yorke, in those ten yeares of his gouernement, exc&eacute;edinglie wan the
hearts of the noblemen and gentlemen of that land, of the which diuerse were slaine with
him at Wakefield; as the contrarie part was the next yeare by his sonne Edward earle
of March at Mortimers crosse in Wales. In which meane time the Irish grew hardie,
&amp; vsurped the English countries insufficientlie defended, as they had doone by
like oportunitie in the latter end of Richard the second. These two seasons
set them so aflote, that henseforward they could neuer be cast out from their
forcible possessions, holding by plaine wrong all Vlster, and by certeine Irish tenures
no small portions of Mounster and Connagh, least in Meth and Leinster
where the ciuill subiects of the English bloud did euer most preuaile.</p>
</div>

<div n="Edward4 Edward5" type="chronicle">
<head>Edward the fourth and Edward the fift.</head>

<p>THOMAS Fitzmorice earle of Kildare, lord iustice till the third yeare of Edward
<note place="marg">Lieutenants and deputies in king Edward the fourth his daies.</note>
the fourth, after which time the duke of Clarence, brother to the king, had the
office of lieutenant while he liued, &amp; made his deputies by sundry turnes, Thomas
earle of Desmond, Iohn Tiptoft earle of Worcester the kings cousine, Thomas earle
of Kildare, and Henrie lord Greie of Ruthin. Great was the credit of the Giraldins euer
when the house of Yorke prospered, and likewise the Butlers thriued vnder the bloud
<note place="marg">The Butlers.</note>

<!--<fw place="bot-right">"of"</fw>-->


<pb n="269"/>

<!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND"</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-right">"269"</fw>-->


of the Lancasters: for which cause the earle of Desmond remained mauie yeres
deputie to George duke of Clarence his good brother: but when he had spoken certeine
disdainefull words against the late marriage of king Edward with the ladie Elizabeth
Greie, the said ladie being now queene, caused his trade of life after the Irish
maner, contrarie to sundrie old statutes inacted in that behalfe, to be sifted and
<note place="marg">The earle of Worcester.</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1467</date></note>
examined by Iohn erle of Worcester his successor; so that he was atteinted of treason,
condemned, and for the same beheaded at Droghedagh.</p>
<p>Iames the father of this Thomas earle of Desmond, being suffered and not controlled,
<note place="marg"><emph>Campion</emph> out of Sentleger in his collections.</note>
during the gouernment of Richard duke of Yorke his godcept, and of
mas earle of Kildare his kinsman, put vpon the kings subiects within the countries of
Waterford, Corke, Kerrie, and Limerike, the Irish impositions of quinto and liuerie,
<note place="marg">Irish impositions</note>
cartings, carriages, lodgings, cocherings, bonnaght, and such like, which customes
are the verie br&eacute;eders, mainteiners, and vpholders of all Irish enormities, wringing
from the poore tenants euerlasting sesse, allowance of meat and monie, whereby
their bodies and goods were brought in seruice and thraldome, so that the
men of warre, horsses, and their Galloglasses lie still vpon the farmers, eat
them out, beggar the countrie, foster a sort of idle vagabonds, readie to rebell if
their lord command them, euer nuzled in stealth and robberies.</p>
<p>These euill presidents giuen by the father, the son did exercise, being lord deputie,
to whome the reformation of that disorder speciallie belonged. Notwithstanding
the same fault being winked at in other, and with such rigor auenged in him,
was manifestlie taken for a quarrell sought and procured. Two yeares after, the
<note place="marg"><date>1469</date></note>
said earle of Worcester lost his head, whilest Henrie the sixt taken out of the tower
was set vp againe, and king Edward proclained vsurper, and then was Kildare inlarged,
whom likewise atteinted, they thought also to haue rid, and shortlie both
the earles of Kildare &amp; Desmond were restored to their bloud by parlement. Sir
<note place="marg">Restitution to bloud.</note>

<note place="marg"><date>1470</date></note>

<note place="marg"><emph>Flatsburie.</emph></note>
Rowland Eustace, sometime treasuror and lord chancellor, was lastlie also lord
deputie of Ireland. He founded saint Francis abbeie beside Kilcollen bridge.
King Edward a yeare before his death honored his yoonger sonne (Richard duke of
Yorke) with the title of lieutenant oner this land, which he injoied till his vnnaturall
vncle bereft both him and his brother king Edward the fift of their naturall
lines.</p>
</div>

<div n="Richard3" type="chronicle">
<head>Richard the third.</head>
<p>WHEN this monster of nature &amp; cruell tyrant Richard the third had killed his
<note place="marg">Richard the third.</note>
two yoong nephues, and taken vpon him the crowne &amp; gouernement of England, he
preferred his owne sonne Edward to the dignitie of lord lieutenant of Ireland, whose
deputie was Girald earle of Kildare that bare that office all the reigue of king Richard,
and a while in Henrie the seuenth his daies.</p>
</div>

<div n="Henry7" type="chronicle">
<head><emph>Henrie the seuenth.</emph></head>
<p>TO which earle came the wilie priest sir Richard Simon, bringing with him a lad
<note place="marg">Henrie the seuenth.</note>

<note place="marg">Sir Richard Simon priest.</note>

<note place="marg">Lambert counterfeit to be the earle of Warwike.</note>
that was his scholer, named Lambert, whome he feined to be the sonne of George
earle of Clarence, latelie escaped foorth of the tower of London. And the boie could
reckon vp his pedigr&eacute;e so readilie, &amp; had learned of the priest such princelie behauiour,
that he lightlie mooued the said earle, and manie others the nobles of Ireland
(tendering as well the linage roiall of Richard Plantagenet duke of Yorke, and his

<!--<fw place="bot-right">"sonne"</fw>-->


<pb n="270"/>

<!--<fw place="top-left">"270"</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>-->


sonne George their countrieman borne, as also maligning the aduancement of the
house of Lancaster in Henrie the seuenth) either to thinke or to faiue, that the world
might bel&eacute;eue they thought verelie this child to be Edward earle of Warwike, the
duke of Clarence his lawfull sonne.</p>
<p>And although king Henrie more than halfe marred their sport, in shewing the
right earle through all the str&eacute;ets of London, yet the ladie Margaret duches of
Burgongne, sister to Edward the fourth, hir nephue John de la Poole, the lord
Louell, sir Thomas Broughton knight, and diuers other capteins of this conspiracie,
<note place="marg">The lord Louell.</note>

<note place="marg">Sir Thomas Broughton.</note>
deuised to abuse the colour of this yoong earles name, for preferring their purpose:
which if it came to good, they agr&eacute;ed to depose Lambert, and to erect the verie
earle ind&eacute;ed, now prisoner in the tower, for whose quarrell had they pretended to
fight, they d&eacute;emed it likelie he should haue b&eacute;ene made awaie. Wherefore it was
blazed in Ireland, that the king to mocke his subiects, had schooled a boie to take
vpon him the earle of Warwikes name, and had shewed him about London, to blind
the eies of the simple folke, and to defeat the lawfull inheritour of the good duke of
Clarence their countriman and protector during his life, vnto whose linage they also
deriued title in right to the crowne.</p>
<p>In all hast they assembled at Dublin, and there in Christs church they crowned
<note place="marg">Lambert crowned.</note>
this idoll, honoring him with titles imperiall, feasting and triumphing, raising mightie
shouts and cries, carrieng him from thense to the castell vpon tall men's shoulders,
that he might be seene and noted, as he was sure an honorable child to looke vpon.
Heerewith assembling their forces togither, they prouided themselues of ships, and
imbarking therein, they tooke the sea, and landing in Lancashire, passed forwards,
till they came to Newarke vpon Trent. Therevpon insued the battell of Stoke,
commonlie called Martin Swarts field, wherein Lambert and his maister were taken,
but yet pardoned of life, and were not executed. The erle of Lincolne, the lord
Louell, Martin Swart, the Almaine capteine, and Maurice Fitzthomas capteine of the
Irish, were slaine, and all their power discomfited, as in the English historie it may
<note place="marg"><date>1490</date></note>

<note place="marg">Iasper duke of Bedford lieutenant.</note>
further appeare. Jasper duke of Bedford, and earle of Pembroke lieutenant, and
Walter archbishop of Dublin his deputie.</p>
<p>In this time befell another like Irish illusion, procured by the duchesse aforesaid,
and certeine nobles in England, whereby was exalted as rightfull king of England,
and vndoubted earle of Vlster, the counterfeit Richard duke of Yorke, preserued
from king Richards crueltie (as the adherents faced the matter downe) and with this
<note place="marg">Perkin Warbecke.</note>
maigame lord, named indeed Peter, (in scorne Perkin) Warbecke, they flattered themselues
manie yeares after. Then was sir Edward Poinings knight sent ouer lord deputie,
<note place="marg"><date>1494</date></note>

<note place="marg">Sir Edward Poinings lord deputie.</note>

<note place="marg">Perkin Warbecke taken.</note>
with commission to apprehend Warbecks principall parteners in Ireland:
amongst whom was named Girald Fitzgirald, whose purgation the king (notwithstanding
diuerse surmising and auouching the contrarie) did accept. After much
adoo, Perkin being taken, confessed by his owne writing the course of his whole
life, and all his proceedings in this enterprise, whereof in the English historie, as
we have borowed the same foorth of <emph>Halles</emph> chronicles, yee may read more, and therefore
h&eacute;ere we haue omitted to speake further of that matter.</p>
<p>In the yeare 1501, king Henrie made lieutenant of Ireland his second sonne
<note place="marg"><date>1501</date></note>

<note place="marg">Henrie duke of Yorke, after king Henrie the eight, lord lieuenant.</note>
Henrie, as then duke of Yorke, who after reigned by the name of Henrie the eight.
To him was appointed deputie the foresaid Girald erle of Kildare, who accompanied
with Iohn Blake maior of Dublin, warred vpon William le Burgh, Obren, and
Mac Nemarre, Ocarroull, and fought with the greatest power of Irishmen that had
b&eacute;ene togither since the conquest, vnder the hill of Knocktow, in English the hill
<note place="marg">The field of Knocktow.</note>
of the axes, six miles from Galowaie, and two miles from Belliclare Burghes manour

<!--<fw place="bot-right">"towne."</fw>-->


<pb n="271"/>

<!--<fw place="top-center">"THE CHRONICLES OF IRELAND."</fw>--><!--<fw place="top-right">"271"</fw>-->


towne. Mac William and his complices were there taken, his souldiers that escaped
the sword were pursued fleeing, for the space of fiue miles: great slaughter was
made of them, and manie capteins caught, without the losse of one Englishman.
The earle of Kildare at his returne was made knight of the noble order of the
<note place="marg">The earle of Kildare, knight of the garter.</note>
garter, and liued in worthie estimation all his life long, as well for this seruice,
as diuerse other his famous exploits.</p>
</div>

	      <trailer>Thus farre the Irish Chronicles continued and ended at Henrie the seauenth.</trailer>

	</body>
      </text> <!-- End of Processe -->
</TEI.2>