<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng"	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title type="main">A Speach, As It Was Delivered In The Vpper Hovse Of The Parliament To The Lords Spiritvall And Temporall, And To The Knights, Citizens And Burgesses There Assembled,</title>
    <title type="sub">On Mvnday The XIX. Day Of March 1603. Being The First Day Of The First Parliament.</title>

    <author>James I</author>
    <editor>Charles Howard McIlwain</editor>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
     <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
     <name>Anne Mahoney</name>
     <name>David Smith</name>
     <name>Clifford Wulfman</name>
    </respStmt>
    <funder n="org:Tufts">Tufts University</funder>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent/>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
    <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
    <date type="release" when="2001" cert="high">Perseus 3.0</date>
    <idno type="filename">james1.speech1603.perseus-eng1.xml</idno>
    <availability>
     <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative
      Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
    </availability>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblStruct>
     <monogr>
      <title>The Political Works of James I: Reprinted from the Edition of 1616</title>
      <author>James I</author>
      <editor>Charles Howard McIlwain</editor>
      <imprint>
       <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
       <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
       <date>1918</date>
      </imprint>
     </monogr>
     <ref target="https://archive.org/details/politicalworksj00mcilgoog/page/n387/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
    </biblStruct>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <refsDecl n="CTS">
    <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+).(\w+)"
     replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
     <p>This pointer pattern extracts section.</p>
    </cRefPattern>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <langUsage>
    <language ident="eng">English</language>
    <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
   </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2024-06-03" who="Cliff Wulfman">Epidoc conversion and all matter of changes</change>
   <change when="2000-03-29" who="Tony Lilly">markup</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>

  <body>
   <div type="edition" n="urn:cts:engLit:james1.speech1603.perseus-eng1" xml:lang="eng">
 <div subtype="section" type="textpart" n="1"><head>A SPEACH, AS IT WAS DELIVERED IN THE VPPER HOVSE OF
THE PARLIAMENT TO THE LORDS SPIRITVALL AND
            TEMPORALL, AND TO THE KNIGHTS, CITIZENS
                      AND BURGESSES THERE ASSEMBLED,<lb/>

 ON MVNDAY THE XIX. DAY OF MARCH 1603. BEING THE FIRST DAY OF
                                        THE FIRST PARLIAMENT.</head>

<div subtype="subsection" type="textpart" n="0"><p> IT did no sooner please God to lighten his hand, and relent the violence of his
     deuouring Angel against the poore people of this Citie, but as soone did I
 resolue to call this Parliament, and that for three chiefe and principall reasons:
 The first whereof is, (and which of it selfe, although there were no more, is not
 onely a sufficient, but a most full and necessary ground and reason for conuening
 of this Assembly) This first reason I say is, That you who are here presently
 assembled to represent the Body of this whole Kingdome, and of all sorts of
 people within the same, may with your owne eares heare, and that I out of mine
 owne mouth may deliuer vnto you the assurance of my due thankefulnes for your
 so ioyfull and generall applause to the declaring and receiuing of mee in this
 Seate (which GOD by my Birthright and lineall descent had in the fulnesse of
 time prouided for me) and that, immediatly after it pleased God to call your late
 Soueraigne of famous memory, full of dayes, but fuller of immortall trophes of
 Honour, out of this transitorie life. Not that I am able to expresse by wordes, or
 vtter by eloquence the viue Image of mine inward thankfulnes, but onely that
 out of mine owne mouth you may rest assured to expect that measure of thanke-
 fulnes at my hands, which is according to the infinitenes of your deserts, and to
 my inclination and abilitie for requital of the same. Shall I euer ? nay, can I
 euer be able, or rather so vnable in memorie, as to forget your vnexpected readi-
 nesse and alacritie, your euer memorable resolution, and your most wonderfull
 coniunction and harmonie of your hearts in declaring and embracing mee as your
 vndoubted and lawfull King and Gouernour ? Or shall it euer bee blotted out of
 my minde, how at my first entrie into this Kingdome, the people of all sorts rid
 and ran, nay rather flew to meet mee ? their eyes flaming nothing but sparkles of
 affection, their mouthes and tongues vttering nothing but sounds of ioy, their
 hands, feete, and all the rest of their members in their gestures discouering a pas-
 sionate longing, and earnestnesse to meete and embrace their new Soueraigne.
 <hi rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="la">Quid ergo retribuam</foreign></hi> ? Shall I allow in my selfe, that which I could neuer beare
 with in another ? No I must plainely and freely confesse here in all your au-
 diences, that I did euer naturally so farre mislike a tongue to smoothe, and diligent
 in paying their creditors with lip payment and verball thankes, as I euer sus-
pected that sort of people meant not to pay their debtors in more substantiall


<pb n="270"/>

sort of coyne. And therefore for expressing of my thankefulnesse, I must resort
vnto the other two reasons of my conuening of this Parliament, by them in action
to vtter my thankefulnesse: Both the said reasons hauing but one ground, which
is the deedes, whereby all the dayes of my life, I am by Gods grace to expresse my
said thankfulnesse towards you, but diuided in this, That in the first of these
two, mine actions of thankes, are so inseparably conioyned with my Person, as
they are in a maner become indiuidually annexed to the same: In the other reason,
mine actions are such, as I may either doe them, or leaue them vndone, although
by Gods grace I hope neuer to be weary of the doing of them.
</p>
<p>As to the first: It is the blessings which God hath in my Person bestowed vpon
 you all, wherein I protest, I doe more glorie at the same for your weale, then for
 any particular respect of mine owne reputation, or aduantage therein.

</p></div>
<div subtype="subsection" type="textpart" n="1"><head>1</head>

<p>The first then of these blessings, which God hath ioyntly with my Person sent
vnto you, is outward Peace: that is, peace abroad with all forreine neighbours:
for I thanke God I may iustly say, that neuer since I was a King, I either receiued
wrong of any other Christian Prince or State, or did wrong to any: I haue euer, I
praise God, yet kept Peace and amitie with all, which hath bene so farre tyed to
my person, as at my comming here you are witnesses I found the State embar-
qued in a great and tedious warre, and onely by mine arriuall here, and by the
Peace in my Person, is now amitie kept, where warre was before, which is no smal
blessing to a Christian Common-wealth: for by Peace abroad with their neigh-
bours the Townes flourish, the Merchants become rich, the Trade doeth encrease,
and the people of all sorts of the Land enioy free libertie to exercise themselues in
their seuerall vocations without perill or disturbance. Not that I thinke this out-
ward Peace so vnseparably tyed to my Person, as I dare assuredly promise to my
selfe and to you, the certaine continuance thereof: but thus farre I can very well
assure you, and in the word of a King promise vnto you, That I shall neuer giue
the first occasion of the breach thereof, neither shall I euer be moued for any par-
ticular or priuate passion of mind to interrupt your publique Peace, except I be
forced thereunto, either for reparation of the honour of the Kingdom, or else by
necessitie for the weale and preseruation of the same: In which case, a secure and
honourable warre must be preferred to an vnsecure and dishonourable Peace:
yet doe I hope by my experience of the by-past blessings of Peace, which God
hath so long euer since my Birth bestowed vpon mee, that hee wil not be weary
to continue the same, nor repent him of his grace towards me, transferring that
sentence of King <hi rend="italic">Dauids</hi> vpon his by-past victories of warre, to mine of Peace,
That, <hi rend="italic">that God who preserued me from the deuouring iawes of the Beare and of the
Lion, and deliuered them into my hands, shall also now grant me victory ouer that
vncircumcised Philistine.</hi>

<pb n="271"/>
</p></div>
<div subtype="subsection" type="textpart" n="2"><head>2</head>

<p>But although outward Peace be a great blessing; yet is it as farre inferiour to
peace within, as Ciuill warres are more cruell and vnnaturall then warres abroad.
And therefore the second great blessing that GOD hath with my Person sent vnto
you, is Peace within, and that in a double forme. First, by my descent lineally
out of the loynes of <hi rend="italic">Henry</hi> the seuenth, is reunited and confirmed in mee the Vnion
of the two Princely Roses of the two Houses of LANCASTER and YORKE, whereof
that King of happy memorie was the first Vniter, as he was also the first ground-
layer of the other Peace. The lamentable and miserable euents by the Ciuill and
bloody dissention betwixt these two Houses was so great and so late, as it need
not be renewed vnto your memories: which, as it was first setled and vnited in
him, so is it now reunited and confirmed in me, being iustly and lineally descended,
not onely of that happie coniunction, but of both the Branches thereof many
times before. But the Vnion of these two princely Houses, is nothing comparable
to the Vnion of two ancient and famous Kingdomes, which is the other inward
Peace annexed to my Person.
</p>
<p>And here I must craue your patiences for a little space, to giue me leaue to dis-
course more particularly of the benefits that doe arise of that Vnion which is made
in my blood, being a matter that most properly belongeth to me to speake of, as
the head wherein that great Body is vnited. And first, if we were to looke no
higher then to naturall and Physicall reasons, we may easily be perswaded of the
great benefits that by that Vnion do redound to the whole Island: for if twentie
thousand men be a strong Armie, is not the double thereof, fourtie thousand, a
double the stronger Armie ? If a Baron enricheth himselfe with double as many
lands as hee had before, is he not double the greater ? Nature teacheth vs, that
Mountaines are made of Motes, and that at the first, Kingdomes being diuided,
and euery particular Towne or little Countie, as Tyrants or Vsurpers could ob-
taine the possession, a Segniorie apart, many of these little Kingdomes are now in
processe of time, by the ordinance of God, ioyned into great Monarchies, whereby
they are become powerfull within themselues to defend themselues from all out-
ward inuasions, and their head and gouernour thereby enabled to redeeme them
from forreine assaults, and punish priuate transgressions within. Do we not yet
remember, that this Kingdome was diuided into seuen little Kingdomes, besides
Wales ? And is it not now the stronger by their vnion ? And hath not the vnion
of Wales to England added a greater strength thereto ? Which though it was a
great Principalitie, was nothing comparable in greatnesse and power to the
ancient and famous Kingdome of Scotland. But what should we sticke vpon any
naturall appearance, when it is manifest that God by his Almightie prouidence
hath preordained it so to be ? Hath not God first vnited these two Kingdomes
both in Language, Religion, and similitude of maners ? Yea, hath hee not made
vs all in one Island, compassed with one Sea, and of it selfe by nature so indiuisible,

<pb n="272"/>
as almost those that were borderers themselues on the late Borders, cannot
distinguish, nor know, or discerne their owne limits ? These two Countries being
separated neither by Sea, nor great Riuer, Mountaine, nor other strength of
nature, but onely by little small brookes, or demolished little walles, so as rather
they were diuided in apprehension, then in effect; And now in the end and ful-
nesse of time vnited, the right and title of both in my Person, alike lineally
descended of both the Crownes, whereby it is now become like a little World
within it selfe, being intrenched and fortified round about with a naturall, and
yet admirable strong pond or ditch, whereby all the former feares of this Nation
are now quite cut off: The other part of the Island being euer before now not
onely the place of landing to all strangers, that was to make inuasion here, but
likewise moued by the enemies of this State by vntimely incursions, to make
inforced diuersion from their Conquests, for defending themselues at home, and
keeping sure their backe-doore, as then it was called, which was the greatest
hinderance and let that euer my Predecessors of this Nation gat in disturbing them
from their many famous and glorious conquests abroad: What God hath con-
ioyned then, let no man separate. I am the Husband, and all the whole Isle is my
lawfull Wife; I am the Head, and it is my Body; I am the Shepherd, and it is my
flocke: I hope therefore no man will be so vnreasonable as to thinke that I that
am a Christian King vnder the Gospel, should be a Polygamist and husband to
two wiues; that I being the Head, should haue a diuided and monstrous Body;
or that being the Shepheard to so faire a Flocke (whose fold hath no wall to
hedge it but the foure Seas) should haue my Flocke parted in two. But as I am
assured, that no honest Subiect of whatsoeuer degree within any whole dominions,
is lesse glad of this ioyfull Vnion then I am; So may the friuolous obiection of any
that would bee hinderers of this worke, which God hath in my Person already
established, bee easily answered, which can be none, except such as are either
blinded with Ignorance, or els transported with Malice, being vnable to liue in a
well gouerned Commonwealth, and onely delighting to fish in troubled waters.
For if they would stand vpon their reputation and priuiledges of any of the King-
domes, I pray you was not both the Kingdomes Monarchies from the beginning,
and consequently could euer the Body bee counted without the Head, which was
euer vnseparably ioyned thereunto ? So that as Honour and Priuiledges of any
of the Kingdomes could not be diuided from their Soueraigne; So are they now
confounded &amp; ioyned in my Person, who am equall and alike kindly Head to you
both. When this Kingdome of <hi rend="italic">England</hi> was diuided into so many little King-
doms as I told you before; one of them behooued to eate vp another, till they
were all vnited in one. And yet can <hi rend="italic">Wiltshire</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Deuonshire</hi>, which were of the
<hi rend="italic">West Saxons</hi>, although their Kingdome was of longest durance, and did by Con-
quest ouercome diuers of the rest of the little Kingdomes, make claime to Prioritie
of Place or Honour before <hi rend="italic">Sussex, Essex</hi>, or other Shires which were conquered by
them ? And haue we not the like experience in the Kingdome of <hi rend="italic">France</hi>, being

<pb n="273"/>
 composed of diuers Dutchies, and one after another conquered by the sword ?
 For euen as little brookes lose their names by their running and fall into great
 Riuers, and the very name and memorie of the great Riuers swallowed vp in the
 Ocean: so by the coniunction of diuers little Kingdomes in one, are all these
 priuate differences and questions swallowed vp. And since the successe was
 happie of the <hi rend="italic">Saxons</hi> Kingdomes being conquered by the speare of <hi rend="italic">Bellona;</hi><note anchored="true" place="foot">Mars.</note>
 How much greater reason haue wee to expect a happie issue of this greater Vnion,
 which is only fastened and bound vp by the wedding Ring of <hi rend="italic">Astrea</hi> ? <note anchored="true" place="foot">Loue and Peace.</note> And as
 God hath made <hi rend="italic">Scotland</hi> the one halfe of this Isle to enioy my Birth, and the first
 and most vnperfect halfe of my life, and you heere to enioy the perfect and the
 last halfe thereof; so can I not thinke that any would be so iniurious to me, no
 not in their thoughts and wishes, as to cut asunder the one halfe of me from the
 other. But in this matter I haue farre enough insisted, resting assured that in
 your hearts and mindes you all applaud this my discourse.
</p></div>
<div subtype="subsection" type="textpart" n="3"><head>3</head>

<p>Now although these blessings before rehearsed of Inward and Outward peace,
 be great: yet seeing that in all good things, a great part of their goodnesse and
 estimation is lost, if they haue not appearance of perpetuity or long continuance;
 so hath it pleased Almighty God to accompany my person also with that fauour,
 hauing healthful and hopefull Issue of my body, whereof some are here present,
 for continuance and propagation of that vndoubted right which is in my Person;
 vnder whom I doubt not but it will please God to prosper and continue for many
 yeeres this Vnion, and all other blessings of Inward and outward Peace, which I
 haue brought with me.</p></div>
<div subtype="subsection" type="textpart" n="4"><head>4</head>

<p>Bvt neither Peace outward, nor Peace inward, nor any other blessings that
can follow thereupon, nor appearance of the perpetuitie thereof, by propagation
in the posteritie, is but a weake pillar and a rotten reed to leane vnto, if God doe
not strengthen and by the staffe of his blessing make them durable: For in
vaine doeth the Watchman watch the Citie, if the Lord be not the principall
defence thereof: In vaine doeth the builder build the house, if God giue not the
successe: And in vaine (as <hi rend="italic">Paul</hi> saith) doeth <hi rend="italic">Paul</hi> plant and <hi rend="italic">Apollo</hi> water, if God
giue not the increase: For all worldly blessings are but like swift passing shadowes,
fading flowers, or chaffe blowen before the wind, if by the profession of trew
Religion, and works according thereunto, God be not moued to maintaine and
settle the Thrones of Princes. And although that since mine entry into this
Kingdome, I haue both by meeting with diuers of the Ecclesiastical Estate, and
likewise by diuers Proclamations clearely declared my minde in points of Re-
ligion, yet doe I not thinke it amisse in this so solemne an Audience, I should now


<pb n="274"/>
take occasion to discouer somewhat of the secrets of my heart in that matter:
For I shall neuer (with Gods grace) bee ashamed to make publike profession
thereof at all occasions, lest God should bee ashamed to professe and allow mee
before men and Angels, especially lest that at this time men might presume
further vpon the misknowledge of my meaning to trouble this Parliament of ours
then were conuenient. At my first comming, although I found but one Religion,
and that which by my selfe is professed, publikely allowed, and by the Law
maintained: Yet found I another sort of Religion, besides a priuate Sect, lurking
within the bowels of this Nation. The first is the trew Religion, which by me is
professed, and by the Law is established: The second is the falsly called Catho-
likes, but trewly Papists: The third, which I call a sect rather then Religion, is
the <hi rend="italic">Puritanes</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Nouelists</hi>, who doe not so farre differ from vs in points of Re-
ligion, as in their confused forme of Policie and Paritie, being euer discontented
with the present gouernment, &amp; impatient to suffer any superiority, which maketh
their sect vnable to be suffred in any wel gouerned Commonwealth. But as for
my course toward them, I remit it to my Proclamations made vpon that Subiect.
And now for the Papists, I must put a difference betwixt mine owne priuate pro-
fession of mine owne saluation, and my politike gouernment of the Realme for
the weale and quietnes thereof. As for mine owne profession, you haue me your
Head now amongst you of the same Religion that the body is of. As I am no
stranger to you in blood, no more am I a stranger to you in Faith, or in the mat-
ters concerning the house of God. And although this my profession be according
to mine education, wherein (I thanke God) I sucked the milke of Gods trewth,
with the milke of my Nurse: yet do I here protest vnto you, that I would neuer
for such a conceit of constancy or other preiudicate opinion, haue so firmly kept
my first profession, if I had not found it agreeable to all reason, and to the rule
of my Conscience. But I was neuer violent nor vnreasonable in my profession:
I acknowledge the Romane Church to be our Mother Church, although defiled
with some infirmities and corruptions, as the Iewes were when they crucified
Christ: And as I am none enemie to the life of a sicke man, because I would haue
his bodie purged of ill humours; no more am I enemie to their Church, because I
would haue them reforme their errors, not wishing the downethrowing of the
Temple, but that it might be purged and cleansed from corruption: otherwise
how can they wish vs to enter, if their house be not first made cleane ? But as I
would be loather to dispense in the least point of mine owne Conscience for any
worldly respect, then the foolishest Precisian of them all; so would I bee as sory
to straight the politique Gouernement of the bodies and mindes of all my Sub-
iectes to my priuate opinions: Nay, my minde was euer so free from persecution,
or thralling of my Subiects in matters of Conscience, as I hope that those of that
profession within this Kingdome haue a proofe since my comming, that I was so
farre from encreasing their burdens with <hi rend="italic">Rehoboam</hi>, as I haue so much as either
time, occasion, or law could permit, lightened them. And euen now at this time

<pb n="275"/>

 haue I bene carefull to reuise and consider deepely vpon the Lawes made against
 them, that some ouerture may be proponed to the present Parliament for clearing
 these Lawes by reason (which is the soule of the Law) in case they haue bene in
 times past further, or more rigorously extended by Iudges, then the meaning of
 the Law was, or might tend to the hurt aswell of the innocent as of guiltie per-
 sons. And as to the persons of my Subiects which are of that profession, I must
 diuide them into two rankes, Clerickes and Layickes; for the part of the Layicks,
 certainely I euer thought them farre more excusable then the other sort, because
 that sort of Religion containeth such an ignorant, doubtfull, and implicit kinde
 of faith in the Layickes grounded vpon their Church, as except they doe generally
 beleeue whatsoeuer their Teachers please to affirme, they cannot be thought
 guilty of these particular points of heresies and corruptions, which their Teachers
 doe so wilfully professe. And againe I must subdiuide the same Layickes into two
 rankes, that is, either quiet and well minded men, peaceable Subiects, who either
 being old, haue retayned their first drunken in liquor vpon a certaine shamefast-
 nesse to be thought curious or changeable: Or being young men, through euil
 education haue neuer bene nursed or brought vp, but vpon such venim in place of
 wholesome nutriment. And that sort of people I would be sorry to punish their
 bodies for the errour of their minds, the reformation whereof must onely come of
 God and the trew Spirit. But the other ranke of Layicks, who either through
 Curiositie, affectation of Noueltie, or discontentment in their priuat humours,
 haue changed their coates, onely to be factious stirrers of Sedition, and Perturb-
 ers of the common wealth, their backwardnesse in their Religion giueth a ground
 to me the Magistrate, to take the better heed to their proceeding, and to correct
 their obstinacie. But for the part of the Clerickes, I must directly say and
 affirme, that as long as they maintaine one speciall point of their doctrine, and
 another point of their practise, they are no way sufferable to remaine in this
 Kingdome. Their point of doctrine is that arrogant and ambitious Supremacie
 of their Head the Pope, whereby he not onely claimes to bee Spirituall head of all
 Christians, but also to haue an Imperiall ciuill power ouer all Kings and Em-
 perors, dethroning and decrowning Princes with his foot as pleaseth him, and
 dispensing and disposing of all Kingdomes and Empires at his appetite. The
 other point which they obserue in continuall practise, is the assassinates and
 murthers of Kings, thinking it no sinne, but rather a matter of saluation, to doe
 all actions of rebellion and hostilitie against their naturall Soueraigne Lord, if he
 be once cursed, his subiects discharged of their fidelitie, and his Kingdome giuen
 a prey by that three crowned Monarch, or rather Monster their Head. And in
 this point, I haue no occasion to speake further here, sauing that I could wish
 from my heart, that. it would please God to make me one of the members of such
a generall Christian vnion in Religion, as laying wilfulnesse aside on both hands,
wee might meete in the middest, which is the Center and perfection of all things.
For if they would leaue, and be ashamed of such new and grosse Corruptions of

<pb n="276"/>
theirs, as themselues cannot maintaine, nor denie to bee worthy of reformation,
I would for mine owne part be content to meete them in the mid-way, so that all
nouelties might be renounced on either side. For as my faith is the Trew, Ancient
Catholike and Apostolike faith, grounded vpon the Scriptures and expresse word
of God: so will I euer yeeld all reuerence to antiquitie in the points of Ecclesiasti-
call pollicy; and by that meanes shall I euer with Gods grace keepe my selfe
from either being an hereticke in Faith, or schismatick in matters of Pollicie.
But of one thing would I haue the Papists of this Land to bee admonished, That
they presume not so much vpon my Lenitie (because I would be loath to be
thought a Persecuter) as thereupon to thinke it lawfull for them dayly to en-
crease their number and strength in this Kingdome, whereby if not in my time,
at least in the time of my posteritie, they might be in hope to erect their Religion
againe. No, let them assure themselues, that as I am a friend to their persons
if they be good subiects: so am I a vowed enemie, and doe denounce mortall
warre to their errors: And that as I would be sory to bee driuen by their ill
behauiour from the protection and conseruation of their bodies and liues; So
will I neuer cease as farre as I can, to tread downe their errors and wrong opinions.
For I could not permit the encrease and growing of their Religion, without first
betraying of my selfe, and mine owne conscience: Secondly, this whole Isle,
aswell the part I am come from, as the part I remaine in, in betraying their Liber-
ties, and reducing them to the former slauish yoke, which both had casten off,
before I came amongst them: And thirdly, the libertie of the Crowne in my
posteritie, which I should leaue againe vnder a new slauery, hauing found it left
free to me by my Predecessors. And therefore would I wish all good Subiects
that are deceiued with that corruption, first if they find any beginning of instinc-
tion in themselues of knowledge and loue to the Trewth, to foster the same by all
lawfull meanes, and to beware of quenching the spirit that worketh within them;
And if they can find as yet no motion tending that way, to be studious to reade
and conferre with learned men, and to vse all such meanes as may further their
Resolution, assuring themselues, that as long as they are disconformable in Re-
ligion from vs, they cannot bee but halfe my Subiects, bee able to doe but halfe
seruice, and I to want the best halfe of them, which is their soules. And here
haue I occasion to speake to you my Lords the Bishops: For as you, my Lord of
Durham, said very learnedly to day in your Sermon, Correction without instruc-
tion, is but a Tyrannie: So ought you, and all the Clergie vnder you, to be more
carefull, vigilant, and diligent then you haue bene, to winne Soules to God, aswell
by your exemplary life, as doctrine. And since you see how carefull they are,
sparing neither labour, paines, nor extreme perill of their persons to diuert, (the
Deuill is so busie a Bishop) yee should bee the more carefull and wakefull in your
charges. Follow the rule prescribed you by S. <hi rend="italic">Paul, Bee carefull to exhort and to
instruct in season, and out of season</hi>: and where you haue beene any way sluggish
before, now waken your selues vp againe with a new diligence in this point, re-

<pb n="277"/>

 mitting the successe to God, who calling them either at the second, third, tenth
 or twelfth houre, as they are alike welcome to him, so shall they bee to mee his
 Lieutenant here.
</p>
<p>The third reason of my conuening of you at this time, which conteineth such
 actions of my thankefulnesse toward you, as I may either doe, or leaue vndone,
 yet shall with Gods grace euer presse to performe all the dayes of my life: It
 consists in these two points; In making of Lawes at certaine times, which is
 onely at such times as this in Parliament; or in the carefull execution thereof at
 all other times. As for the making of them, I will thus farre faithfully promise
 vnto you, That I will euer preferre the weale of the body and of the whole Com-
 mon-wealth, in making of good Lawes and constitutions, to any particular or
 priuate ends of mine, thinking euer the wealth and weale of the Common-wealth
 to bee my greatest weale and worldly felicitie: A point wherein a lawfull King
 doeth directly differ from a Tyrant. But at this time I am onely thus farre to
 forewarne you in that point, That you beware to seeke the making of too many
 Lawes, for two especiall reasons: First, because <hi rend="italic">In corruptissima Republica
 plurimae leges</hi>; and the execution of good Lawes is farre more profitable in a
 Common-wealth, then to burden mens memories with the making of too many of
 them. And next, because the making of too many Lawes in one Parliament, will
 bring in confusion, for lacke of leisure wisely to deliberate before you conclude:
 For the Bishop said well to day, That to Deliberation would a large time be giuen,
 but to Execution a greater promptnesse was required. As for the execution of
 good Lawes, it hath bene very wisely and honourably foreseene and ordered by
 my predecessours in this Kingdome, in planting such a number of Iudges, and all
 sorts of Magistrates in conuenient places for the execution of the same: And
 therefore must I now turne mee to you that are Iudges and Magistrates vnder
 mee, as mine Eyes and Eares in this case. I can say none otherwise to you, then
 as <hi rend="italic">Ezekias</hi> the good King of Iuda said to their Iudges, <hi rend="italic">Remember that the Thrones
 that you sit on are Gods, and neither yours nor mine</hi>: And that as you must be
 answerable to mee, so must both you and I be answerable to GOD, for the due
 execution of our Offices. That place is no place for you to vtter your affections
 in, you must not there hate your foe nor loue your friend, feare the offence of the
 greater partie or pity the miserie of the meaner; yee must be blinde and not see
 distinctions of persons, handlesse, not to receiue bribes; but keepe that iust
 temper and mid-course in all your proceedings, that like a iust ballance ye may
 neither sway to the right nor left hand. Three principall qualities are required
 in you; Knowledge, Courage, and Sinceritie: that you may discerne with knowl-
 edge, execute with courage, and doe both in vpright sinceritie. And as for my
part, I doe vow and protest here in the presence of God, and of this honourable
Audience, I neuer shall be wearie, nor omit no occasion, wherein I may shew my
carefulnesse of the execution of good Lawes. And as I wish you that are Iudges
not to be weary in your Office in doing of it; so shall I neuer be wearie, with Gods
grace, to take account of you, which is properly my calling.

<pb n="278"/>
</p>
<p>And thus hauing tolde you the three causes of my conuening of this Parlia-
  ment, all three tending onely to vtter my thankefulnesse, but in diuers formes, the
  first by word, the other two by action; I doe confesse that when I haue done and
  performed all that in this Speech I haue promised, <hi rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="la">Inutilis seruus sum</foreign></hi>: Inutile,
  because the meaning of the word <hi rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="la">Inutilis</foreign></hi> in that place of Scripture is vnderstood,
  that in doing all the seruice which wee can to God, it is but our due, and wee doe
  nothing to God but that which wee are bound to doe. And in like maner, when I
  haue done all that I can for you, I doe nothing but that which I am bound to do,
  and am accomptable to God vpon the contrary: For I doe acknowledge, that the
  speciall and greatest point of difference that is betwixt a rightfull King and an
  vsurping Tyrant is in this; That whereas the proude and ambitious Tyrant doeth
  thinke his Kingdome and people are onely ordeined for satisfaction of his desires
  and vnreasonable appetites; The righteous and iust King doeth by the contrary
  acknowledge himselfe to bee ordeined for the procuring of the wealth and pros-
  peritie of his people, and that his greatest and principall worldly felicitie must
  consist in their prosperitie. If you bee rich I cannot bee poore, if you bee happy
  I cannot but bee fortunate, and I protest that your welfare shall euer be my
  greatest care and contentment: And that I am a Seruant it is most trew, that as I
  am Head and Gouernour of all the people in my Dominion who are my naturall
  vassals and Subiects, considering them in numbers and distinct Rankes; So if
  wee will take the whole People as one body and Masse, then as the Head is
  ordeined for the body and not the Body for the Head; so must a righteous King
  know himselfe to bee ordeined for his people, and not his people for him: For
  although a King and people be <hi rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="la">Relata</foreign></hi>; yet can hee be no King if he want people
  and Subiects. But there be many people in the world that lacke a Head, where-
  fore I will neuer bee ashamed to confesse it my principall Honour to bee the great
  Seruant of the Common-wealth, and euer thinke the prosperitie thereof to be my
  greatest felicitie, as I haue already said.
</p>
<p>But as it was the whole Body of thisKingdome, with an vniforme assent and
 harmonie, as I told you in the beginning of my Speech, which did so farre oblige
 me in good will and thankefulnesse of requitall by their alacritie and readinesse
 in declaring and receiuing mee to that place which God had prouided for mee,
 and not any particular persons: (for then it had not bene the body) So is my
 thankefulnesse due to the whole State. For euen as in matter of faults, <hi rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="la">Quod à
 multis peccatur, impunè peccatur</foreign></hi>: Euen so in the matter of vertuous and good
 deedes, what is done by the willing consent and harmonie of the whole body, no
 particular person can iustly claime thankes as proper to him for the same. And
 therefore I must heere make a little Apologie for my selfe, in that I could not
 satisfie the particular humours of euery person, that looked for some aduance-
 ment or reward at my hand since my entrie into this Kingdome. Three kinde of
 things were craued of mee: Aduancement to honour, Preferment to place of
Credit about my Person, and Reward in matters of land or profit. If I had

<pb n="279"/>
  bestowed Honour vpon all, no man could haue beene aduanced to Honour: for
  the degrees of Honour doe consist in perferring some aboue their fellowes. If
  euery man had the like accesse to my Priuy or Bed-chamber, then no man could
  haue it, because it cannot containe all. And if I had bestowed Lands and Re-
  wards vpon euery man, the fountaine of my liberalitie would be so exhausted and
  dried, as I would lacke meanes to bee liberall to any man. And yet was I not so
  sparing, but I may without vaunting affirme that I haue enlarged my fauour in
  all the three degrees, towards as many and more then euer King of <hi rend="italic">England</hi> did
  in so short a space: No, I rather craue your pardon that I haue beene so bounti-
  full: for if the meanes of the Crowne bee wasted, I behoued then to haue recourse
  to you my Subiects, and bee burdensome to you, which I would bee lothest to bee
  of any King aliue. For as it is trew, that as I haue already said, it was a whole
  Body which did deserue so well at my hand, and not euery particular person of
  the people: yet were there some who by reason of their Office, credit with the
  people or otherwise, tooke occasion both before, and at the time of my comming
  amongst you, to giue proofe of their loue and affection towards me. Not that I
  am any way in doubt, that if other of my Subiects had beene in their places, and
  had had the like occasion, but they would haue vttered the like good effects, (so
  generall and so great were the loue and affection of you all towards mee:) But yet
  this hauing beene performed by some speciall persons, I could not without vn-
  thankfulnesse but requite them accordingly. And therefore had I iust occasion to
  aduance some in Honour, some to places of seruice about mee, and by rewarding
  to enable some who had deserued well of mee, and were not otherwise able to
  maintaine the rankes I thought them capable of, and others who although they
  had not particularly deserued before, yet I found them capable and worthy of
  place of preferment and credit, and not able to sustaine those places for which
  I thought them fit, without my helpe. Two especiall causes moued mee to be so
  open handed: whereof the one was reasonable and honourable; but the other
  I will not bee ashamed to confesse vnto you, proceeded of mine owne infirmitie.
That which was iust and honourable, was: That being so farre beholding to the
body of the whole State, I thought I could not refuse to let runne some small
brookes out of the fountaine of my thankefulnesse to the whole, for refreshing of
particular persons that were members of that multitude. The other which pro-
ceeded out of mine owne infirmitie, was the multitude and importunitie of
Sutors. But although reason come by infusion in a maner, yet experience groweth
with time and labour: And therefore doe I not doubt, but experience in time com-
ming will both teach the particular Subiects of this Kingdome, not to be so im-
portune and vndiscreete in crauing: And mee not to be so easily and lightly
mooued, in granting that which may be harmefull to my Estate, and consequently
to the whole Kingdome.
</p>
<p>And thus hauing at length declared vnto you my minde in all the points, for
the which I called this Parliament: My conclusion shall onely now be to excuse

<pb n="280"/>

my selfe, in case you haue not found such Eloquence in my Speech, as peraduen-
ture you might haue looked for at my hands. I might, if I list, alledge the great
weight of my Affaires and my continuall businesse and distraction, that I could
neuer haue leasure to thinke vpon what I was to speake, before I came to the
place where I was to speak: And I might also alledge that my first sight of this
so famous and Honourable an Assembly, might likewise breede some impedi-
ment. But leauing these excuses, I will plainely and freely in my maner tell you
the trew cause of it, which is; That it becommeth a King, in my opinion, to vse
no other Eloquence then plainnesse and sinceritie. By plainenesse I meane, that
his Speeches should be so cleare and voyd of all ambiguitie, that they may not be
throwne, nor rent asunder in contrary sences like the old Oracles of the Pagan
gods. And by sinceritie, I vnderstand that vprightnsse and honestie which
ought to be in a Kings whole Speeches and actions: That as farre as a King is in
Honour erected aboue any of his Subiects, so farre should he striue in sinceritie
to be aboue them all, and that his tongue should be euer the trew Messenger of
his heart: and this sort of Eloquence may you euer assuredly looke for at my
hands.

<pb n="281"/>
</p>
</div>
 </div>

   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
